<?xml version="1.0"?>
<platform>
  <party>Green</party>
  <year>2012</year>
  <source>http://www.gp.org/committees/platform/2012/</source>
  <body>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Preamble</h2>
      <p>Never has our country faced as many challenges and crises as we do now. Levels of federal revenue are the lowest they have been since 1950 because of tax cuts and breaks for the very rich and for corporations. Government agencies charged with safeguarding public health and safety are operating with slashed budgets that paralyze their efforts. Jobs are being permanently relocated outside the country, while social and educational programs are being gutted. Our food, water, air, and soil are increasingly found to bear toxins and debilitating pollution. Every single level of government&#x2014;local, county, state, and federal&#x2014;is operating in the red, running up crushing amounts of debt. Many of our allies and former friends around the world are disgusted with our imperialist foreign policy, militarism, and arrogant corporate behavior. Realizing that our actions will be judged by future generations, we ask how we can draw on the best of our traditions, calling forth a spirit of ingenuity and citizen participation to achieve a free, democratic, just, and responsible society, one that actively responds to the crucial ecological challenges of our time, rather than denying them.</p>
      <p>We submit a bold vision of our
country's future, a Platform on which we stand:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Our Ten Key Values as a guide to a
    politics of vision and action,</li>
        <li>A creative, pragmatic plan for a
    prospering sustainable economy, and</li>
        <li>A call to restore and protect a
    healthy, diverse environment and to cultivate a sense of community at
    all levels, from the local to the planetary.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>We propose a vision of our common good that is advanced through an independent politics free from the control of corporations and big money, and through a democratic structure and process that empowers and reaches across lines of division to bring together our combined strengths as a people.</p>
      <p>We, the Green Party, see our political and economic progress, and our individual lives, within the context of an evolving, dynamic world.</p>
      <p>As in nature, where adaptation and diversity provide key strategies through which life flourishes, a successful political strategy is one that is diverse, adaptable to changing needs, and strong and resilient in its core values:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Participatory Democracy, rooted in
    community practice at the grassroots level and informing every
    level, from the local to the international.</li>
        <li>Social Justice and Equal
    Opportunity emphasizing personal and social responsibility,
    accountability, and an informing ethic of Nonviolence.</li>
        <li>Ecological and Economic
    Sustainability, balancing the interests of a regulated market economy
    and community-based economics with effective care for the Great
    Economy in which we are embedded: the ecosystems of the Earth.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The Green Party Platform seeks to identify the most crucial problems facing our country and offers ideas for responsible action to solve them. Looking to the future with hope and optimism, we believe we can truly correct the course of reckless, destructive governance that has allowed and encouraged the degradation of our ecological life-support systems, gutted our economy, and strained the social fabric to the point of causing material hardship for millions of Americans. Our common destiny brings us together across our nation and around the globe. We act in service to our children and the future generations of all our relations in the Earth community. We act in service to the future we are creating today.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <h2>10 Key Values</h2>
      <h3>Grassroots Democracy</h3>
      <p>Every human being deserves a say in the decisions that affect his or her life and should not be subject to the will of another. Therefore, we will work to increase public participation at every level of government and to ensure that our public representatives are fully accountable to the people who elect them. We will also work to create new types of political organizations that expand the process of participatory democracy by directly including citizens in the decision-making process.</p>
      <h3>Social Justice and Equal Opportunity</h3>
      <p>All persons should have the rights and opportunity to benefit equally from the resources afforded us by society and the environment. We must consciously confront in ourselves, our organizations and society at large, barriers such as racism and class oppression, sexism and homophobia, ageism and disability, which act to deny fair treatment and equal justice under the law.</p>
      <h3>Ecological Wisdom</h3>
      <p>Human societies must operate with the understanding that we are part of nature, not separate from nature. We must maintain an ecological balance and live within the ecological and resource limits of our communities and our planet. We support a sustainable society that utilizes resources in such a way that future generations will benefit and not suffer from the practices of our generation. To this end we must practice agriculture that replenishes the soil; move to an energy efficient economy; and live in ways that respect the integrity of natural systems.</p>
      <h3>Non-Violence</h3>
      <p>It is essential that we develop effective alternatives to society's current patterns of violence. We will work to demilitarize, and eliminate weapons of mass destruction, without being naive about the intentions of other governments. We recognize the need for self-defense and the defense of others who are in helpless situations. We promote non-violent methods to oppose practices and policies with which we disagree, and will guide our actions toward lasting personal, community and global peace.</p>
      <h3>Decentralization</h3>
      <p>Centralization of wealth and power contributes to social and economic injustice, environmental destruction, and militarization. Therefore, we support a restructuring of social, political and economic institutions away from a system that is controlled by and mostly benefits the powerful few, to a democratic, less bureaucratic system. Decision-making should, as much as possible, remain at the individual and local level, while assuring that civil rights are protected for all citizens.</p>
      <h3>Community Based Economics</h3>
      <p>Redesign our work structures to encourage employee ownership and workplace democracy. Develop new economic activities and institutions that will allow us to use our new technologies in ways that are humane, freeing, ecological and accountable, and responsive to communities. Establish some form of basic economic security, open to all. Move beyond the narrow "job ethic" to new definitions of "work," jobs" and "income" that reflect the changing economy. Restructure our patterns of income distribution to reflect the wealth created by those outside the formal monetary economy: those who take responsibility for parenting, housekeeping, home gardens, community volunteer work, etc. Restrict the size and concentrated power of corporations without discouraging superior efficiency or technological innovation.</p>
      <h3>Feminism and Gender Equity</h3>
      <p>We have inherited a social system based on male domination of politics and economics. We call for the replacement of the cultural ethics of domination and control with more cooperative ways of interacting that respect differences of opinion and gender. Human values such as equity between the sexes, interpersonal responsibility, and honesty must be developed with moral conscience. We should remember that the process that determines our decisions and actions is just as important as achieving the outcome we want.</p>
      <h3>Respect for Diversity</h3>
      <p>We believe it is important to value cultural, ethnic, racial, sexual, religious and spiritual diversity, and to promote the development of respectful relationships across these lines. We believe that the many diverse elements of society should be reflected in our organizations and decision-making bodies, and we support the leadership of people who have been traditionally closed out of leadership roles. We acknowledge and encourage respect for other life forms than our own and the preservation of biodiversity.</p>
      <h3>Personal and Global Responsibility</h3>
      <p>We encourage individuals to act to improve their personal wellbeing and, at the same time, to enhance ecological balance and social harmony. We seek to join with people and organizations around the world to foster peace, economic justice, and the health of the planet.</p>
      <h3>Future Focus And Sustainability</h3>
      <p>Our actions and policies should be motivated by long-term goals. We seek to protect valuable natural resources, safely disposing of or "unmaking" all waste we create, while developing a sustainable economics that does not depend on continual expansion for survival. We must counterbalance the drive for short-term profits by assuring that economic development, new technologies, and fiscal policies are responsible to future generations who will inherit the results of our actions. Make the quality of life, rather than open-ended economic growth, the focus of future thinking.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Democracy</h2>
      <p>Our nation was born as the first great experiment in modern democracy. We seek to rescue that heritage from the erosion of citizen participation. Moreover, we seek to dissolve the grip of the ideology, intoned by big-money interests for more than twenty years, that government is intrinsically undesirable and destructive of liberty and that elected officials should rightly "starve the beast" by slashing all spending on social program, in the name of freedom. We challenge that tactic by calling on all Americans to think deeply about the meaning of government of the people, by the people, and for the people. In a democracy, individuals come together to form structures of governance that protect and advance the common good. We the citizens are the government, and we the citizens can direct it to fulfill its finest goals and purposes. Our citizens must not permit usurpation of their authority by acts of individuals and government agencies that isolate or insulate government from their oversight and control. We, the People, have a responsibility to participate in self-government through all the means that our Constitution provides.</p>
      <p>Citizens of a democracy must have the information and ability to determine the actions of their government. Vast concentrations of wealth and power that have occurred in recent years are inherently undemocratic. The deregulation of corporate activity and the decentralization and underfunding of the regulatory structures that remain&#x2014;accompanied by the centralizing of big money&#x2014;has been a disaster for our country. The true owners of the public lands, pension funds, and the public airwaves are the American people, who today have little or no control over their pooled assets or their commonwealth.</p>
      <p>The power of civic action is an antidote to the corporate control of so much of our lawmaking and regulating. The pervasive abuse imposed by corporate power increasingly undermines our democracy, but the Green Party seeks to rekindle the democratic flame. As voting citizens, taxpayers, workers, consumers, and stakeholders, we unite to exercise our rights and, as Thomas Jefferson urged, to counteract the "excesses of the moneyed interests." Toward this end, we consider serious reform of campaign funding to be essential, as well as curbs on the influence of corporations on lawmakers and regulatory agencies.</p>
      <p>The Green Party considers American democracy to be an ongoing, unfolding project that is dynamic and creative in nature. We are committed to the strengthening of our civil society, including the many mediating institutions at the community level that have always characterized our democracy. We seek to heal the alienation and apathy that has been cultivated in the citizenry by the power brokers of the status quo. Righteous anger about the crippling of our democracy is rising in the land, and the Greens offer constructive alternatives. In addition, we seek to repair the plummeting opinion of the United States in the international community resulting from our arrogant, narcissistic foreign policy of recent years. A growing and grave imbalance between the citizens of this country and the interests that extract power from the citizens is an imminent danger to our security and national and global social stability. We strongly feel that our country should view itself as a member of the community of nations... not above it. The United States could well play a leadership role in that community but only if we become committed to an eco-social vision of peace, national self-determination, and international cooperation.</p>
      <p>Our goal is to become an important political force in this country, and to present candidates for election at every level of government.</p>
      <h3>Political Reform</h3>
      <h4>Our Position:</h4>
      <p>Greens will crack down on political corruption and strengthen the voice of the people at all levels of government.</p>
      <p>Everyone deserves the opportunity to influence the governmental decisions that affect them. But the defining characteristics of modern politics in the United States are a corrupt campaign finance system that enables corporate and wealthy elites to purchase political outcomes; and an abundance of anti-democratic electoral, ballot access and debate rules designed to minimize participation and choice.</p>
      <p>To achieve genuine citizen participation, citizens must share in the power of governing. Greens seek to bring vibrant grassroots democracy to every part of the United States.</p>
      <p>Greens seek to repair U.S. electoral system, from how elections are financed, to conducting them in more fair and representative ways, to ensuring accountability and transparency on all levels of government. In particular, Greens believe that the U.S. winner-take-all voting system is fundamentally flawed, resulting in low voter participation, little choice or competition in countless elections, and far too few women and minorities in elected office.</p>
      <p>The failure to fulfill the promise of democracy leaves millions of people in our country too discouraged to vote and others who chose to vote seemingly trapped among false and limited choices. A system that promotes full and fair representation would draw millions of people in the United States into civic life and could revive democracy in this country</p>
      <h4>Green solutions</h4>
      <h5>Electoral reform</h5>
      <ol>
        <li>Enact proportional representation voting systems for legislative seats on municipal, county, state and federal levels. Proportional representation systems provide that people are represented in the proportion their views are held in society and are based on dividing seats proportionally within multi-seat districts, compared to the standard U.S. single-seat, winner-take all districts. Forms of proportional representation include choice voting (candidate-based), party list (party-based) and mixed member voting (combines proportional representation with district representation).</li>
        <li>Enact Instant Run-off Voting (IRV) for chief executive offices like mayor, governor and president and other single-seat elections. Under IRV, voters can rank candidates in their order of preference (1,2,3, etc.) IRV ensures that the eventual winner has majority support and allows voters to express their preferences knowing that supporting their favorite candidate will not inadvertently help their least favored candidate. IRV thus frees voters from being forced to choose between the lesser of two evils, and saves money by eliminating unnecessary run-off elections.</li>
        <li>Provide full public financing of federal, state and local elections, including free and equal radio and television time on the public airwaves for all ballot-qualified candidates and parties.</li>
        <li>Prohibit corporations from spending to influence elections, preferably by constitutional amendment abolishing corporate personhood, or as a condition of receipt of a corporate charter by federal chartering of corporations.</li>
        <li>Eliminate all ballot access laws and rules that discriminate against smaller parties and independents, and otherwise place undue burden on the right of citizens to run for office.</li>
        <li>Abolish the Electoral College and provide for the direct national election of the president by Instant Runoff Voting. As a step in that direction, support National Popular Vote legislation which would guarantee the Presidency to the presidential candidate who receives the most popular votes in all 50 states (and the District of Columbia), which would take effect only when enacted, in identical form, by states possessing a majority of the electoral votes -- that is, enough electoral votes to elect a President (270 of 538).</li>
        <li>Create a new publicly-funded People's Commission on Presidential Debates, and open its presidential debates to all candidates who appear on at least as many ballots as would represent a majority of the Electoral College and who raise enough funds to otherwise qualify for general election public financing. Any candidate who refuses to participate in such debates would lose general election public financing for their candidacy. Amend federal law to remove the non-profit tax exemption status that allows corporations to fund the existing Commission on Presidential Debates and other such exclusive privately controlled debate entities.</li>
        <li>Amend the Federal Election Campaign Act to change the percentage of the presidential popular vote required for a new party's candidate to receive first time General Election public funding from 5% in the previous General Election to 1%; and change the percentage of the presidential popular vote required for a new party to receive public presidential convention funding from 5% for its candidate in the previous general election to 1%.</li>
        <li>Include the option to vote for a binding None of the Above (NOTA) on all party primary and general election ballots.</li>
        <li>Support the right to initiative, referendum and recall at all levels of government. Enact signature gathering standards that empower volunteer collection efforts and financial disclosure requirements that identify the sources of funding behind paid signature efforts.</li>
        <li>Enact a national "right to vote" law or constitutional amendment to guarantee universal, automatic, permanent voter registration, along with fail-safe voting procedures, so that eligible voters whose names are not on the voter rolls or whose information is out-of-date can correct the rolls and vote on the same day.</li>
        <li>Enact statehood for the District of Columbia. Ensure that residents of the District of Columbia have the same rights and representation as all other U.S. citizens.</li>
        <li>Restore full citizenship rights to felons upon completion of their sentence, including the right to vote and to run for elected office. Enable greater enfranchisement of overseas voters.</li>
        <li>Support strong enforcement of the Federal Voting Rights Act and, where applicable, state voting rights acts like the California Voting Rights Act.</li>
        <li>Make Election Day a national holiday and/or have weekend elections.</li>
        <li>Amend the U.S. Constitution to require that all vacancies in the U.S. Senate be filled by election rather than appointment.</li>
      </ol>
      <h5>Reducing corruption and promoting good government</h5>
      <p>a. Develop publicly-owned, open source voting equipment and deploy it across the nation to ensure high national standards, performance, transparency and accountability, and use verifiable paper ballots.</p>
      <p>b. Establish guarantees that every citizen's vote counts, and that all U.S. voting systems -- including electronic ones -- are verifiable, transparent and accurate.</p>
      <p>c. Establish a National Elections Commission with the mandate to establish minimum national election standards and uniformity, partner with state and local election officials to ensure pre-election and post-election accountability for their election plans, require nonpartisan election boards, and depoliticize and professionalize election administration across the United States.</p>
      <p>d. Establish independent and
transparent non-partisan redistricting processes to stop partisan
gerrymandering and protect minority rights and representation.</p>
      <p>e. Increase the number of polling
places, and increase the pay for poll workers.</p>
      <p>f. Strengthen "sunshine laws" to
provide citizens with all necessary information and access to their
political system.</p>
      <p>g. Ensure that all important federal,
state and local government documents are on the Internet, especially
texts of bills, searchable databases of voting records, draft
committee and conference reports, and court decisions.</p>
      <p>h. Reinvigorate the independent
investigative agencies, such as the General Accounting Office and the
inspectors general.</p>
      <p>i. In addition to allowing members of
Congress to send mail to their constituents for free, letters from
citizens to their members of Congress shall also be free.</p>
      <p>j. Enact tough new federal anti-bribery
and gratuity laws to stop corporations and the wealthy from
purchasing government action, and vigorously enforce of
anti-corruption laws by the Justice Department.</p>
      <p>k. Prohibit members of Congress,
Governors, state legislators and their staffs from accepting for
their own personal benefit any gifts of any amount from lobbyists or
the general public.</p>
      <p>l. Require outside counsel to
investigate ethics complaints against members of Congress, and
toughen punishments within the congressional ethics processes for
corruption, abuse of power and other wrongdoing.</p>
      <p>m. Replace the Federal Election
Commission with a vigorous watchdog empowered to enforce federal
campaign finance laws.</p>
      <p>n. Expand revolving-door lobbying
"cooling off" periods for members of Congress and their top staff
to at least two years.</p>
      <p>o. Allow any member of Congress to
require a floor vote on any congressional earmark, to stop wasteful
spending.</p>
      <p>p. Support the ability of cities to
establish civilian police review boards to increase understanding
between community members and police officers, provide a public forum
to air concerns on policy matters and to ensure public oversight and
accountability of their local police department. 
</p>
      <h3>B. Community</h3>
      <p>Community is the basic unit of green
politics because it is personal, value-oriented, and small enough for
each member to have an impact. Community involvement is a foundation
for public policy.</p>
      <p>     Social diversity is the wellspring
of community life where old and young, rich and poor, and people of
all races and beliefs can interact individually and learn to care for
each other, and to understand and cooperate. We emphasize a return to
local, face-to-face relationships that humans can understand and care
about.</p>
      <p>     Among Greens, our guiding
principle is to think globally and act locally. Community needs
recognize a diversity of issues, and local control recognizes a
variety of approaches to solving problems, ones that tend to be
bottom-up not top-down. Green politics does not place its faith in
paternalistic big government. Instead, Greens believe face-to-face
interactions are essential to productive and meaningful lives for all
citizens.</p>
      <p>     The Green vision includes building
communities that nurture families, generate good jobs and housing,
and provide public services; creating cities and towns that educate
children, encourage recreation, and preserve natural and cultural
resources; building local governments that protect people from
environmental hazards and crime; and motivating citizens to
participate in making decisions.</p>
      <p>     The Green vision calls for a
global community of communities that recognize our immense diversity,
respect our personal worth, and share a global perspective. We call
for an approach to politics that acknowledges our endangered planet
and habitat. Our politics responds to global crises with a new way of
seeing our shared international security.</p>
      <p>     We will conceive a new era of
international cooperation and communication that nurtures cultural
diversity, recognizes the interconnectedness between communities, and
promotes opportunities for cultural exchange and assistance.</p>
      <p>     We call for increased public
transportation, convenient playgrounds and parks for all sections of
cities and small towns, and funding to encourage diverse
neighborhoods. [See section C.Transportation in chapter III] 
</p>
      <p>     We support a rich milieu of art,
culture, and significant (yet modestly funded) programs such as the
National Endowment for the Arts and National Endowment for the
Humanities. [See section E. Education and the Arts in chapter II] 
</p>
      <p>1. Families and Children</p>
      <p>a. We call for social policies to focus
on protecting families. The young &#x2014;our citizens of
tomorrow &#x2014;are increasingly at risk. Programs must ensure that
children, who are among the most vulnerable members of society,
receive basic nutritional, educational, and medical necessities. The
Green Party supports and seeks to expand Head Start and Pre- and
neo-natal programs. A Children's Agenda should be put in place to
focus attention and concerted action on the future that is our
children. [See section A.8. Youth Rights in chapter II]</p>
      <p>b. A universal, federally funded
childcare program for pre-school and young schoolchildren should be
developed. 
</p>
      <p>c. Family assistance such as the earned
income tax credit, available to working poor families in which the
parent supports and lives with the children, should be maintained and
increased to offset regressive payroll taxes and growing inequalities
in American society. [See section E. True Cost Pricing and Tax
Fairness in chapter IV] 
</p>
      <p>d. A living family wage is vital to the
social health of communities. [See section D. Livable Income in
chapter IV] 
</p>
      <p>e. The actuarial protection of social
security is essential to the well-being of our seniors, and
maintenance of the system's integrity is an essential part of a
healthy community. We oppose privatization of social security, call
for the program to remain under the aegis of the Federal Government,
and seek to expand its effectiveness. [See section M. National Debt
in chapter IV] 
</p>
      <p>f. We support the leading-edge work of
non-profit public interest groups and those individuals breaking out
of "careerism" to pursue non-traditional careers in public
service. 
</p>
      <p>2. Alternative Community Service</p>
      <p>a. We must create new opportunities for
citizens to serve their communities through non-military community
service. Alternative community service to the military should be
encouraged. 
</p>
      <p>b. We advocate the formation of a
Civilian Conservation Corps, with national leadership and state and
local affiliates, to spearhead efforts to work on the tasks of
environmental education, restoration of damaged habitats,
reforestation, and cleaning up polluted waterways. Providing
land and resource management skills will challenge young people while
encouraging social responsibility. 
</p>
      <h3>C. Free Speech and Media Reform</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Independent, critical media are
essential to an informed and healthy democracy. 
</p>
      <p>     Citizens must have ready access to
news and information to make responsible informed choices as voters
and to carry out their other duties of citizenship.</p>
      <p>     The United States' original
communications policy was the 1st Amendment. Freedom of the press was
guaranteed in the Constitution because an exchange of ideas and an
unfettered debate were considered essential components of a
democratic society. Today, however, government policy is designed
less to enhance public deliberation than to boost the profitability
of media corporations. 
</p>
      <p>     Our media laws and rules promote
the formation of huge media conglomerates while discouraging
competing voices. As a result, the mainstream media is increasingly
cozy with the economic and political elites whom they should be
investigating. Mergers in the news industry have accelerated, further
limiting the spectrum of viewpoints in the mass media. With U.S.
media overwhelmingly owned by for-profit conglomerates and supported
by corporate advertisers, investigative journalism is in an alarming
decline.</p>
      <p>     In response, Greens will
strengthen citizens' influence over the broadcast media, break up
the dominant media conglomerates and boost the number of community
and non-profit news outlets, all to fortify the media's crucial
watchdog function and to help create a more diverse and lively
exchange of ideas in America.</p>
      <p>     Since governments too often have
an interest in controlling the flow of information, we must
constantly guard against official censorship. In our society however,
large corporations are a far more common source of censorship than
governments. Media outlets kill stories because they undermine
corporate interests; advertisers use their financial clout to squelch
negative reports; powerful businesses employ the threat of expensive
lawsuits to discourage legitimate investigations. The most frequent
form of censorship is self-censorship: journalists deciding not to
pursue certain stories that they know will be unpopular with the
advertisers.</p>
      <p>Green solutions</p>
      <p>1. Return ownership and control of the
electromagnetic spectrum to the public. We urge the public to reclaim
the airwaves. The privatization of the broadcast airwaves, one of our
most important taxpayer assets, has caused serious deformations of
our politics and culture. End the privatization of broadcast
frequencies and reserve them for the creation of new not-for-profit
community broadcasters around the country and for broadband and wifi
networks owned and operated by cities, counties and towns which want
to deliver this vital tool to their people at reasonable cost.</p>
      <p>2. Enact tough new anti-trust laws for
the media, carve up the big media conglomerates, and follow up with
vigorous anti-trust enforcement.</p>
      <p>3. End commercial broadcasters' free
licensed use of the public airwaves. Require market-priced leasing of
any commercial use of the electromagnetic spectrum. Revenues derived
from these license fees should be used to fund the operation of
community media. Tax electronic advertising to fund democratic media
outlets.</p>
      <p>4. Reinstate and strengthen the
Fairness Doctrine, to require that holders of broadcast licenses
present controversial issues of public importance in an equitable and
balanced manner.</p>
      <p>5. Establish substantial public
interest obligations for broadcasters and hold them accountable, and
revoke licenses from outlets that fail to satisfy these obligations.</p>
      <p>6. Support Public, Educational and
Governmental (PEG) Access Television to ensure that citizens and
community organizations have the opportunity to create and present
their own programming on cable television.</p>
      <p>7. Expand the role of community radio,
by expanding the licensing of new non-commercial low power FM radio
stations.</p>
      <p>8. Promote greater opportunity for
women and minority ownership of media outlets.</p>
      <p>9. Provide broadband Internet access
for all residents of this country, so that access to information is a
right, not a commodity.</p>
      <p>10. Ensure net neutrality, so that
Internet users can access any web content they choose and use any
applications they choose, without restrictions or limitations imposed
by their Internet service provider.</p>
      <p>11. Ensure free and equal airtime for
all ballot-qualified political candidates and parties on radio and
television networks and stations.</p>
      <p>12. Provide generous public funding for
Public Broadcasting System (PBS) television and National Public Radio
(NPR) to ensure high-quality news and cultural programming with the
widest possible range of viewpoints.</p>
      <p>13. Prohibit commercial advertising
targeted to children less than 12 years old, as well as advertising
in public places such as schools, parks, and government buildings.</p>
      <p>14. Oppose censorship in the arts,
media, press and on the Internet.</p>
      <p>15. Reform the Federal Communications
Commission so that it is responsive and accountable to the public at
large, not just to lobbyists and commercial interests.</p>
      <p>16. Repeal the Telecommunications Act
of 1996.</p>
      <p>17. Reduce mailing costs for non-profit
and independent magazines and journals, and eliminate them for those
that receive less than 20% of their revenues from advertising.</p>
      <p>18. Promote policies to expand
investigative reporting on federal, state and local issues.</p>
      <p>19. Promote policies to encourage the
people of the United States to watch less television, and instead to
spend time with their families, friends and neighbors, and to engage
in myriad other constructive, artistic or healthful pursuits.</p>
      <p>20. Create a publicly-controlled
"Audience Network" empowered to take airtime from commercial
television and radio stations, to broadcast a variety of
non-commercial cultural, political, entertainment, scientific or
other high-quality programs.</p>
      <h3>D. Foreign Policy</h3>
      <p>At the start of a new century, we stand
poised between the geopolitical conflict of East versus West; a
future marked by the aftermath of the catastrophic events of
September 11, 2001; the dangers of global terrorism; the U.S.-led
invasion of Afghanistan followed by the unprovoked invasion and
occupation of Iraq; the escalation of conflict in the Middle East;
and the continued research and development of nuclear weapons and the
stockpiling of bio-chemical weapons.</p>
      <p>     In the area of trade, third- and
fourth-world economies and resources are being ravaged and our own
economy and job security undermined by global corporatization, which
concentrates greater power in the hands of fewer interests who are
unaccountable to the vast majority of the world's people.</p>
      <p>     As we overcome continued conflicts
and violence, we realize the difficulties inherent in encouraging
democracy and of advancing the cause of peace. We face a more complex
set of challenges in how our nation defines its national security.
Greens support sustainable development and social and economic
justice across the globe. Reducing militarism and reliance on arms
policies is the key to progress toward collective security.</p>
      <p>1. Foreign Policy&#x2014;Peace and
Disarmament</p>
      <p>a. As one of the initiators and primary
authors of the United Nations Charter, the United States is obligated
to conform to the stipulations of the U.S. Constitution, which
identifies all such agreements as treaties that hold the authority of
U.S. law. The U.S. government is pledged to abide by its principles
and guidelines in the conduct of foreign relations and affairs. 
</p>
      <p>b. We recognize our government's
obligation to take disputes with other nations or foreign bodies to
the U.N. Security Council and General Assembly forum for negotiation
and resolution. The U.N. and international laws, treaties and
conventions that the U.S. has signed are the framework that controls
U.S. military actions abroad. 
</p>
      <p>c. The U.S. must recognize the
sovereignty of nation-states and their right of self-determination. 
</p>
      <p>d. We recognize and support the right
of the U.N. to intervene in a nation-state engaged in genocidal acts
or in its persistent violation and denial of the human rights of an
ethnic or religious group within its boundaries, and the right to
protect the victims of such acts. 
</p>
      <p>e. The U.S. is obligated to render
military assistance or service under U.N. command to enforce U.N.
Security Council resolutions. 
</p>
      <p>f. The U.S. must recognize and abide by
the authority of the U.N. General Assembly to act in a crisis
situation by passing a resolution under the Uniting for Peace
Procedure when the U.N. Security Council is stalemated by vetoes. 
</p>
      <p>g. We seek the permanent repeal of the
veto power enjoyed by the five permanent members of the U.N. Security
Council. 
</p>
      <p>h. We urge our government to sign the
International Criminal Court agreement and respect the authority
of that institution. 
</p>
      <p>i. Our government does not have the
right to justify pre-emptive invasion of another country on the
grounds that the other country harbors, trains, equips and funds a
terrorist cell. 
</p>
      <p>j. Our government should establish a
policy to abolish nuclear weapons. It should set the conditions and
schedule for fulfilling that goal by taking the following steps: 
</p>
      <p>Declare a no-first-strike policy. 
</p>
      <p>Declare a no-pre-emptive strike policy.
</p>
      <p>Declare that the U.S. will never
threaten or use a nuclear weapon, regardless of size, on a
non-nuclear nation. 
</p>
      <p>Sign the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty
(CTBT). Our pledge to end testing will open the way for non-nuclear
states to sign the Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT), which has been
held up by our refusal to sign the CTBT. Honor the conditions
set in the NPT for nuclear nations. 
</p>
      <p>Reverse our withdrawal from the
Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty and honor its stipulations. 
</p>
      <p>End the research, testing and
stockpiling of all nuclear weapons of any size. 
</p>
      <p>Dismantle all nuclear warheads from
their missiles.</p>
      <p> 
</p>
      <p>k. We urge our government to sign the
Toronto treaty banning the production, stockpiling, use and sale of
land mines, and assist other nations in unearthing and disabling land
mines buried in their lands. 
</p>
      <p>l. We urge our government to end all
stockpiling of chemical and biological weapons and all research, use,
and sale of such weapons; and sign the convention that will establish
the decrease and inspection of all nations' stockpiles of such
weapons, which the U.S. abandoned. 
</p>
      <p>m. The U.S. must allow foreign teams to
visit the U.S. for verification purposes at least annually. 
</p>
      <p>n. Our defense budget has increased out
of all proportion to any military threat to the United States, and to
our domestic social, economic and environmental needs. The United
States government must reduce our defense budget to half of its
current size. The 2005 defense budget is estimated at around $425
billion, and that does not take into account military expenditures
not placed under the defense budget. 
</p>
      <p>o. The U.S. has over 700 foreign
military bases. We urge our government to phase out all bases not
specifically functioning under a U.N. resolution to keep peace and
bring home our troops stationed abroad, except for the military
assigned to protect a U.S. embassy. Many of these bases are small and
can be closed immediately. We advocate further reductions in U.S.
foreign military bases at a rate of closure of 1/4 to 1/5 of their
numbers every year. 
</p>
      <p>p. Close the Western Hemisphere
Institute for Security Cooperation, formerly known as the School of
the Americas, in Ft. Benning, Georgia. 
</p>
      <p>q. The U.S. is the largest arms seller
and dealer in the world. We urge our government to prohibit all arms
sales to foreign nations and likewise prohibit grants to impoverished
and undemocratic nations unless the money is targeted on domestic,
non-military needs. In addition, grants to other nations may not be
used to release their own funds for military purposes. 
</p>
      <p>r. The U.S. must not be a conduit for
defense contractors to market their products abroad and must shift
our export market from arms to peaceful technology, industrial and
agricultural products, and education. 
</p>
      <p> 
</p>
      <p>s. The U.S. must prohibit all covert
actions used to influence, de-stabilize or usurp the governments of
other nations, and likewise prohibit the assassination of, or
assistance in any form for the assassination of, foreign government
officials. 
</p>
      <p>t. We must build on the Earth Charter
that came out of the 1992 U.N. environmental Earth Summit. New
definitions of what constitutes real security between nations must be
debated and adopted by the foreign policy community.</p>
      <p>2. A Real Road to Peace in the Middle
East</p>
      <p>The Green Party of the United States
recognizes that our greatest contribution to peace in the Middle East
will come through our impact on U.S. policy in the region.</p>
      <p>     Our commitments to ecological
wisdom, social justice, grass-roots democracy, and non-violence
compel us to oppose U.S. government support for "friendly"
regimes in the region when those regimes violate human rights,
international law, and existing treaties. We call on congressional
intelligence committees to conduct comprehensive public hearings on
the development and deployment of weapons of mass destruction by all
states in the region. U.S. policy should support the removal and/or
destruction of all such weapons wherever they are found there.</p>
      <p>The Palestinian-Israeli Conflict</p>
      <p>Our Green values oblige us to support
popular movements for peace and demilitarization in Israel-Palestine,
especially those that reach across the lines of conflict to engage
both Palestinians and Israelis of good will.</p>
      <p>a. We reaffirm the right of
self-determination for both Palestinians and Israelis, which
precludes the self-determination of one at the expense of the other.
We recognize the historical and contemporary cultural diversity of
Israeli-Palestinian society, including the religious heritage of
Jews, Christians, Muslims and others. This is a significant part of
the rich cultural legacy of all these peoples and it must be
respected. To ensure this, we support equality before international
law rather than appeals to religious faith as the fair basis on which
claims to the land of Palestine-Israel are resolved.</p>
      <p>b. We recognize that Jewish insecurity
and fear of non-Jews is understandable in light of Jewish history of
horrific oppression in Europe. However, we oppose as both
discriminatory and ultimately self-defeating the position that Jews
would be fundamentally threatened by the implementation of full
rights to Palestinian-Israelis and Palestinian refugees who wish to
return to their homes. As U.S. Greens, we refuse to impose our views
on the people of the region. Still, we would turn the U.S. government
towards a new policy, which itself recognizes the equality, humanity,
and civil rights of Jews, Muslims, Christians, and all others who
live in the region, and which seeks to build confidence in prospects
for secular democracy.</p>
      <p>c. We reaffirm the right and
feasibility of Palestinian refugees to return to their homes in
Israel. We acknowledge the significant challenges of equity and
restitution this policy would encounter and call on the U.S.
government to make resolution of these challenges a central goal of
our diplomacy in the region.</p>
      <p>d. We reject U.S. unbalanced financial
and military support of Israel while Israel occupies Palestinian
lands and maintains an apartheid-like system in both the Occupied
Palestinian Territories and in Israel toward its non-Jewish citizens.
Therefore, we call on the U.S. President and Congress to suspend all
military and foreign aid, including loans and grants, to Israel until
Israel withdraws from the Occupied Territories, dismantles the
separation wall in the Occupied West Bank including East Jerusalem,
ends its siege of Gaza and its apartheid-like system both within
the Occupied Palestinian Territories and in Israel toward its
non-Jewish citizens.</p>
      <p>e. We also reject U.S. political
support for Israel and demand that the U.S. government end its veto
of Security Council resolutions pertaining to Israel. We urge our
government to join with the U.N. to secure Israel's complete
withdrawal to the 1967 boundaries and its compliance with
international law.</p>
      <p>f. We support a much stronger and
supportive U.S. position with respect to all United Nations, European
Union, and Arab League initiatives that seek a negotiated peace. We
call for an immediate U.N.-sponsored, multinational peacekeeping and
protection force in the Palestinian territories with the mandate to
initiate a conflict-resolution commission.</p>
      <p>g. We call on the foreign and military
affairs committees of the U.S. House and Senate to conduct full
hearings on the status of human rights and war crimes in
Palestine-Israel, especially violations committed during Israel's
2008-2009 invasion of Gaza ("Operation Cast Lead") as documented
in the 2009 "UN Fact Finding Mission on the Gaza Conflict" ("The
Goldstone Report") authorized by the UN Commission on Human Rights.</p>
      <p>h. We recognize that despite decades of
continuous diplomatic attempts by the international community, it has
failed to bring about Israel's compliance with international law or
respect for basic Palestinian human rights; and that, despite
abundant condemnation of Israel's policies by the UN, International
Court of Justice, and all relevant international conventions, the
international community of nations has failed to stop Israeli
violations of Palestinian human rights in Israel and the OPT, while
Israeli crimes continue with impunity. We recall that ending
institutionalized racism (apartheid) in South Africa demanded an
unusual, cooperative action by the entire international community in
the form of a boycott, divestment, and sanctions (BDS) campaign
against apartheid South Africa, and that BDS can become the most
effective nonviolent means for achieving justice and genuine peace
between Palestinians and Israelis, and for the region, through
concerted international pressure as applied to apartheid South
Africa; and that Palestinian resistance to ongoing dispossession has
mainly been nonviolent, including its most basic form&#x2014;remaining
in their homes, on their land; and that while Palestinian armed
resistance is legitimate under international law when directed at
non-civilian targets, we believe that only nonviolent resistance will
maintain the humanity of Palestinian society, elicit the greatest
solidarity from others, and maximize the chance for future
reconciliation between Israelis and Palestinians. However, we also
recognize that our appeal to Palestinians to continue to resist
nonviolently in the face of ongoing existential threats from Israel
is hypocritical unless accompanied by substantial acts of
international support. We recall that in 2005, Palestinian Civil
Society appealed to the international community to support a BDS
campaign against Israel, and that in response the Green Party of the
US endorsed this BDS campaign in 2005. Therefore, we support the
implementation of boycott and divestment initiatives against Israel
similar to those applied to South Africa in the apartheid era, which
includes pressuring our government to impose embargoes and sanctions
against Israel; and we support maintaining these nonviolent punitive
measures until Israel meets its obligation to recognize the
Palestinian people's inalienable right to self-determination and
fully complies with the precepts of international law by:</p>
      <p>1. Ending its occupation and
colonization of all Palestinian lands and dismantling the Wall in the
West Bank;</p>
      <p>2. Recognizing the fundamental rights
of Palestinian citizens of Israel to full equality; and</p>
      <p>3. Respecting, protecting and promoting
the rights of Palestinian refugees to return to their homes and
properties as stipulated in UN resolution 194.</p>
      <p>i. We recognize that international
opinion has been committed to a two-state solution to the
Israeli-Palestinian conflict. Yet, we view the two-state solution as
neither democratic nor viable in the face of international law,
material conditions and "facts on the ground" that now exist in
Israel and the Occupied Palestinian Territories. Given this reality,
we support a U.S. foreign policy that promotes the creation of one
secular, democratic state for Palestinians and Israelis on the land
between the Mediterranean Sea and the River Jordan as the national
home of both peoples, with Jerusalem as its capital. We encourage a
new U.S. diplomatic initiative to begin the long process of
negotiation, laying the groundwork for such a single-state
constitution.</p>
      <p>j. We recognize that such a state might
take many forms and that the eventual model chosen must be decided by
the peoples themselves. We also acknowledge the enormous hostilities
that now exist between the two peoples, but history tells us that
these are not insurmountable among people genuinely seeking peace.</p>
      <p>k. As an integral part of peace
negotiations and the transition to peaceful democracy, we call for
the establishment of a Truth and Reconciliation Commission whose
inaugurating action would be mutual acknowledgement by Israelis and
Palestinians that they have the same basic rights, including the
right to exist in the same, secure place.</p>
      <p>3. Foreign Policy&#x2014;Trade</p>
      <p>We urge our government to do the
following:</p>
      <p>a. Re-formulate all international trade
relations and commerce as currently upheld by the North American Free
Trade Agreement (NAFTA), the World Trade Organization (WTO), the
International Monetary Fund (IMF) and World Bank (WB) to protect the
labor, human rights, economy, environment and domestic industry of
partner and recipient nations so that the growth of local industry
and agriculture has the advantage over foreign corporate domination.
The U.S. government should call for replacing the WTO, IMF, and World
Bank with new institutions that are democratic, transparent, and
accountable to the citizens of all nations.</p>
      <p>b. While the IMF and World Bank still
exist in their current forms, re-structure the rules of performance
of the IMF/WB to end the debts of recipient nations, prohibit the use
of IMF/WB loans to impose structural adjustment programs that
emphasize debt service and export-led development at the expense of
social needs, and to install strict standards in the IMF/WB that
control the use of grants or loans to prevent fraud, misuse, and
subversion of funds by recipient governments.</p>
      <p>c. Re-write the rules for investment of
corporate capital in projects operated under the IMF/WB to guarantee
the rights of the citizens of the nations receiving the investment
and their right to public ownership and control of their own
resources.</p>
      <p>d. Mandate and protect labor's right
to organize, create unions and negotiate with management in all
countries receiving U.S. investment, and require U.S. corporations
that operate in other countries to adhere to the core labor standards
established by the International Labor Organization (ILO) Declaration
of the Fundamental Principles and Rights at Work.</p>
      <p>e. Legislate and enable oversight by an
independent agency or a labor union to verify that foreign workers'
rights are protected.</p>
      <p>f. At home, secure the rights of our
states to establish stricter standards for health, safety, and for
the environment than those of our national government, and to protect
themselves against substandard, imported goods.</p>
      <p>g. Secure the right of states and
municipalities to refuse to invest in foreign businesses that do not
abide by their standards for imported goods, fair trade, and
environmental protection.</p>
      <p>h. Prohibit U.S. corporations from
avoiding or evading payment of their taxes by banking abroad or
locating their charters offshore.</p>
      <p>i. Every day over $1 trillion dollars
circles the globe in currency trade &#x2014;reaking havoc on
low-economy nations&#x2014;without obligation to sustainable
investment. We seek to restrict the unfettered flow of capital and
currency trade, and levy the Tobin tax of .05% on cross border
currency transactions. [See section E. 2. Fair Taxation in chapter
IV]</p>
      <p> j. We support the funding and
expansion of non-governmental organizations (NGOs) in their missions
to educate and train people of less developed nations in initiating
local business and economic development, and in providing health care
and family planning.</p>
      <p>k. Under the agency of the United
Nations, we demand that our government renew and initiate government
funding and support for family planning, contraception, and abortion
in all countries that request it.</p>
      <p>l. We reject the U.S. government's
economic blockade of Cuba. We ask the U.S. Congress to lift the
embargo and restore normal diplomatic relations and respect for
national sovereignty, and demand that the U.S. government end its
veto of U.N. resolutions pertaining to Cuba. 
</p>
      <p>4. Human Rights</p>
      <p>We propose the following amendment to
the Constitution of the United States:</p>
      <p>1. The rights established by this
Constitution and the laws of the United States of America are
exclusively the rights of living, breathing humans, citizens of this
country or residing therein. No corporation or other type of
association or organization can have the status of a "legal person"
and thus cannot derive rights from such status.</p>
      <p>2. These organizations have no
permanent, constitutionally protected rights, though they may have
such powers or immunities as are explicitly granted to them by
legislative actions at either the federal or the state level. These
powers or immunities may be modified or removed by later action of
the same legislative bodies. In no case can these powers or
immunities override the constitutionally protected rights of human
beings. 
</p>
      <p>5. Women's Rights</p>
      <p>a. The Green Party makes a strong and
urgent call for U.S. passage of CEDAW, the Convention on the
Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination Against Women, which was
adopted in 1979 by the UN General Assembly and ratified by 173
countries. It is also known as the Women's Convention, the Women's
Bill of Rights, and an International Bill of Rights for Women. The
United States is one of a very few countries and the only
industrialized nation that has not ratified it.</p>
      <p>b. The illegal international
trafficking in humans, primarily women, has reached staggering
numbers and consequences around the world. The Green Party supports
the UN Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking In
Persons, Especially Women and Children, which supplements the UN
Convention against Transnational Organized Crime adopted by the
UN General Assembly in November 2000 as an important tool to
facilitate international cooperation. The U.S. and 80 other countries
signed the Protocol in December 2000 and by doing so have made a
commitment to criminalize trafficking and to protect its many
victims. We call for effective collaborative relationships between
sending and receiving countries, including the U.S. We also call for
studies analyzing and connecting the role of globalization in
trafficking.</p>
      <p>6. Puerto Rican Independence</p>
      <p>In 1898, Puerto Rico was invaded by the
United States and has been held by the U.S. in the form of a colony
ever since. In response to international pressure, in 1952, the U.S.
established the "Free Associated State" status for Puerto Rico
but continued to claim that Puerto Rico belongs to, yet is not a part
of, the United States.</p>
      <p>a. Greens support the right of the
people of Puerto Rico to self-determination and independence in
conformity with United Nations Resolution 1514(XV) of 1960, the
release of all Puerto Rican political prisoners being held in U.S.
prisons, and call for the appropriate environmental clean-up and
sustainable development of Vieques and Culebra, islands that were
used as firing ranges by the U.S. military. We oppose recruitment of
the youth of Puerto Rico into the U.S. armed forces and their
deployment to U.S. wars abroad.</p>
      <h3>E. Domestic Security</h3>
      <p>Greens want to stop the assault on our
civil liberties that intensified after the attacks of September 11,
2001, and restore these and other freedoms to all people.</p>
      <p>     During the last several decades,
there has been an erosion of freedom in the United States. This has
come from many sources and takes many forms, including the war on
drugs and widespread imprisonment of nonviolent drug offenders; the
increased use of personal identification, surveillance of employees
at work, and the growing use of private security forces by
corporations; restrictions on the speech of protesters and students;
and random traffic stops of persons of color and the commonplace use
of roadblocks.</p>
      <p>     Since 9/11, this erosion has
turned into a collapse of our freedoms, as then President Bush
authorized torture, illegal wiretapping, indefinite detention without
trial, and widespread government surveillance.</p>
      <p>     Greens believe that all such
systematic degradation or elimination of our constitutional
protections must stop, and that corrective measures need to be taken
in a timely manner by Congress to fully reinstate all such losses of
guaranteed citizen protections.</p>
      <p>1. The Green Party calls for a
complete, thorough, impartial, and independent investigation of the
terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, including the role of the
administration of George W, Bush, various U.S. based corporations and
interests, and other nations and third parties. 
</p>
      <p>2. We call for the repeal of the USA
PATRIOT Act. Many of its provisions, along with many of the other
so-called National Security Acts, undermine and erode our Bill of
Rights, and contribute to the destruction of the democratic
foundation of checks and balances between the branches of government.</p>
      <p>3. Strict enforcement of our First
Amendment rights of speech, assembly, association and petition.
Federal, state and local governments must safeguard our right to
public, non-violent protest. It is intolerable that law enforcement
agencies intimidate lawful protesters with brutality, surveillance,
repression and retaliation.</p>
      <p>4. End torture, such as in prisons like
Abu Ghraib, Guantanamo Bay and other U.S.-controlled facilities.
Ensure those guilty of ordering or executing torture are held
accountable for violations U.S. and international law.</p>
      <p>5. Restore habeas corpus, a legal
action to obtain relief from illegal detention. End the use of
indefinite detention without trial.</p>
      <p>6. Revoke the 2010 re-authorization of
the Patriot Act, including "John Doe" roving wiretaps and the
"library records" provision.</p>
      <p>7. End the abuse of National Security
Letters, which the FBI uses to force Internet service providers,
libraries, banks, and credit reporting companies to reveal sensitive
information about their patrons.</p>
      <p>8. End illegal government spying,
including the use of warrantless wiretaps. Three federal judges have
ruled that President Bush's National Security Agency warrantless
wiretaps violated the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act, which
contains criminal sanctions. Ensure that anyone who violated the FISA
is held accountable for crimes committed.</p>
      <p>9. Enact a constitutional amendment
affirming that the rights outlined in our Bill of Rights are human
rights and do not apply in any way to corporations.</p>
      <p>10. Support U.S. constitutional
guarantees for freedom of religion, separation of church and state,
and that there shall be no religious test for public office.
Eliminate federal, state, and local laws that discriminate against
particular religious beliefs or non-belief. End faith-based
initiatives and charitable choice programs, whereby public funds are
used to support religious organizations that may not adhere to
specified guidelines and standards, including anti-discrimination
laws.</p>
      <p>11. Oppose the death penalty in the
United States and worldwide.</p>
      <p>12. Support students' constitutional
rights to free speech.</p>
      <p>13. Ensure that government actions
towards immigrants comply with our Constitution and universal human
rights principles.</p>
      <p>14. Support strict Fourth Amendment
protections against illegal search and seizure.</p>
      <p>F. Demilitarization and Exploration of
Space</p>
      <p>The Green Party recognizes the need for
the inspiration and education that the peaceful exploration of Space
provides; the need for space-based systems to monitor environmental
conditions on Earth; the many advances in space technology that
benefit all people on Earth; and the inspiration provided to children
by Space exploration can prompt them to pursue math, science, and
other important courses of study. 
</p>
      <p>     The peaceful exploration of Space
has been usurped by the militarization of Space. The last four
U.S.-backed military conflicts have used space-based technology to
disrupt the computer and communication systems of sovereign states.
The funds required for continuing peaceful Space exploration have
been used, instead, for the design, implementation and deployment of
wasteful and dangerous Space hardware, such as the Strategic Defense
Initiative.</p>
      <p>1. The Green Party calls for the end of
Space militarization and opposes any form of space-based military
aggression. We embrace peaceful Space exploration as a means for all
people on this planet to work together. The benefits of inspired
education are well worth the investment in peaceful Space
exploration. 
</p>
      <p>2. The Green Party supports only the
peaceful and sustainable exploration of Space, on a case-by-case,
mission-specific basis, including the signing of the International
Treaty for the Demilitarization of Space. The Green Party advocates a
reduction of human-staffed space flight due to the high cost and risk
for human life and the availability of automated technology that can
perform necessary functions in space-based research. 
</p>
      <p>II. Social Justice</p>
      <p>Historically, America led the world in
establishing a society with democratic values such as equal
opportunity and protection from discrimination. Today, however, our
country is among the most extreme examples of industrialized nations
that have a widening gap between the wealthy and the rest of its
citizenry&#x2014;the working poor, the struggling middle class, and
those who increasingly cannot make ends meet.</p>
      <p>Our public schools, from kindergarten
through college, are forced to cut back countless programs and
services. Fees for community colleges are up sharply, and many public
universities must turn away qualified students. More than 50 million
Americans have no medical insurance coverage. The crisis in publicly
subsidized housing is intensifying, while publicly funded "corporate
welfare" continues unabated. Our tax code favors the wealthy. Our
criminal justice system assigns long prison terms to hundreds of
thousands of perpetrators of victimless crimes, such as selling
marijuana. Our civil liberties of privacy and free speech are
impaired by the excesses of the USA PATRIOT Act and kindred new laws
that use a national tragedy (the attacks on September 11, 2001) as an
excuse to impose ubiquitous surveillance and control over citizens.
In addition, discrimination based on gender, ethnicity, or race
continues to sap the potential of our society and to violate personal
dignity.</p>
      <p>Feelings of isolation and helplessness
are common in America today. Children are increasingly shaped by an
"electronic childhood" with little direct experience of nature
and free play. Our families are scattered, our popular culture is
crassly manipulated by the profit motives of increasingly
concentrated media conglomerates, and our sense of community is a
pale shadow of what earlier generations of Americans knew.</p>
      <p>The Green Party strongly believes that
quality of life is determined not only by material aspects that can
be measured and counted, but also by elements that cannot be
quantified. We firmly support the separation of church and state, but
we also acknowledge the spiritual dimension of life, and we honor the
cultivation of various types of spiritual experience in our diverse
society.</p>
      <p>We believe that artistic expression and
a thriving structure of art institutions are key to community
well-being. We believe that a deep and broad embrace of nonviolence
is the only effective way to stop cycles of violence, from the home
to the streets to the international level. We advocate a diverse
system of education that would introduce children early to the
wonders of the Great School (Nature), and would cultivate the wisdom
of eco-education, eco-economics, eco-politics, and eco-culture. We
seek to protect our children from the corrosive effects of mass
culture that trains them to regard themselves first and foremost as
consumers.</p>
      <p>We support the shift in modern medicine
to include healing through complementary therapies and engagement
with the Great Hospital (Nature). We seek, in short, to facilitate
the healthy unfolding of the person within the unfolding story of the
family, community, bioregion, state, nation, and Earth community.</p>
      <h3>A. Civil Rights and Equal Rights</h3>
      <p>The foundation of any democratic
society is the guarantee that each member of society has equal
rights. Respect for our constitutionally protected rights is our best
defense against discrimination and the abuse of power. Also, we
recognize an intimate connection between our rights as individuals
and our responsibilities to our neighbors and the planet. The
Green Party shall strive to secure universal and effective
recognition and observance of the principles and spirit expressed in
the United National Universal Declaration of Human Rights as an
international standard that all nations must meet.</p>
      <p>One of our key values is
respect for diversity. We are committed to establishing relationships
that honor diversity; that support the self-definition and
self-determination of all people; and that consciously confront the
barriers of racism, sexism, homophobia, class oppression, ageism, and
the many ways our culture separates us from working together. We
support affirmative action to remedy discrimination, to protect
constitutional rights and to provide equal opportunity under the law.</p>
      <p>1. Women's Rights</p>
      <p>Since the beginning of what we call
civilization, when men's dominance over women was firmly
established, until the present day, our history has been marred with
oppression of and brutality to women. The Green Party deplores this
system of male domination, known as patriarchy, in all its forms,
both subtle and overt&#x2014;from oppression, inequality, and
discrimination to all forms of violence against women and girls
including rape, trafficking, forced sex which is also rape, slavery,
prostitution and violence against women within marriage and
relationships and in all institutions. The change the world is crying
for cannot occur unless women's voices are heard. Democracy cannot
work without equality for women, which provides equal participation
and representation. It took an extraordinary and ongoing fight over
72 years for women to win the right to vote. However, the Equal
Rights Amendment, first introduced in 1923, has still not been
ratified by 2010, representing a continuous struggle of 87 years with
no victory in sight.</p>
      <p>     We believe that equality should be
a given, and that all Greens must work toward that end. We are
committed to increasing participation of women in politics,
government and leadership so they can change laws, make decisions,
and create policy solutions that affect and will improve women's
lives, and we are building our party so that Greens can be elected to
office to do this. In July 2002 the National Women's Caucus of the
Green Party of the United States was founded to carry out the Party's
commitment to women.</p>
      <p>     We also support, and call on
others to support, the many existing and ongoing efforts for women:</p>
      <p>Social Equality</p>
      <p>a. We support the equal application of
the Constitution of the United States of America to all citizens, and
therefore call for passage of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA). We
urge accelerated ratification by three or more of the remaining 15
states that are required to pass ERA into law and into the
Constitution. We urge renewed efforts and campaigns to ratify the
ERA. We support the Equal Rights Amendment reintroduced in the U.S.
House of Representatives on July 21, 2009 as H.J.Res 61, and support
using the precedent of a three-state strategy for ratification. 
</p>
      <p>b. We call for equal representation of
women in Congress instead of the current 15% in 2010.</p>
      <p>c. The Green Party calls for U.S.
passage of CEDAW, the Convention on the Elimination of all forms of
Discrimination Against Women, which was adopted in 1979 by the U.N.
General Assembly and ratified by 173 countries. The U.S. is one of
the very few countries, and the only industrialized nation, that have
not ratified it. 
</p>
      <p>d. The Equal Employment Opportunities
Commission should actively investigate and prosecute sexual
harassment complaints. Women who file complaints must not be
persecuted and should be protected under federal and state law. We
must enshrine in law the basic principle that women have the same
rights as men, and promote gender equality and fairness in the work
force to ensure that women receive equal pay for jobs of equal worth.
</p>
      <p>e. We support the inclusion of an equal
number of women and men in peace talks and negotiations, not only
because these efforts directly affect their lives and those of their
husbands, children and families, but also because when women are
involved, the negotiations are more successful. 
</p>
      <p>Reproductive Rights</p>
      <p>f. Women's rights must be protected
and expanded to guarantee each woman's right as a full participant
in society, free from sexual harassment, job discrimination or
interference in the intensely personal choice about whether to have a
child. 
</p>
      <p>g. Women's right to control their
bodies is non-negotiable. It is essential that the option of a safe,
legal abortion remains available. The "morning-after" pill must
be affordable and easily accessible without a prescription, together
with a government-sponsored public relations campaign to educate
women about this form of contraception. Clinics must be accessible
and must offer advice on contraception and the means for
contraception; consultation about abortion and the performance of
abortions, and; abortion regardless of age or marital status. 
</p>
      <p>h. We endorse women's right to use
contraception and, when they choose, to have an abortion. This right
cannot be limited to women's age or marital status. Contraception
and abortion must be included in all health insurance policies in the
U.S., and any state government must be able to legally offer these
services free of charge to women at the poverty level. Public health
agencies operating abroad should be allowed to offer family planning,
contraception, and abortion in all countries that ask for those
services. We oppose our government's habit of cutting family
planning funds when those funds go to agencies in foreign countries
that give out contraceptive devices, offer advice on abortion, and
perform abortions.</p>
      <p>i. We encourage women and men to
prevent unwanted pregnancies. It is the inalienable right and duty of
every woman to learn about her body and to be aware of the phases of
her menstrual cycle, and it is the duty for every man to be aware of
the functions and health of his and his partner's bodies. This
information is necessary for self-determination, to make informed
decisions, and to prevent unintended consequences. Unplanned
conception takes control away from individuals and makes them subject
to external controls. The "morning-after" pill and option of a
safe and legal abortion need to remain available. 
</p>
      <p>Economic Equality</p>
      <p>j. Since, nationally, women earn only
77% of men's wages for equal work, despite outnumbering men in the
workforce and despite the U.S. 1963 Equal Pay Act, we support
intensified effort to see this unfair gap closed, including support
for the Paycheck Fairness Act now in the Senate as S.182 and similar
legislation, and greater effort at enforcement.</p>
      <p>k. Single mothers are the largest and
most severely impoverished group in the United States, which explains
why 25% of the children in our country live below the poverty line.
Welfare reform has forced mothers to abandon their children while
they travel to work at minimum wage jobs. With the extreme pay
inequity, single mothers cannot afford child care, nurture their
children, and move out of poverty. 
</p>
      <p>l. The Green Party supports real
reforms to end poverty and return dignity and opportunity to all
mothers. We call for implementing innovative programs that work with
the particular and special needs of motherhood. We also support other
programs such as a universal basic income (known also as a guaranteed
income or Citizen Dividend, as described in True Cost Pricing and Tax
Fairness) that will provide for those who nurture the next
generation&#x2014;work that is of incalculable importance to our
society.</p>
      <p>Violence and Oppression</p>
      <p>m. Language is often used as a weapon
by those with power, and women have traditionally borne the brunt of
inflicted injuries. Freedom of speech is vital to democracy. However,
we believe that this freedom should not be used to perpetuate
oppression and abuse. 
</p>
      <p>n. Violence against women is increasing
nationwide. We must address the root cause of all violence even as we
specifically address violence to women. We support stronger
legislation, programs and enforcement. We also call for new dialog
and re-thinking that can lead to better language, ideas and
solutions. We urge that the term "domestic violence" be replaced
by the term "violence," because "domestic violence" is not
perceived as real violence, which leads to it not being treated
legally and practically for the violence that it is. We urge that the
term "sex work" not be used in relation to prostitution. With the
increasing conflation of trafficking (the violent and illegal
trafficking in women and girls for forced sex) with prostitution, it
is impossible to know which is which, and what violence the term "sex
work" is masking. No source in existence knows which forms of
prostitution comprise forced sex and which comprise free will or
choice prostitution. Forced sex is rape, and it is a crime. An
increasing number of experts think the percentage of choice
prostitution is very small, leaving the larger number of women
exposed to serious and often fatal violence. Much of what is commonly
called prostitution is actually sex trafficking by definition. The
Green Party calls for a safer world for women and girls.</p>
      <p>o. The Green Party has zero tolerance
for the illegal international trafficking in humans. Of the millions
of humans trafficked worldwide, the large majority are women and
children who are bought and sold as slaves. They are kept
captive and in debt-bondage that can never be paid off. Most are sold
over and over again for forced sex prostitution. Forced sex is rape
and a serious crime. Some are forced to labor in agriculture, sweat
shops, hotels, restaurants, domestic service and other forms of
servitude. According to Human Rights Watch, in all cases coercive
tactics&#x2014;including deception, fraud, intimidation, isolation,
threat and use of physical force, or debt bondage&#x2014;are used to
control women. Estimates of human trafficking in the U.S. vary
greatly from 18,000 to 50,000 to over 100,000 with a worldwide
estimate of 12.5 million, mostly women and children.</p>
      <p>p. The Green Party calls for new U.S.
legislation relating to prostitution modeled on the Swedish law
passed in 1999, now adopted by other countries and being considered
by more, that has drastically reduced human trafficking and
prostitution in Sweden. That law criminalizes the purchase of
services from prostitutes, pimps and brothel keepers instead of
criminalizing the prostitutes. The Green Party urges the U.S. to open
dialogs and visit with Sweden as a step toward introducing
legislation in the U.S. Congress to address the exploitation,
violence and harm to women through prostitution.</p>
      <p>q. The Green Party supports all efforts
to eradicate this extreme abuse of human rights, including but not
limited to enforcement of existing laws and passage of tough new
ones, punishing traffickers, aiding victims, increasing public
awareness, reforming immigration laws, supporting existing programs
and creating new ones. 
</p>
      <p>r. We support the State Department's
annual Trafficking in Persons Report as an important document to
begin to combat this abuse. We support and urge enforcement of the
Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act (HR 3244) signed
into law on October 28, 2000. This Act authorizes funding for the
prevention of trade in human beings and for protecting victims. It
gives the State Department a historic opportunity to create an office
with the exclusive responsibility of ending traffic in humans and
protecting the victims of this worldwide trade. We urge committed
political support to achieve the cooperation of all different levels
of government. 
</p>
      <p>s. The Green Party urges a more
thorough dialog and understanding of violence against women and
girls, including from prostitution and trafficking, that causes
health and injury damage that seriously degrades their lives, even to
death or premature death including from HIV, syphilis and many other
diseases, as well as causing severe economic hardships. We call for
solutions to this enormous problem that can result in awareness and
the introduction of legislation in the U.S. Congress to address it.</p>
      <p>2. Racial Discrimination</p>
      <p>The development of the United States
has been marked by conflict over questions of race. Our nation was
formed only after Native Americans were displaced. The institution of
slavery had as its underpinnings the belief in white supremacy, which
we as Greens condemn. In slavery's aftermath, people of color have
borne the brunt of violence and discrimination. The Green Party
unequivocally condemns these evils, which continue to be a social
problem of paramount significance.</p>
      <p>a. The community of people of African
ancestry whose family members were held in chattel slavery in what is
now the United States of America have legitimate claims to
reparations including monetary compensation for centuries of human
rights violations, including the Transatlantic slave trade now
recognized by the United Nations as a "crime against humanity."
As our Nation has done in the past with respect to the Choctaw, the
Lakota, the Lambuth, and more recently for Japanese Americans and the
European Jewish community, reparations are now due to address the
debt still owed to descendants of enslaved Africans.</p>
      <p>b. We commit to full and complete
reparations to the African American community of this nation for the
past four hundred plus years of genocide, slavery, land-loss,
destruction of original identity and the stark disparities which
haunt the present evidenced in unemployment statistics, substandard
and inadequate education, higher levels of mortality including infant
and maternal mortality and the practice of mass incarceration. We
recognize that reparations are a debt (not charity) that is owed by
our own and other nations and by the corporate institutions chartered
under our laws to a collective of people. We believe that the
leadership on the question of what our nation owes to this process of
right ought to come from the African American community, whose right
to self-determination and autonomy to chart the path to healing we
fully recognize.</p>
      <p>c. We understand that until significant
steps are taken to reverse the ongoing abuses; to end the
criminalization of the Black and Brown communities, to eradicate
poverty, to invest in education, health care and the restoration
and protection of human rights, that it will be impossible to repair
the continuing damage wrought by the ideology of white supremacy
which permeates the governing institutions of our nation.</p>
      <p>d. While consensus is still evolving on
what would constitute full and complete reparations, we support the
following initial steps:</p>
      <p>i. We support the creation of a claim
of action and a right to recover inherited wealth and other profits
accumulated from the slave trade for the benefit of a reparations
trust fund.</p>
      <p>ii. We will initiate the repeal of the
slave clauses that survive today in the U.S. Constitution.</p>
      <p>iii. We will work to restore lands
stolen through a variety of tactics including: violence, terrorism
and the discriminatory access to operating capital that together has
robbed black farmers and the broader community of their lands.</p>
      <p>iv. We support the release of all
political prisoners held by the USA. It is time that the political
frame-ups, the prosecutorial misconduct and the racist application of
police power that pass for justice in our country be buried and those
victimized by these abuses of state power be given their lives back.</p>
      <p>v. We will support existing
Historically Black Colleges and Universities, as well as new and
existing Education and Development Funds.</p>
      <p>e. We support efforts to overcome the
effects of over 200 years of racial discrimination. 
</p>
      <p>f. We call for an end to official
support for any remaining symbols of slavery and specifically call
for the removal of the Confederate battle flag from all government
buildings. 
</p>
      <p>g. We condemn the practice of racial
profiling by law enforcement agencies, which are guilty of stopping
motorists, harassing individuals, or using unwarranted violence
against suspects with no other justification than race or ethnic
background. 
</p>
      <p>h. We favor strong measures to combat
official racism in the forms of police brutality directed against
people of color. 
</p>
      <p>i. We support effective enforcement of
the Voting Rights Act, including language access to voting. 
</p>
      <p>j. We oppose discriminatory
English-only pressure groups. We call for a national language policy
that would encourage all citizens to be fluent in at least two
languages. [See section K. Immigration / Emigration in this chapter] 
</p>
      <p>k. We strongly support the vigorous
enforcement of civil-rights laws, the aggressive prosecution of hate
crimes, and the strengthening of legal services for the poor. 
</p>
      <p>3. Indigenous Peoples</p>
      <p>We have great respect for Native
American cultures, especially their deference for community and the
Earth.</p>
      <p>a. We recognize both the sovereignty of
Native American tribal governments and the Federal Government's
trust obligation to Native American people. Native American nations
are just that&#x2014;nations&#x2014;and should be treated in like
fashion, with the special circumstance that they are located within
the United States. 
</p>
      <p>b. The federal government is obligated
to deal in good faith with Native Americans; honor its treaty
obligations; adequately fund programs for the betterment of tribal
governments and their people; affirm the religious rights of Native
Americans in ceremonies (American Indian Religious Freedom Act);
provide funds for innovative economic development initiatives,
education and public health programs; and respect land, water and
mineral rights within the borders of reservations and traditional
lands.</p>
      <p>c. We support efforts to broadly reform
the Bureau of Indian Affairs to make this vast agency more
responsible and more responsive to tribal governments. 
</p>
      <p>d. We support the just settlement of
the claims of the thousands of Native American uranium miners who
have suffered and died from radiation exposure. We condemn the stance
of secrecy taken by the Atomic Energy Commission during this era
and its subsequent claim of government immunity, taken knowingly and
immorally at the expense of Native people. We support the complete
clean-up of those mines and tailing piles, which are a profoundly
destructive legacy of the Cold War. 
</p>
      <p>e. Native American land and treaty
rights often stand as the front line against government and
multinational corporate attempts to plunder energy, mineral, timber,
fish, and game resources; pollute water, air, and land in the service
of the military; expand economically; and consume natural resources.
We support legal, political, and grassroots efforts by, and on behalf
of, Native Americans to protect their traditions, rights,
livelihoods, and sacred spaces. 
</p>
      <p>f. The Green Party supports the rights
of indigenous peoples to their lands, their ways of life, and all
other rights of free peoples. We support the UN Declaration on the
Rights of Indigenous Peoples adopted by the UN General Assembly on
September 13, 2007, and call for its provisions to be actively
supported by our own government and by governments worldwide.</p>
      <p>4. Justice for Native Hawaiians:

Kanaka Maoli </p>
      <p>Since illegal annexation in 1898, the
federal and state governments have cheated and neglected the native
Hawaiian people. In 1993, the U.S. Congress passed, and President
Clinton signed into law, the "Apology Bill" (U.S. Public Law
103-150). This admission of crime states in part, "the native
Hawaiians have never lost their inherent sovereignty nor their
national home base."</p>
      <p>     The Green Party demands justice
for Kanaka Maoli. We support the following:</p>
      <p>a. Protecting sacred and culturally
significant sites.</p>
      <p>b. Efforts to nurture native Hawaiian
culture.</p>
      <p>c. Kanaka maoli leadership and
guardianship in protecting gathering rights, and lobbying the
legislature to safeguard these rights without interference. 
</p>
      <p>d. Return of, or fair compensation for,
ceded lands.</p>
      <p>e. Immediate distribution of Hawaiian
Homelands, with government funds allocated for the necessary
infrastructure.</p>
      <p>f. Prohibition of future sale or
diminishments of the Ceded Land Trust. 
</p>
      <p>g. A call for open dialogue among all
residents of Hawai'i on the sovereignty option of full
independence.</p>
      <p>h. Hawaiian sovereignty in a form that
is fair to both native Hawaiians and other residents of Hawai'i. 
</p>
      <p>i. We acknowledge and actively endorse
the inherent and absolute right of indigenous nations to
self-determination, and thereby call upon the U.S. government to
reverse its opposition to enactment of the proposed United Nations
Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in its entirety. 
</p>
      <p>5. Sexual Orientation and Gender
Identity</p>
      <p>In keeping with the Green Key Values of
diversity, social justice and feminism, we support full legal and
political equality for all persons, regardless of sex, gender, sexual
orientation, or gender identity, characteristics, and expression.</p>
      <p>a. The Green Party affirms the rights
of all individuals to freely choose intimate partners, regardless of
their sex, gender, gender identity, or sexual orientation.</p>
      <p>b. The Green Party recognizes the equal
rights of persons who identify as gay, lesbian, bisexual, intersex,
transsexual, queer, or transgender to housing, jobs, civil marriage,
medical benefits, child custody, and in all areas of life including
equal tax treatment.</p>
      <p>c. The Green Party will be inclusive of
language in local, state and federal anti-discrimination law that
ensures the rights of intersex individuals and prohibits
discrimination based on gender identity, characteristics, and
expression as well as on sex, gender, or sexual orientation. We are
opposed to intersex genital mutilation.</p>
      <p>d. The Green Party affirms the right of
all persons to self-determination with regard to gender identity and
sex. We therefore support the right of intersex and transgender
individuals to be free from coercion and involuntary assignment of
gender or sex. We affirm the right of access to medical and surgical
treatment for assignment or reassignment of gender or sex, based on
informed consent.</p>
      <p>e. We will pursue legislation against
all forms of hate crimes, including those directed against people who
identify as lesbian, gay, bisexual, queer, transgender, and intersex.
Offenders must pay compensation to the LGBTIQ people who have
suffered violence and injustice.</p>
      <p>f. The Green Party will end all Federal
military and civilian aid to national governments whose laws result
in the imprisonment or otherwise bring harm to citizens and residents
based on sexual orientation, or gender identity, characteristics, and
expression.</p>
      <p>g. The Green Party will enact a policy
that the U.S. Government recognize all international marriages and
legal equivalents, such as civil unions, in processing visitor and
immigration Visas.</p>
      <p>h. The Green Party would repeal don't
ask don't tell, abolish security clearances denied on the basis of
sexual orientation and/or gender identity, and supports the rights of
defense personnel and volunteers to serve their country openly
without penalty irrespective of sex, sexual orientation, and gender
identity.</p>
      <p>i. The Green Party would end security
surveillance and covert infiltration of organizations that promote
equal rights on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity.</p>
      <p>6. Rights of the Disabled</p>
      <p>We support the full enforcement of the
Americans with Disabilities Act to enable all people with
disabilities to achieve independence and function at the highest
possible level. Government should work to ensure that children with
disabilities are provided with the same educational opportunities as
those without disabilities.</p>
      <p>     The physically and mentally
challenged are people who are differently abled from the majority,
but who are nevertheless able to live independently. The mentally ill
are people with serious mental problems who often need social support
networks. Physically and mentally challenged people have the right to
live independently in their communities. The mentally ill also have
the right to live independently, circumscribed only by the
limitations of their illness. These people are their own best
advocates in securing their rights and for living in the social and
economic mainstream.</p>
      <p>     Current Medicaid policy forces
many challenged people to live in costly state-funded institutions.
Excluding these people from society alienates them; excluding them
from the work force denies them the chance to use their potentials.</p>
      <p>     The diminishing funds available to
provide care for the growing number of the mentally ill often result
in their homelessness, vagrancy and dependence on short-term crisis
facilities. Lack of funding also increases the necessity of placing
them in long-term, locked facilities.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party urges the
government to:</p>
      <p>a. Increase rehabilitation funding so
that persons with disabilities can pursue education and training to
reach their highest potential. The differently abled should
participate fully in the allocation decisions of state rehabilitation
departments' funds.</p>
      <p>b. Aggressively implement the Americans
with Disabilities Act.</p>
      <p>c. Fund in-home support services to
allow the differently abled to hire personal care attendants while
remaining at home. 
</p>
      <p>d. Allocate adequate funding to support
community-based programs that provide out-patient medical services,
case management services and counseling programs. We should provide a
residential setting within the community for those who do not need
institutional care but who are unable to live independently.</p>
      <p>e. Make it easier for the chronically
mentally ill to apply for and receive Supplemental Security Income.</p>
      <p>f. Mainstream the differently abled.
Increase the training of teachers in regards to the needs of
differently abled students.</p>
      <p>g. Discourage stereotyping of the
mentally and physically challenged by the entertainment industry and
the media. 
</p>
      <p>h. Fund programs to increase public
sensitivity to the needs of the mentally ill and differently abled.</p>
      <p>7. Religious Freedom and Secular
Equality</p>
      <p>The United States Bill of Rights
guarantees freedom of religion. We affirm the right of each
individual to the exercise of conscience and religion, while
maintaining the constitutionally mandated separation of government
and religion. We believe that federal, state, and local governments
must remain neutral regarding religion.</p>
      <p>     We call for:</p>
      <p>a. Ending discriminatory federal,
state, and local laws against particular religious beliefs, and
non-belief. The U.S. Constitution states that there shall be no
religious test for public office. This requirement should apply to
oaths (or affirmations) for holding public office at any level,
employment at all government levels, oaths for witnesses in courts,
oaths for jury membership, and the oath for citizenship.</p>
      <p>b. Prosecution of hate crimes based on
religious affiliation or practice. 
</p>
      <p>c. Elimination of displays of religious
symbols, monuments, or statements on government buildings, property,
websites, money, or documents. 
</p>
      <p>d. Restoration of the Pledge of
Allegiance to its pre-1954 version, eliminating the politically
motivated addition of "under God."</p>
      <p>e. Ending faith-based initiatives and
charitable choice programs, whereby public funds are used to support
religious organizations that do not adhere to specified guidelines
and standards, including anti-discrimination laws. 
</p>
      <p>f. Ending school vouchers whereby
public money pays for students in religious schools.</p>
      <p>g. Ending governmental use of the
doctrines of specific religions to define the nature of family,
marriage, and the type and character of personal relationships
between consenting adults.</p>
      <p>h. Ending religiously based curricula
in government-funded public schools.</p>
      <p>i. Ending the use of religion as a
justification to deny children necessary medical care or subject them
to physical and emotional abuse.</p>
      <p>j. Ending the use of religion by
government to define the role and rights of women in our society. 
</p>
      <p>k. Revocation of the Congressional
charter of the Boy Scouts of America. Any private organization that
practices bigotry against certain religious beliefs and classes of
people should not have a Congressional endorsement or access to
public property and funds.</p>
      <p>8. Youth Rights</p>
      <p>All human beings have the right to a
life that will let them achieve their full potential. Young people
are one of the least protected classes of human beings, yet they
represent our future. We must ensure they have an upbringing that
allows them to take their place as functioning, productive, and
self-actualized members of their community.</p>
      <p>a. Youth are not the property of their
parents or guardians, but are under their care and guidance.</p>
      <p>b. Youth have the right to survive by
being provided adequate food, shelter and comprehensive health care,
including prenatal care for mothers.</p>
      <p>c. Youth have the right to be protected
from abuse, harmful drugs, violence, environmental hazards, neglect,
and exploitation. 
</p>
      <p>d. Youth have the right to develop in a
safe and nurturing early environment provided by affordable childcare
and pre-school preparation.</p>
      <p>e. Youth have the right to an education
that is stimulating, relevant, engaging, and that fosters their
natural desire to learn.</p>
      <p>f. Young people's creative potential
should be encouraged to the greatest extent possible. 
</p>
      <p>g. Young people should have input into
the direction and pace of their own education, including input into
the operation of their educational institutions.</p>
      <p>h. Young people should be provided with
education regarding their own and others' sexuality at the earliest
appropriate time.</p>
      <p>i. Young people should be provided the
opportunity to express themselves in their own media, including
television, radio, films and the Internet. Young people should also
be given skills in analyzing commercial media.</p>
      <p>j. Young people should be kept free
from coercive advertising at their educational institutions.</p>
      <p>9. GI and Veterans' Rights</p>
      <p>Support for men and women in the armed
forces must go far beyond the rhetoric used to discredit the peace
movement in the U.S. today. We believe that the ill-advised and
illegal actions of the U.S. administration have unnecessarily put our
troops in harm's way. We further believe that the dangerous burden
of fighting the unnecessary war in Iraq, and the wars that may
follow, due to the administration's overly narrow and militaristic
response to terrorism is disproportionately borne by families of
lesser means. Those who are required to carry out militaristic
policies, often with great hardship to themselves, their families,
and even the risk of their lives, deserve our respect and our
commitment to adequate compensation and benefits. Our first priority
in foreign policy considerations is to creating a future without war.
We are committed that future generations not face the separations and
sacrifices of war.</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>a. Increase the current pay levels,
including monthly combat pay, imminent danger pay and family
separation allowances for those risking their lives in combat zones.</p>
      <p>b. Provide better care for the wounded,
sick and injured soldiers. Restore full funding for veterans'
health programs. Ensure that the Pentagon takes all steps necessary
to fully diagnose and treat the physical and mental health conditions
resulting from service in combat zones, including post-traumatic
stress disorder. Support increased funding for additional clinics to
provide services which now are too often delayed or denied
throughout the Veterans Affairs system because of over crowding
and budget constraints.</p>
      <p>c. Ensure that all pre-deployment
physicals are completed within the standard allotted time period, and
that medical follow-ups are routinely given to all soldiers.</p>
      <p>d. Honor all laws concerning time
limits on deployments.</p>
      <p>e. Ensure a smooth transition from
active military service to civilian life by providing counseling,
housing, emergency management, job protection and other support
systems.</p>
      <p>f. Many of those U.S. Soldiers,
Sailors, Marines and Airmen who served during U.S. Wars in the past
two decades have been exposed to nuclear, chemical and possibly
biological warfare agents. We insist that the Veterans Administration
not ignore the suffering they have experienced since coming home from
the war. The Congress should fund and the VA should implement a
comprehensive program to survey Vets and the impacts of Gulf War
Syndrome on them and their families and to provide the best possible
medical treatment available to minimize the suffering of these men
and women and their families.</p>
      <p>g. Veterans of the U.S. wars in Iraq
and Afghanistan are being unfairly discharged from the service with
PTSD and other injuries caused by stress, trauma and head injuries,
under trumped-up behavioral charges, as a means of military budget
cost-cutting. As Greens we insist that all U.S. combatants are
entitled to medical and psychiatric health care by the VA, after
serving any time in a combat zones. Service members serving in combat
zones are subjected to assorted variations of permanent physical and
mental damage and are entitled to treatment by the Veterans
Administration. This nation has a moral obligation to provide health
care services and disability entitlements to its veterans. We support
funding for additional clinics to provide services which now are too
often delayed or denied because of over-crowding and budget
constraints throughout the VA system.</p>
      <p>h. Provide recognized, independent
veteran organizations with access to military personnel to ensure
they are being informed of their rights, including those who are
hospitalized due to service related injuries or illnesses.</p>
      <p>i. Establish a panel of independent
medical doctors to examine and oversee the military policies
regarding forced vaccinations and shots, especially with experimental
drugs. Insist that the military halt the practice of testing
experimental medicines and inoculations on service members without
their consent.</p>
      <p>j. Enact a new GI Bill, similar to the
one that began after World War II and ended in 1981, to provide
tuition grants for four years of college or other educational
opportunities, low interest loans for housing or business start-ups,
and free medical care for military personnel and their families for
ten years following separation from the armed forces.</p>
      <p>k. Support a transparent and democratic
conscientious objection process free of harassment, imprisonment, or
deployment to war zones for conscientious objectors. Defend the right
of individuals in the military service to modify or completely
separate from military involvement because of conscientious
objection. 
</p>
      <p>10. Consumer Protection</p>
      <p>The Green Party supports strong
consumer protections against fraud, dangerous products, usury,
corporate greed and rip-offs.</p>
      <p>     We believe that prevention and
justice are at the heart of consumer protection. Millions of lives
will be saved or lost depending on the strength of our consumer
protection laws. We aim to stop corporations and others from
defrauding consumers or endangering them with defective products or
negligence. We stand with consumers, who have been injured or
defrauded by corporations and others, and support their efforts to
redress the wrongs done to them. We stand with whistleblowers, who
are often the public's best protection against corporate crime,
fraud and waste.</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>a. Strengthen product safety standards
and enforcement for a variety of products, including food, motor
vehicles, pharmaceuticals and airplanes.</p>
      <p>b. Restore state health, safety, and
consumer protection laws by striking federal preemptions that weaken
state law.</p>
      <p>c. Preserve and expand product labeling
requirements to ensure that consumers are informed about the origin,
ingredients and ecological life cycle of all products, including
animal testing and the product's organic, recycled and
genetically-engineered content. Include information about the
nutritional value and the vegetarian or vegan status of food
products.</p>
      <p>d. Prohibit corporations from
concealing information about public health, labor conditions or
environmental safety via protective orders or confidential
settlements.</p>
      <p>e. Expand class action rights against
manufacturers of unsafe products and practices, and strengthen the
civil justice system and supply the resources necessary to bring to
justice to those corporations that injure innocent consumers.</p>
      <p>f. Protect whistle blowers against
demotion, job loss, and other forms of retaliation.</p>
      <p>g. Oppose "tort reform" that
undermines consumers' ability to seek redress, and "medical
malpractice reform" that relieves negligent doctors of
responsibility for injuring or killing their patients.</p>
      <p>h. Grant consumers the right to limit
collection and secondary use of personal information by any
commercial entity.</p>
      <p>i. Prohibit lenders and credit card
companies from charging more than 12% annual interest, indexed for
inflation, along with broad protections against unwarranted fees
and other abusive terms.</p>
      <p>j. Prohibit the widespread practice of
price gouging against women and the poor.</p>
      <p>k. Repeal the misnamed Bankruptcy Abuse
Prevention and Consumer Protection Act of 2005 in order to restore
Chapter 7 bankruptcy as a viable final safety net for consumers
caught by health crises, unaffordable mortgages, credit card debts
and student loans.</p>
      <p>l. Ban the use of mandatory arbitration
clauses in consumer contracts, which companies use to shunt
consumers into anti-consumer and unfair dispute resolution
processes.</p>
      <p>m. Establish new independent government
consumer advocacy agencies to protect the interests of consumers, and
restore the U.S. Office of Consumer Affairs.</p>
      <p>n. Support policies to encourage
citizens, taxpayers, ratepayers and consumers to form Citizens
Utility Boards to advocate for the public interest. 
</p>
      <h3>B. Environmental Justice</h3>
      <p>The Green Party supports a holistic
approach to justice, recognizing that environmental justice, social
justice and economic justice depend on and support each other. We
believe that no one&#x2014;including people of color and the
poor&#x2014;should be poisoned nor subjected to harmful levels of
toxic chemicals and that no group of people should bear a
disproportionate share of the pollution from industrial, governmental
and commercial sources or policies. Across the United States, the
poor and people of color do suffer disproportionately from
environmental hazards in the workplace, at home, and in their
communities. Inadequate environmental laws, lax enforcement, and weak
penalties for environmental violations undermine environmental
integrity, public health and civil rights.</p>
      <p>     Environmental justice is the
crossroads of environmental activism and the civil rights movement.
It is founded on two fundamental beliefs: that all people have the
right to live, work, learn, and play in safe and healthful
environments; and that people have the right to influence decisions
that affect environmental quality in their communities.</p>
      <p>     We believe that government must
ensure the fair treatment of people of all races, cultures, and
incomes with respect to the development, adoption, implementation,
and enforcement of environmental laws, regulations and policies. To
accomplish this, we unconditionally support implementation of the
principle of environmental justice in our practices, policies and
laws across the nation.</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>1. Make "pollution prevention" the
preferred strategy for dealing with environmental justice issues,
through eliminating environmental threats before they occur and
considering cumulative environmental impacts when evaluating risk.</p>
      <p>2. Uphold the precautionary principle,
requiring polluters to bear the burden of proof in demonstrating the
safety of their practices. Expand the application of the
precautionary principle from chemicals and health to land use, waste,
energy, food policy and local economic development.</p>
      <p>3. Expand the public trust doctrine,
which holds that government's role is to protect the commons, to
include the domains of public health and protection of the natural
environment.</p>
      <p>4. Promote programs, policies, and
legislation that build the capacity to identify disproportionate or
discriminatory siting of polluting or toxic facilities. Assure
nondiscriminatory compliance with all environmental, health and
safety laws to guarantee equal protection.</p>
      <p>5. Facilitate procedural justice,
ensuring the public's right to know. Ensure rules and regulations
are transparent to help communities employ their rights and
participate in decision-making. Provide information in languages
appropriate to the affected communities.</p>
      <p>6. Enforce corrective justice, ensuring
the rights of communities and local agencies to seek judicial
redress. Communities and local agencies must not be required to show
or prove "intent to discriminate" to achieve redress for problems
of disproportionate and/or racist environmental impacts.</p>
      <p>7. Target precautionary and corrective
justice actions and resources in communities with the highest
concentrations of environmental hazards and in communities lacking
socioeconomic resources.</p>
      <p>8. Support, enforce and strengthen the
National Environmental Policy Act. 
</p>
      <h3>C. Economic Justice / Social Safety
  Net</h3>
      <p>The passage of the 1996 Welfare Act by
Congress and its signing by the President confronts us with hard
choices. Democrats and Republicans seem to be saying the country
cannot afford to care for children and poor mothers. In ending over
fifty years of federal policy guaranteeing cash assistance for poor
children, Congress has set in motion a radical experiment that will
have a profound impact on the lives of the weakest members of our
society. How will state, city and county governments, local
communities, businesses and religious institutions&#x2014;all of
us&#x2014;respond?</p>
      <p>     We have a special
responsibility to the health and wellbeing of the young. Yet we see
the federal safety net being removed and replaced with limited and
potentially harsh state welfare programs. How will social services be
adequately provided if local resources are already stretched thin?</p>
      <p>     We believe our community
priorities must first protect the young and helpless. Yet how will
state legislatures and agencies, under pressure from more powerful
interests, react? We believe local decision-making is important, but
we realize, as we learned during the civil rights era, that strict
federal standards must guide state actions in providing basic
protections. As the richest nation in history, we should not condemn
millions of children to a life of poverty, while corporate welfare is
increased to historic highs.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party opposes the
privatization of Social Security. It is critical that the public
protections of Social Security are not privatized and subjected to
increased risk. The bottom 20% of American senior citizens get
roughly 80% of their income from Social Security, and without Social
Security, nearly 70% of black elderly and 60% of Latino elderly
households would be in poverty.</p>
      <h3>D. Welfare: A Commitment to Ending
  Poverty</h3>
      <p>An unjust society is an unsustainable
society. When communities are stressed by poverty, violence and
despair, our ability to meet the challenges of the post industrial
age are critically impaired. A holistic, future-focused perspective
on how we distribute resources in this country would consider the
effects of such distribution not just on our present needs, but on
the seventh generation to come.</p>
      <p>     It is time for a radical shift in
our attitude toward support for families, children, the poor and the
disabled. Such support must not be given grudgingly; it is the right
of those presently in need and an investment in our future. We must
take an uncompromising position that the care and nurture of
children, elders and the disabled are essential to a healthy,
peaceful, and sustainable society. We should recognize that the work
of their caregivers is of social and economic value, and reward it
accordingly. Ensuring that children and their caregivers have access
to an adequate, secure standard of living should form the cornerstone
of our economic priorities. Only then can we hope to build our future
on a foundation of healthy, educated children who are raised in an
atmosphere of love and security.</p>
      <p>a. All people have a right to food,
housing, medical care, jobs that pay a living wage, education, and
support in times of hardship.</p>
      <p>b. Work performed outside the monetary
system has inherent social and economic value, and is essential to a
healthy, sustainable economy and peaceful communities. Such work
includes: child and elder care; homemaking; voluntary community
service; continuing education; participating in government; and the
arts.</p>
      <p>c. We call for restoration of a
federally funded entitlement program to support children, families,
the unemployed, elderly and disabled, with no time limit on benefits.
This program should be funded through the existing welfare budget,
reductions in military spending and corporate subsidies, and a fair,
progressive income tax.</p>
      <p>d. We call for a graduated supplemental
income, or negative income tax, that would maintain all individual
adult incomes above the poverty level, regardless of employment or
marital status.</p>
      <p>e. We advocate reinvesting a
significant portion of the military budget into family support,
living-wage job development, and work training programs. Publicly
funded work training and education programs should have a goal of
increasing employment options at finding living-wage jobs.</p>
      <p>f. We support public funding for the
development of living-wage jobs in community and environmental
service. For example, environmental clean-up, recycling, sustainable
agriculture and food production, sustainable forest management,
repair and maintenance of public facilities, neighborhood-based
public safety, aides in schools, libraries and childcare centers, and
construction and renovation of energy-efficient housing. We oppose
enterprise zone giveaways, which benefit corporations more than
inner-city communities 
</p>
      <p>g. The accumulation of individual
wealth in the U.S. has reached grossly unbalanced proportions. It is
clear that we cannot rely on the rich to regulate their profit-making
excesses for the good of society through "trickle-down economics."
We must take aggressive steps to restore a fair distribution of
income. We support tax incentives for businesses that apply fair
employee wage distribution standards, and income tax policies that
restrict the accumulation of excessive individual wealth.</p>
      <p>h. Forcing welfare recipients to accept
jobs that pay wages below a living wage drives wages down and
exploits workers for private profit at public expense. We reject
workfare as being a form of indentured servitude.</p>
      <p>i. Corporations receiving public
subsidies must provide jobs that pay a living wage, observe basic
workers' rights, and agree to affirmative action policies. 
</p>
      <h3>E. Education and the Arts</h3>
      <p>1. Education</p>
      <p>The Green Party supports equal access
to high-quality education, and sharp increases in financial aid for
college students.</p>
      <p>     A great challenge facing the
people of the United States is to educate ourselves to build a just,
sustainable, humane and democratic future, and to become responsible
and effective citizens of the local and global communities we share.
Greens believe every child deserves a public education that fosters
critical and holistic thought, and provides the breadth and depth of
learning necessary to become an active citizen and a constructive
member of our society. We do not believe our public school system, as
it presently operates, helps us reach that goal.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party is strongly
opposed to the dissolution of public schools and the privatization of
education. We believe that the best educational experience is
guaranteed by the democratic empowerment of organized students, their
parents and communities along with organized teachers.</p>
      <p>     We must stop disinvestment in
education and instead put it at the top of our social and economic
agenda. Effective schools have sufficient resources. Too many of our
teachers are overworked, underpaid, and starved of key materials. We
also must be more generous to our schools so that our children will
learn what generosity is, and know enough to be able to be generous
to us in return.</p>
      <p>     Greens believe in education, not
indoctrination. We do not think that schools should turn our children
into servile students, employees, consumers or citizens. We believe
it is very important to teach our children how to ask good questions.</p>
      <p>     Unfortunately, we often expect too
little from our students, teachers and schools. We must teach our
children and teenagers to be leaders, and challenge them with great
works of literature, economics, philosophy, history, music, and the
arts.</p>
      <p>     We also call attention to the
results of a quarter century of corporate funding from the likes of
the Bradley and Wal-Mart Family Foundations and a decade of No Child
Left Behind&#x2014;a vast, well-endowed and lucrative sector which
seeks to dismantle, privatize, or militarize public education and
destroy teachers unions. Regimes of high-stakes standardized testing
and the wholesale diversion of resources away from public schools are
provoking crises for which the bipartisan corporate consensus
recommends school closings, dissolution of entire school districts
and replacement by unaccountable, profit-based charter schools. The
Green Party is unalterably opposed to the dissolution of public
schools and the privatization of education. 
</p>
      <p>     The Green Party views learning as
a lifelong and life-affirming process to which all people should have
access. We cannot state more forcefully our belief that in learning,
and openness to learning, we find the foundation of our Platform.</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>a. Eliminate gross inequalities in
school funding. Federal policy on education should act principally to
provide equal access to a quality education.</p>
      <p>b. Provide free college tuition to all
qualified students at public universities and vocational schools.
It's time to forgive all student and parent loans taken out to
finance post-secondary and vocational education.</p>
      <p>c. Oppose the administration of public
schools by private, for-profit entities.</p>
      <p>d. Increase funding for after-school
and daycare programs.</p>
      <p>e. Promote a diverse set of educational
opportunities, including bi-lingual education, continuing education,
job retraining, distance learning, mentoring and apprenticeship
programs.</p>
      <p>f. Give K-12 classroom teachers
professional status and salaries commensurate with advanced
education, training and responsibility.</p>
      <p>g. Teach non-violent conflict
resolution and humane education at all levels of education.</p>
      <p>h. Prohibit advertising to children in
schools. Corporations should not be allowed to use the schools as
vehicles for commercial advertising or corporate propaganda.</p>
      <p>i. Provide healthy school meals that
are rich in vitamins, minerals, protein and fiber, and offer
plant-based vegetarian options. Support Farm-to-School programs that
provide food from local family farms and educational opportunities.</p>
      <p>j. Ban the sale of soda pop and junk
food in schools. Junk food is defined as food or beverages that are
relatively high in saturated or trans fat, added sugars or salt, and
relatively low in vitamins, minerals, protein and fiber.</p>
      <p>k. Oppose military and corporate
control over the priorities and topics of university academic
research.</p>
      <p>l. Expand opportunities for universal
higher education and life-long learning.</p>
      <p>m. Make student loans available to all
college students, with forgiveness for graduates who choose public
service occupations.</p>
      <p>n. Repeal the No Child Left Behind Act.</p>
      <p>o. Include a vigorous and engrossing
civics curriculum in later elementary and secondary schools, to teach
students to be active citizens.</p>
      <p>p. Encourage parental responsibility by
supporting parenting, and increasing opportunities for parents to be
as involved as possible in their children's education. Values start
with parents. Teaching human sexuality is a parental and school
responsibility.</p>
      <p>q. Expand arts education and physical
education opportunities at school.</p>
      <p>r. Recognize the viable alternative of
home-based education.</p>
      <p>s. Oppose efforts to restrict the
teaching of scientific information and the portrayal of religious
belief as fact.</p>
      <p>t. Provide adequate academic and
vocational education and training to prisoners.</p>
      <p>u. We urge that our nation amend its
"binding declaration" with respect to the "Optional Protocol to
the Convention on the Rights of the Child on the involvement of
children in armed conflict" to join the rest of the world in
setting 18 as the absolute minimum age for military recruitment.</p>
      <p>v. No person should be permitted to
sign away eight (8) years of their life to the armed forces, without
full written disclosure of what is expected of them and what they can
expect in return from the government. We demand that the practice of
deceiving prospective service recruits about the truth of their
service contract be recognized as a fraudulent practice and
sufficient grounds for revoking an enlistment contract. Current
practices holding individuals legally to all the terms of their
military service contract should also apply to the government.</p>
      <p>w. We demand an end to the
militarization of our schools. JROTC programs are an expensive drain
on our limited educational resources and a diversion from their
important mission to prepare our young to assume their role in a
peaceful tomorrow. ASVAB testing is being used to mine public school
student bodies for data to support military recruiting. Forbid
military access to student records. The Pentagon's Recruitment
Command is misdirecting public tax dollars on manipulative
campaigns that prey on our young. We insist that local education
authorities stand up to these destructive practices.</p>
      <p>2. The Arts</p>
      <p>Freedom of artistic expression is a
fundamental right and a key element in empowering communities, and in
moving us toward sustainability and respect for diversity. Artists
can create in ways that foster healthy, non-alienating relationships
between people and their daily environments, communities, and the
Earth. This can include both artists whose themes advocate
compassion, nurturance, or cooperation; and artists whose creations
unmask the often-obscure connections between various forms of
violence, domination, and oppression, or effectively criticize
aspects of the very community that supports their artistic activity.
The arts can only perform their social function if they are
completely free from outside control.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party supports:</p>
      <p>a. Alternative, community-based systems
treating neither the artwork nor the artist as a commodity.</p>
      <p>b. Eliminating all laws that seek to
restrict or censor artistic expression, including the withholding of
government funds for political or moral content. 
</p>
      <p>c. Increased funding for the arts
appropriate to their essential social role at local, state and
federal levels of government. 
</p>
      <p>d. Community-funded programs employing
local artists to enrich their communities through public art
programs, including public performances, exhibitions, murals on
public buildings, design or re-design of parks and public areas,
storytelling and poetry reading, and publication.</p>
      <p>e. The establishment of non-profit
public forums for local artists to display their talents and
creations. Research, public dialogue, and trial experiments to
develop alternative systems for the valuation and exchange of
artworks and for the financial support of artists. Some examples
include community subscriber support groups, artwork rental busts,
cooperative support systems among artists, legal or financial
incentives to donate to the arts or to donate artworks to public
museums.</p>
      <p>f. Responsible choices of non-toxic,
renewable, or recyclable materials. Funding sources not connected
with social injustice or environmental destruction. 
</p>
      <p>g. Education programs in the community
that will energize the creativity of every community member from the
youngest to the oldest, including neglected groups such as teenagers,
senior citizens, prisoners, immigrants, and drug addicts. These
programs would provide materials and access to interested, qualified
arts educators for every member of the community who demonstrates an
interest. 
</p>
      <p>h. Funding and staffing to incorporate
arts education into every school curriculum. We encourage local
artists and the community to contribute time, experience, and
resources to these efforts. 
</p>
      <p>i. Diversity in arts education in the
schools including age-specific hands-on activities and appreciative
theoretical approaches, exposure to the arts of various cultures and
stylistic traditions, and experiences with a variety of media,
techniques and contents. 
</p>
      <p>j. The integration of the arts and
artistic teaching methods into other areas of the curriculum to
promote a holistic perspective. 
</p>
      <p>F. Health Care</p>
      <p>The Green Party supports single-payer
universal health care and preventive care for all. We believe that
health care is a right, not a privilege.</p>
      <p>     Our current health care system
lets tens of thousands of people die each year by excluding them from
adequate care, while its exorbitant costs are crippling our economy.
The United States is the only industrialized nation in the world
without a national health care system.</p>
      <p>     Under a universal, comprehensive,
national single-payer health care system, the administrative waste of
private insurance corporations would be redirected to patient care.
If the United States were to shift to a system of universal coverage
and a single payer plan, as in Canada and many European countries,
the savings in administrative costs would be more than enough to
offset the cost of additional care. Expenses for businesses currently
providing coverage would be reduced, while state and local
governments would pay less because they would receive reimbursement
for services provided to the previously uninsured, and because
public programs would cease to be the "dumping ground" for
high-risk patients and those rejected by health maintenance
organizations (HMOs) when they become disabled and unemployed. In
addition, people would gain the peace of mind in knowing that they
have health care they need. No longer would people have to worry
about the prospect of financial ruin if they become seriously ill,
are laid off their jobs, or are injured in an accident.</p>
      <p>     Greens support a wide-range of
health care services, not just traditional medicine which too often
emphasizes "a medical arms race" that relies upon high-tech
intervention, surgical techniques and costly pharmaceuticals. Chronic
conditions are often best cured by alternative medicine. We support
the teaching, funding and practice of holistic health approaches and
as appropriate, the use of complementary and alternative therapies
such as herbal medicines, homeopathy, naturopathy, traditional
Chinese medicine and other healing approaches.</p>
      <p>     Greens recognize that our own
health is also intimately tied to the health of our communities and
environment. To improve our own health, we must improve the quality
of our air, water and food and the health of our workplaces, homes
and schools.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party unequivocally
supports a woman's right to reproductive choice, no matter her
marital status or age, and that contraception and safe, legal
abortion procedures be available on demand and be included in all
health insurance coverage in the U.S., as well as free of charge in
any state where a woman's income falls below the poverty level.
[See section A.1. Women's Rights in this chapter]</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>1. Single-Payer Health Care</p>
      <p>Enact a universal, comprehensive,
national single-payer health plan that will provide the following
with no increase in cost:</p>
      <p>a. A publicly funded health care
insurance program, administered at the state and local levels, with
comprehensive lifetime benefits, including dental, vision, mental
health care, substance abuse treatment, medication coverage, and
hospice and long-term care;</p>
      <p>b. Participation of all licensed and/or
certified health providers, subject to standards of practice in
their field, with the freedom of patients to choose the type of
health care provider from a wide range of health care choices, and
with decision-making in the hands of patients and their health
providers, not insurance companies;</p>
      <p>c. Portability of coverage regardless
of geographical location or employment;</p>
      <p>d. Cost controls via streamlined
administration, national fee schedules, bulk purchases of drugs and
medical equipment, coordination of capital expenditures and publicly
negotiated prices of medications;</p>
      <p>e. Primary and preventive care as
priorities, including wellness education about diet, nutrition and
exercise; Holistic health including homeopathy, naturopathic
medicine, traditional Chinese medicine, Ayurvedic medicine, herbalism
and medical marijuana;</p>
      <p>f. More comprehensive services for
those who have special needs, including the mentally ill, the
differently abled and those who are terminally ill;</p>
      <p>g. A mental health care system that
safeguards human dignity, respects individual autonomy, and protects
informed consent;</p>
      <p>h. Greatly reduced paperwork for both
patients and providers;</p>
      <p>i. Fair and full reimbursement to
providers for their services;</p>
      <p>j. Hospitals that can afford safe and
adequate staffing levels of registered nurses;</p>
      <p>k. Establishment of national, state,
and local health policy boards consisting of health consumers and
providers to oversee and evaluate the performance of the system,
ensure access to care, and help determine research priorities; and</p>
      <p>l. Establishment of a National Health
Trust Fund that would channel all current Federal payments for health
care programs directly into the Fund, in addition to employees'
health premium payments.</p>
      <p>2. AIDS / HIV</p>
      <p>The Green Party calls for
comprehensive, humane, and competent care of all people with
AIDS/HIV.</p>
      <p>     An all-out campaign must be waged
against AIDS/ HIV and other blood-borne diseases such as hepatitis.
The AIDS epidemic has not been adequately addressed at the local,
state, federal, or international levels. All people in all countries,
including those with AIDS/HIV, have a right to medical care,
protection from discrimination, and confidentiality.</p>
      <p>     Drug corporations have a strong
profit motivation to make this disease a manageable one (like
diabetes) with guaranteed sales of very expensive drugs, in the
billions of dollars every year. Drug companies have not emphasized
research that targets a cure. While new drugs have dramatically saved
lives, many have side effects so debilitating that the quality of
life is poor, if not intolerable during the extended lifetime of the
patient. But even these need to be produced generically to stop the
devastation resulting from corporate refusal to provide these drugs
to the millions dying throughout the world who cannot afford these
basic lifesaving drugs. Drug researchers should have a cure for AIDS
as their ultimate goal.</p>
      <p>     We recommend the following
actions:</p>
      <p>a. Increased funding for AIDS education
and patient care. 
</p>
      <p>b. Increased funding for comprehensive
sex education that includes AIDS education.</p>
      <p>c. Increased funding for research
focusing on a cure, methods of prevention, and on bolstering the
immune system.</p>
      <p>d. Improved technology, facilities,
laboratories, researchers, staff and personnel to cure AIDS/HIV. A
"Manhattan Project" for a cure is required.</p>
      <p>e. Complete sharing of information
among researchers, funding agencies (including corporations), and the
public on AIDS/HIV before awarding the next research grant. 
</p>
      <p>f. More research into better methods of
prevention of HIV infection. While we support condom use, better
condoms are also required. We support more vaccine research as well
as research on prevention methods such as microbicides. People must
be provided the means and support to protect themselves from all
sexually transmitted diseases.</p>
      <p>g. Equal access to AIDS education,
treatment and medications for all affected. Accordingly, funding and
accountability should be increased.</p>
      <p>h. Allowing all prisoners affected with
AIDS/HIV in all countries to have the same access as free citizens to
education, treatment, preventive measures (including condom use), and
medical care.</p>
      <p>i. A uniform international definition
of AIDS.</p>
      <p>j. Protecting the confidentiality of
all people diagnosed with AIDS/HIV or tested for HIV.</p>
      <p>k. More careful and timely approval of
effective AIDS drugs by the FDA.</p>
      <p>l. Production of affordable and
available versions of patented medicines in all countries.</p>
      <p>m. Targeting the young for
age-appropriate education about AIDS/HIV and appropriate methods of
prevention. We support sex education and the distribution of condoms
in schools.</p>
      <p>n. Prevention awareness and access to
condoms to prevent the spread of AIDS. We condemn HIV-related
discrimination.</p>
      <p>o. Make drug treatment and other
programs available for all addicts who seek help.</p>
      <p>p. Expand clinical trials for
treatments and vaccines.</p>
      <p>q. Speed-up the FDA drug approval
process.</p>
      <p>r. Providing housing for homeless and
poor people with AIDS/HIV.</p>
      <p>s. Providing treatment for homeless
people with AIDS/ HIV. 
</p>
      <p>t. Support for needle exchange programs
and for programs to help drug addicts.</p>
      <p>u. No mandatory screening for AIDS/HIV;
anonymous screening must be available.</p>
      <p>v. Lifting the ban prohibiting HIV
positive people from entering the U.S. as visitors or as immigrants.</p>
      <h3/>
      <h3>G. Labor</h3>
      <p>The right to organize unions, bargain
freely and strike when necessary is being destroyed by employers and
their representatives in government. Today, nearly one out of ten
workers involved in union organizing drives is illegally fired by
employers who wage a campaign of fear, threats, and slick propaganda
to keep workers from exercising a genuinely free choice.</p>
      <p>     And as union membership falls, so
do the wages of all working people, union and non-union alike. We
support efforts to overcome these legal handicaps, especially in the
South and Southwest where the laws are most hostile. We also must
dedicate ourselves to fighting for a complete overhaul of this
country's labor laws.</p>
      <p>1. The Green Party supports the
irreducible right of the working people, without hindrance, to form a
union and to bargain collectively with their employer. This right was
guaranteed under the National Labor Relations Act of 1935.</p>
      <p>a. We support the right of workers,
without penalty, to inform other workers on the premises of a union
being formed. This includes advertising and recruiting.</p>
      <p>b. We support the right to organize has
been eroded and diluted over the years by incremental infringements
and restrictions, especially by the Taft-Hartley Act of 1947 passed
over President Truman's veto. We stand for repeal of the
Taft-Hartley Act. The right to organize has also been diminished by
an aggressive anti-union offensive by employers who have undermined
the law, and in many cases, brazenly violated it. To restore these
legal rights, we call for the enactment of the Employee Free Choice
Act.</p>
      <p>2. It is imperative that employees
enjoy workplace democracy, which includes the following:</p>
      <p>a. The right to elect representatives
to sit equally with management on the Board of Directors.</p>
      <p>b. The right to fair and democratic
elections of their own union officers.</p>
      <p>c. No permanent replacement of striking
workers.</p>
      <p>d. No forced overtime.</p>
      <p>e. Encourage flexible working schedules
so employees can arrange our own time to deal with personal and
family concerns</p>
      <p>f. All workers, temporary or permanent,
must be paid a living wage.</p>
      <p>g. All workers must have health care
coverage, at least half paid by employer, until the passage of
universal health care.</p>
      <p>h. All workers must have unemployment
insurance, workers' compensation, and access to a jobs search
program when they are unemployed. This security applies to farm
workers as well.</p>
      <p>i. Require minimum pensions for all
workers, fully vested and portable, that do not reduce social
security benefits.</p>
      <p>j. Mediation must be the first
available solution to labor-management disputes with an agreed-upon
time limit.</p>
      <p>k. New union members must have the
right to submit a first contract to binding arbitration at the
request of the union.</p>
      <p>l. Labor has the first right to buy out
a company that is for sale or is going bankrupt, or being outsourced
to another state or another country.</p>
      <p>m. We support a law requiring employers
who purchase or merge with other companies to honor all existing
collective bargaining agreements and contracts.</p>
      <p>o. Labor has the right to stock
ownership and oversight of the investment of its own funds in the
company where it works.</p>
      <p>3. We support the enactment of living
wage laws that apply to all workers. A major consequence of this law
will be the lessening of the ever-widening gap between CEOs' income
and workers' pay.</p>
      <p>4. Agricultural and other excluded
workers must be covered by federal labor laws, except where existing
state laws offer more protection.</p>
      <p>5. We encourage cooperative ownership
and management of enterprises.</p>
      <p>6. We support day-care service offered
at every workplace when feasible, or reasonably near-by when not
feasible at the workplace.</p>
      <p>7. Management's ability to close its
workplace and move to a lower-pay locale must be circumscribed to the
degree that it protects the local workforce and their job security.</p>
      <p>8. We support the establishment of a
reduced-hour work week and at least one month of vacation per year
for all workers.</p>
      <p>9. The ever-widening gap between rich
and poor is destructive of democracy and creates an uneven playing
field for economic opportunity. Public welfare that depends on
hand-outs from the corporate rich reduces democracy by that same
amount. Every citizen must have the leverage necessary to become a
productive member of the economy and the society in which we live.</p>
      <p>10. All workers have a right to a safe
and humane working environment. A lack of adequate enforcement of
Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) laws and/or
insufficient standards put many workers at risk. We support the
following safety policies:</p>
      <p>a. Protect and enforce OSHA laws. We
insist on adequate testing of equipment and funding of enforcement
procedures.</p>
      <p>b. Inform workers of workplace hazards.
Employers have a responsibility to protect workers from those
hazards.</p>
      <p>c. Legislate full funding for worker
safety programs at both the state and federal levels.</p>
      <p>d. Insist on agricultural practices
that don't endanger farm workers. Put agricultural practices under
the jurisdiction of OSHA.</p>
      <p>11. We stand firmly opposed to
privatization and contracting-out of public services. A government
that works for us would provide critical goods and services that
should not be run for profit. 
</p>
      <h3>H. Criminal Justice</h3>
      <p>Our position:</p>
      <p>Reduce the prison population, invest in
rehabilitation, and end the failed war on drugs.</p>
      <p>     The United States has the highest
incarceration and recidivism rates of industrialized countries, while
our nation's criminal justice system in general is too often
inhumane, ineffective, and prohibitively expensive. With less than
five percent of the world's population, the United States locks up
nearly a quarter of the world's prisoners. Our law enforcement
priorities place too much emphasis on drug-related and petty,
non-violent crimes, and not enough on prosecution of corporate, white
collar, and environmental crime. The majority of prisoners are
serving terms for non-violent, minor property and drug addiction
crimes, or violations of their conditions of parole or probation,
while the poor, the under-educated and various racial and ethnic
minorities are over-represented in the prison population.</p>
      <p>     The negative effects of
imprisonment are far-reaching. Prisoners are isolated from their
communities and often denied contact with the free world and the
media. Access to educational and legal materials is in decline.
Prison administrators wield total authority over their environments,
diminishing procedural input from experts and censoring employee
complaints.</p>
      <p>     Our priorities must include
efforts to prevent violent crime and address the legitimate needs of
victims, while addressing the socio-economic root causes of crime and
practicing policies that prevent recidivism.</p>
      <p>     Greens oppose the increasingly
widespread privatization of prisons. These prisons treat people as
their product and provide far worse service than government-run
prisons. Profits in privately run prisons are derived from
understaffing, which severely reduces the acceptable care of inmates.
Greens believe that greater, not lesser public input, oversight and
control of prisons is the answer.</p>
      <p>     Greens call for an end to the "war
on drugs", legalization of drugs and for treating drug abuse as
a health issue. The "war on drugs" has been an ill conceived
program that has wasted billions of dollars misdirecting law
enforcement resources away from apprehending and prosecuting violent
criminals, while crowding our prisons with non-violent drug offenders
and disproportionately criminalizing youth of color.</p>
      <p>     Greens also call attention to the
fact that more than forty percent of those 2.3 million locked down
come from America's black one-eighth.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party recognizes that
our nation's ostensibly color-blind systems of law enforcement and
crime control, from police practices to prosecutorial prerogatives,
to mandatory sentencing and zero-tolerance have effectively
constituted an ubiquitous national policy of racially selective mass
incarceration, a successor to Jim Crow as a means of social control,
a policy that must be publicly discussed, widely recognized, and
ultimately reversed. The nearly universal, though largely unspoken
nature of this policy makes piecemeal reforms not accompanied by
public discussion of the larger policy ineffective outside the
context of a broad social movement.</p>
      <p>Green solutions</p>
      <p>1. Alternatives to Incarceration</p>
      <p>a. Encourage and support positive
approaches to punishment that build hope, responsibility and a sense
of belonging. Prisons should be the sentence of last resort, reserved
for violent criminals. Those convicted of non-violent offenses should
be handled by alternative, community-based programs including halfway
houses, work-furlough, community service, electronic monitoring,
restitution, and rehabilitation programs.</p>
      <p>b. Treat substance abuse as a medical
problem, not a criminal problem. Free all non-violent incarcerated
prisoners of the drug war. Provide treatment to parolees and
probationers who fail a drug test instead of re-incarceration.</p>
      <p>c. Release prisoners with diagnosed
mental disorders to secure mental health treatment centers. Ensure
psychological and medical care and rehabilitation services for
mentally ill prisoners.</p>
      <p>d. Release prisoners who are too old
and/or infirm to pose a threat to society to less expensive,
community-based facilities.</p>
      <p>e. Make reduction of recidivism a
primary goal of parole. Treat parole as a time of reintegration into
the community, not as a continuation of sentence. Provide community
reentry programs for inmates before their release. Provide access to
education, addiction and psychological treatment, job training, work
and housing upon their release. Provide counseling and other services
to the members of a parolee's family, to help them with the changes
caused by the parolee's return. Prevent unwarranted search without
reasonable cause to parolees and their homes.</p>
      <p>f. Increase funding for rape and
domestic violence prevention and education programs.</p>
      <p>g. Never house juvenile offenders with
adults. House violent and non-violent juvenile offenders separately.
Continue the education of juveniles while in custody. Substantially
decrease the number of juvenile's assigned to each judge and
caseworker to oversee each juvenile's placement and progress in the
juvenile justice system.</p>
      <p>2. Prison Conditions, Prisoner
Treatment and Parolees</p>
      <p>a. Ensure prison conditions are humane
and sanitary, including but are limited to heat, light, exercise,
clothing, nutrition, libraries, possessions, and personal safety.
Meet prisoners' dietary requirements. Ensure availability of
psychological, drug, and medical treatment, including access to
condoms and uninterrupted access to all prescribed medication.
Minimize isolation of prisoners from staff and one another only as
needed for safety. Make incarceration more community-based, including
through increased visitor access by families. Establish and enforce
prison policies that discourage racism, sexism, homophobia and rape.</p>
      <p>b. Ban private prisons.</p>
      <p>c. Implement a moratorium on prison
construction. Redirect funds to alternatives to incarceration.</p>
      <p>d. Require that each state prison
system install a rehabilitation administrator with equal authority as
the highest authority.</p>
      <p>e. Ensure that all prisoners have the
opportunity to obtain a General Education Diploma (i.e. high school
equivalency diploma) and higher education. Education has proven to
reduce recidivism by 10%.</p>
      <p>f. Ensure the First Amendment rights of
prisoners, including the right to communicate with journalists, write
letters, publish their own writings, and become legal experts on
their own cases.</p>
      <p>g. Provide incarcerated individuals the
right to vote by absentee ballot in the district of their domicile,
and the right to vote during parole.</p>
      <p>h. Restore the right to hold public
office to felons who have completed their prison sentence.</p>
      <p>i. Conduct racial and ethnic disparity
impact studies for new and existing categories of offenses.</p>
      <p>3. Criminal Justice Reform</p>
      <p>a. Abolish the death penalty.</p>
      <p>b. Repeal "three strikes"
laws. Restore judicial discretion in sentencing. Abolish mandatory
sentencing.</p>
      <p>c. Establish and fund programs to
strengthen self-help and community action through neighborhood
centers that provide legal aid, alternative dispute-resolution
practices, mediated restitution, community team policing, and access
to local crisis/assault care shelters.</p>
      <p>d. Establish elected or appointed
independent civilian review boards with subpoena power to investigate
complaints about prison guard and community police behavior. Sharply
restrict police use of weapons and restraining techniques such as
pepper spray, stun belts, tasers and choke holds.</p>
      <p>e. Prohibit property forfeiture and
denial of due process for unconvicted suspects.</p>
      <p>f. Establish freedom on bail as a right
of all defendants charged with non-violent crimes. Incorporate mental
health and social services in bail agreements.</p>
      <p>g. Increase compensation for jurors and
provide childcare for those serving jury duty.</p>
      <p>h. Protect victims' rights. Ensure the
opportunity for victims to make victim-impact statements. Consider
forms of restitution to victims.</p>
      <p>4. End the War on Drugs</p>
      <p>a. End the "war on drugs."
Redirect funds presently budgeted for the "war on drugs" toward
expanded research, education, counseling and treatment.</p>
      <p>b. Amend the Controlled Substances Act
to reflect that drug use in itself is not a crime, and that persons
living in the United States arrested for using drugs should not be
incarcerated with those who have committed victim oriented crimes.</p>
      <p>c. Legalize possession of
cannabis/marijuana.</p>
      <p>d. Strike from the record prior felony
convictions for marijuana possession.</p>
      <p>e. Grant amnesty and release from
confinement without any further parole or probation, those who have
been incarcerated for the use of marijuana in federal and state
prisons and in county/city jails, and who otherwise are without
convictions for victim oriented crimes, or who do not require
treatment for abuse of hard drugs. Provide the option for drug
treatment to those leaving confinement.</p>
      <p>f. Implement a step-by-step program to
decriminalize all drugs in the United States. 
</p>
      <h3>I. Population</h3>
      <p>Humans have a unique responsibility for
stewardship of the Earth. No species, especially on the upper end of
the food chain, can have unchecked exponential growth without
depleting the Earth's carrying capacity&#x2014;human population
expands at the expense of other species.</p>
      <p>     Limiting the discussion to
population numbers and birthrates diverts attention from
over-consumption in the industrial world and historic patterns of
exploitation of developing countries. Consumption-oriented lifestyles
that have evolved in the industrial world have resulted in a minority
of people consuming a majority of resources. This is as significant a
threat to the Earth's carrying capacity as the high birth rates in
low-consumption countries.</p>
      <p>     Current global demographics
demonstrate that economic wellbeing promotes low birthrates. Any
discussion of population must also be a discussion of women
throughout the world. There is documented evidence that the economic
and social status of women is a primary factor in birthrates - when
women have control over their lives, birthrates decrease. Also, a
major barrier to the improvement of women's reproductive health is
a lack of shared responsibility between men and women in family
planning. A combination of male attitudes and cultural traditions
have resulted in most men being under-educated and uninvolved in the
planning of their families.</p>
      <p>     Globally, human population is
increasing while food production has leveled off. When population
increases faster than the economy grows, the disparity between rich
and poor also increases. Higher human consumption rates and
populations increase the pressure on the environment in every
ecological problem area.</p>
      <p>1. Those living in the industrialized
world must end the habits of waste and over-consumption that place as
much stress on the environment as does population growth in
developing nations.</p>
      <p>2. We must remove the political and
economic barriers that prevent women around the world from having all
the resources necessary to become skilled family planners.</p>
      <p>3. Funds must be allocated for expanded
scientific research into safer and more effective birth control
techniques and devices. We demand better-than-adequate health care
for women and children&#x2014;especially prenatal care. [See section
D. Foreign Policy in chapter I and section A.1. Women's Rights in
this chapter]</p>
      <p>4. There must be access to free birth
control devices, information counseling, and clinics to all who
desire them. We call for implementation of family planning education
for both genders in all levels of the state school system. [See
section D. Foreign Policy in chapter I and section A.1. Women's
Rights in this chapter]</p>
      <p>5. We must promote new traditions and
images of men becoming fully involved in all aspects of the family
planning process. 
</p>
      <h3/>
      <h3>J. Immigration / Emigration</h3>
      <p>Immigration and particularly the large
number of undocumented immigrants in the U.S. has become a hot
political issue. Laws to oppress immigrants have been proposed in the
Congress. Millions of immigrants and supporters of justice for
immigrants have marched in the streets. Politicians have stirred up
anti-immigrant sentiment among sections of the U.S. population.</p>
      <p>     It also must be acknowledged that
the trigger for such an influx of immigrants in this country has been
largely due to unfair US trade policies. If it were economically
possible to provide for their families many would choose to remain in
their native countries. Any immigration policy should be seen a way
to address all people's humanitarian needs as we undo the damage to
local communities and chart a course toward sustainable local
economies.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party stands firmly for
social justice for all those living in this country regardless of
their immigration status. Above all, policy and law must be humane.
Anything less would be inconsistent with our Green Values, and with
our nation's values.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party accepts as a goal
a world in which persons can freely choose to live in and work in any
county he or she desires. We recognize that this would be impractical
without reciprocity between nations. We seek that reciprocity as a
practical goal. Countries do have a right to know the identity of
persons seeking to enter. They also have the right to limit who can
come in to protect public safety.</p>
      <p>     The U.S. needs a complete overhaul
of its immigration laws. Our current situation has created extreme
social injustice. Millions of people are living and working in the
U.S. with no legal status, making them subject to extreme
exploitation and abuse. Immigration raids are terrorizing the
immigrant community. Families are being broken up. Employer abuses of
undocumented workers are rampant.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party must consider
immigration issues from an international standpoint, taking into
account international labor and environmental standards, and human
rights.</p>
      <p>     The following proposals may not
yield perfect answers, but they provide better answers than the
status quo. We must recognize that there cannot be any true solutions
to the conflicts created by immigration until we are able to organize
globally to overcome the power of multinational corporations, which
are engaged in an unending campaign to drive down workers' living
standards everywhere. International cooperation and solidarity among
labor organizations, to advance the rights of labor and raise such
living standards globally, are essential to combat this trend. Until
the power of the multinationals is curbed, we will continue to be
confronted with seemingly "no win" choices.</p>
      <p>     While working toward that goal, we
propose the following immigration policies, consistent with the Ten
Key Values.</p>
      <p>1. Policy Reform</p>
      <p>The undocumented immigrants who are
already residing and working in the United States, and their
families, should be granted a legal status which includes the chance
to become U.S. citizens. Persons should be excluded from this process
only if they present a clear and present danger to other members of
our society. The level of fees required for this process should not
be a burden on low-income workers. In any path to citizenship created
to provide an orderly and appropriate resolution of the status of
persons currently in the United States without proper documentation,
we demand a recognition of past, uncredited payments into the Social
Security System as part of any fees assessed for regularization of
status. In regard to who should have a right to come and live and
work in the U.S. we believe the following policies are fair:</p>
      <p>a. The Green Party calls for permanent
border passes to all citizens of Mexico and Canada whose identity can
be traced and verified. The "matricula consular" should be
accepted as one means of proving one's identity. Work permits for
citizens of Mexico and Canada must be easily obtainable, thereby
decriminalizing the act of gainful employment. This action would help
eliminate exploitation of undocumented persons by criminals engaged
in human contraband (coyotes) and unethical employers. It would also
help ensure that taxes will be paid in each corresponding nation per
its laws. These measures will also help temporary residents from
Mexico and Canada to secure driving privileges and liability
insurance.</p>
      <p>b. All persons fleeing political,
racial, religious, or other types of persecution must be welcomed and
given permanent resident status. The history of arbitrary denial of
political asylum claims must be ended. Particular attention should be
given to those minorities who are political exiles and refugees and
those whose lives would be at risk if asylum is not granted.</p>
      <p>c. Family reunification must be a
priority in accepting applications for permanent residency. The years
of waiting that families are currently put through must be ended.</p>
      <p>d. Permanent residency should not be
denied based on political views, racial or national origin, religious
beliefs, sexual orientation, disability, or any other arbitrary
basis.</p>
      <p>e. There are many countries in the
world where the economic policies and military actions of the U.S.
government or U.S. based corporations have caused extreme hardships.
The peoples of these countries deserve special consideration if they
wish to come to the U.S. to escape intolerable conditions created by
our government or U.S. corporations.</p>
      <p>f. We must keep faith with our
commitment to the United Nations, to assist in the resettlement,
including to our own country, of refugees currently stranded in
refugee camps in other parts of the world.</p>
      <p>g. All those who are issued work
permits must have the option to come and go from the U.S. as they
desire. They must also have the option of remaining in the U.S. and
becoming U.S. Citizens.</p>
      <p>2. Interim Measures</p>
      <p>Recognizing that a just reform of
immigration policy may take some time, the Green Party supports:</p>
      <p>a. Measures to allow undocumented
immigrants to obtain drivers licenses if they can prove their
identity and pass the required tests. This will improve road safety
and allow the undocumented who are driving in any case to obtain
insurance.</p>
      <p>b. Measures to give legal status to
undocumented immigrants who graduate from high school in the U.S. and
who are otherwise qualified, to allow them to attend colleges and
universities on an equal basis with other high school graduates. The
Green Party is opposed to efforts to force undocumented youth into
becoming cannon fodder for the U.S. military as the price for legal
status.</p>
      <p>c. Reduce wait lists and make the
system work more efficiently: current numeric caps on immigrant visas
must be increased. The current system of quotas and preferences has
to be thoroughly and realistically reformed. Current backlogs must be
brought up to date as soon as possible. Wait times for processing and
resolving immigration benefit applications should be reduced to no
more than six months. Pre-1996 screening criteria for legal permanent
residency and citizenship applications should be restored.</p>
      <p>d. The understandable concern about
immigrant workers competing for jobs with current citizens cannot and
should not be addressed by criminalizing undocumented immigration or
punishing fellow victims of U.S. corporatist policies. Instead, we
must reverse these policies. Among other things, we should repeal
NAFTA, CAFTA, Fast Track and other corporate globalization policies.
We must stop using our tax dollars to subsidize corporate
agribusiness and to promote poverty in Latin America, and start using
them to help reward environmentally responsible family farmers,
encourage improved infrastructure and economic conditions in Latin
America, and raise labor standards, at home and abroad. Here at home,
we must also promote the policies, as outlined in the Economy and
Workers' Rights sections of this Platform, that can help us achieve
a full employment economy at a living wage, including strictly
enforcing and expanding the rights of all workers to form unions.</p>
      <p>e. We advocate an end to employer
sanctions, which have been shown to hurt not only undocumented
workers but also U.S.-born workers (especially those of color).
Instead, the focus on employers must be to vigorously enforce our
wage and labor laws. Instead of further victimizing the victims of
corporate globalization, create real opportunities and raise labor
standards for all!</p>
      <p>f. We oppose the provision of current
law which allows local police to become agents of the immigration
agency. Local policing functions should be totally separate from
immigration enforcement.</p>
      <p>g. Greens oppose "English-only"
legislation. Immigrants already have ample incentive to learn
English. But when interaction with the government is limited to the
English speaking, persons are put at additional risk of exploitation.
The focus needs to be on providing adequate and accessible English
language instruction and assistance. We advocate legislation to
ensure that federal funds marked for communities to provide ESL
(English as second language) training, and health and social support
services to immigrants actually go to them. When funds are spent in
other areas, immigrants are being deprived of benefits that they earn
as productive workers in their communities. Meanwhile, courts, social
service agencies, and all government agencies dealing with the public
must provide trained and certified translators. Additionally, the
language rights of peoples who were in this land before it became
part of the U.S., including Native Americans and Mexicans in the
Southwest, must be recognized and respected.</p>
      <p>h. We oppose the militarization of our
borders, (mis-) using the National Guard as border police, and
building a wall between the U.S. and Mexico. This will further
intensify the human rights disaster our immigration policy has
become, as well as seriously harm border ecosystems. We demand an
immediate end to policies designed to force undocumented
border-crossers into areas where conditions dramatically increase the
risk of permanent injury or death, destruction of fragile
environments, and the cutting off of corridors needed by wildlife for
migration within their habitat. For these reasons we specifically
oppose the walling off of both traditional urban crossing areas and
of wilderness areas. We also call for the immediate dismantling of
the border wall. We mourn the death of those thousands of men, women
and children who have died trying to cross this border, where a
couple of decades ago such deaths were virtually unheard of.</p>
      <p>i. We must resist proposals that use
illegal immigration as an excuse to put us all under further
government monitoring and control by means of a national ID card or
other identification or tracking systems. We also oppose the
imposition of the "E-Verify" system to screen people applying for
jobs. Citizen workers who have been propagandized to support
"tougher" measures to identify and apprehend undocumented workers
need to carefully consider what they are asking for. The same snare
they want the government to use against undocumented workers can
easily be used to repress them. Our government is already engaged in
illegal spying and surveillance of its own citizens. It is already
invading our privacy. A national ID card system is one of the
hallmarks of a totalitarian government or police state. We need to
repeal the Real ID Act and resist the establishment of any system
that would suppress freedom to travel and require citizens and
non-citizens alike to "show their papers" and reveal their
private information to government monitors at every turn.</p>
      <p>j. We demand recognition of the
sovereignty of indigenous nations whose territories cross national
boundaries. These indigenous nations have the right to determine the
status of their members.</p>
      <p>k. We demand new policies and laws that
deal more effectively and humanely with the victims of illegal
international trafficking in humans -- primarily women and children
who are bought, kidnapped, coerced, brutalized, defrauded, tricked,
sold and marketed for forced sex (rape) and prostitution, with an
estimated 50,000 trafficked to the U.S. 
</p>
      <p>     We call for stiffer, more
appropriate policy, structure and laws to deal with traffickers, and
also demand that procedures to deport victims before the traffickers
are prosecuted must be changed to allow the victims to testify
against the traffickers, which plays a major role in bringing these
cases to justice and helping stem the tide of this heinous crime. The
victims of trafficking should have the option of permanent residence
in the U.S. or return to their home countries, according to their own
choice.</p>
      <h3>K. Housing and Homelessness </h3>
      <p>People have a right to a home and to be
secure in their tenancy. However the supply of affordable housing is
not meeting the need, while in an era of increasing deregulation,
many tenants are losing important legal protections. 
</p>
      <p>     Instead of enacting zoning laws to
increase affordable housing, the trend has too often been to increase
the proportion of land zoned for commercial property at the expense
of residential property. Instead of providing funding to increase
affordable housing, amount of funds dedicated to this purpose is
decreasing. At the same time, rent control and tenant eviction
protections do not exist in most jurisdictions, and where they do,
they are often inadequate and under attack. State governments
continue to weaken or preempt local rent control laws, while
landlords who violate housing code requirements by failing to keep
their property in habitable condition, are often tolerated or given
lenient penalties. Housing discrimination also remains rampant
against people of color, immigrants, disabled, single people, gays
and lesbians, and families with children. 
</p>
      <p>     Compounding these concerns is the
long-term stagnation of workers' real wages, which further
exacerbates the housing availability and affordability crisis. At the
same time those who are not housed&#x2014;for example, the homeless&#x2014;are often hounded, threatened, and often cannot obtain badly needed
services. While increased affordable housing can help alleviate the
problem of homelessness, the homeless have additional needs that go
far beyond housing. 
</p>
      <p>The Green Party recommends the
following actions:</p>
      <p>Renters/Tenants' Rights 
</p>
      <p>1. Guarantee tenant's rights,
including: freedom from harassment and evictions without just cause;
well-enforced habitability standards; strong anti-discrimination
enforcement, including family protection laws and domestic
partnerships; continuation of established services and amenities; the
right to reasonable guest visitation; maintenance of roommate
privileges; and the right to communicate with other tenants about
conditions or circumstances in their buildings. 
</p>
      <p>2. Enact and enforce strong penalties
for landlords who violate these rights. 
</p>
      <p>3. Fund public and non-profit
tenant-related counseling and legal assistance for renters. 
</p>
      <p>Rent Control 
</p>
      <p>4. Defend and expand cities' right to
enact local rent control laws, including vacancy control/recontrol,
that fit the needs of their communities. 
</p>
      <p>5. Provide for publicly elected Rent
Control/Stabilization Boards for communities with local rent control
laws. 
</p>
      <p>Preserve and Increase Affordable Housing Supply 
</p>
      <p>6. Defend and expand cities' ability
to enact affordable housing inclusionary ordinances that fit the
needs of their communities, so that the private sector will
contribute its share of affordable housing construction. 
</p>
      <p>7. Provide funding for publicly built
affordable housing, including funding for non-profit corporations
that build affordable housing. 
</p>
      <p>8. Enact zoning to promote mixed-use
development along transit corridors to locate housing next to jobs
and public transportation. Lower parking requirements for new
multi-family development to lower cost of construction to enable
greater affordability. 
</p>
      <p>9. Regulate and limit the legal
conversion of existing affordable housing into hotels, motels and
short-term vacation rentals and establish and enforce laws to prevent
illegal conversions. 
</p>
      <p>Fair Housing</p>
      <p>10. Enforce and strengthen the federal
Fair Housing Act and other federal and state fair-housing laws that
prohibit discrimination based on race, color, religion, gender,
sexual orientation, disability, familial status and national origin. 
</p>
      <p>11. Increase funding to assist people
who believe they have been victims of housing discrimination and
support and fund fair housing enforcement and education across the
nation. Consider establishment of an independent Fair Housing
Enforcement Agency outside of the U.S. Department of Housing and
Urban Development in order to improve enforcement and restore public
confidence in the implementation of federal fair housing policies. 
</p>
      <p>12. Require that communities that
receive federal housing funds provide evidence that their housing
policies are affirmatively furthering fair housing. 
</p>
      <p>13. Amend the federal Section 8 Housing
Choice Voucher Program to increase access of eligible families to
high opportunity communities, by including higher rents where
necessary, improving administrative portability of vouchers across
jurisdictional lines, re-establishing housing mobility programs to
assist voucher-holders seeking to move to higher opportunity areas,
creating strong incentives and performance goals for administering
agencies, and providing incentives to recruit new landlords into the
program. 
</p>
      <p>14. Amend the Low Income Housing Tax
Credit program to include fair housing requirements for site
selection, affirmative marketing, and reporting of racial/ ethnic
data to ensure that this program works to further fair housing goals.
</p>
      <p>15. Ensure that fair housing principles
are emphasized in programs addressing the mortgage and financial
crisis. 
</p>
      <p>16. Revive the President's Fair
Housing Council to coordinate federal activities across agencies to
support fair housing. 
</p>
      <p>Measures to Address Homelessness 
</p>
      <p>17. Prevent homelessness before it
occurs by addressing its structural causes, through raising the
income floor under the working poor, creating living-wage jobs,
providing job training and education that will enable low-wage
workers to obtain living-wage jobs, preserving and expanding
affordable housing, providing affordable health care, ensuring
sufficient mental health care and substance abuse services,
availability of healthy food and providing effective, holistic
assistance that connects vulnerable individuals with sources of
income and essential services. 
</p>
      <p>18. Recognize that there are multiple,
related and individualized causes of homelessness, and develop
solutions that address them. Maintain and expand the social services
necessary to address the varied aspects of homelessness.</p>
      <p>19. Move people rapidly into stable
living arrangements, where they are under constant threat of
displacement or worrying about untreated health problems or other
personal difficulties. Support and encourage service integration at
all levels and move beyond the shelter approach to provide supportive
housing that combines accommodation and an array of necessary
services, to transition people out of homelessness. 
</p>
      <p>20. Responding creatively to provide
additional transitional housing through master leasing of private
apartment blocks; purchase for-profit single room occupancy hotels;
and where feasible, conversion of short-term emergency shelter
facilities into permanent supportive housing. 
</p>
      <p>21. Provide the resources necessary to
advocate, develop and monitor discharge practices of local hospitals,
jails and foster care through a zero-tolerance policy for discharging
people to the streets. 
</p>
      <p>22. Increase employment for homeless
people. Set aside a share of public-sector jobs for homeless people
who are able to work. Ensure that public agencies devoted to job
creation are active in providing job training and work opportunities
for homeless residents. Support non-profit agencies that do the same.
</p>
      <p>23. Ensure that public assistance is
enough to allow recipients to afford a roof over their head. Help
homeless who are entitled to federal Social Security benefits and
veterans' disability payments to obtain them. 
</p>
      <p>24. Repeal laws that criminalize
homelessness. 
</p>
      <p>25. Involve homeless people in
decision-making about short- and long-term solutions to homelessness.
</p>
      <p>26. Educate homeless people about their
right to vote. Encourage voter registration and voter participation
among homeless people.</p>
      <p>III. Ecological Sustainability</p>
      <p>The human community is an element of
the Earth community, not the other way around. All human endeavors
are situated within the dynamics of the biosphere. If we wish to have
sustainable institutions and enterprises, they must fit well with the
processes of the Earth. The ideology of industrialism, in both
capitalist and communist countries, insists that modern society lives
on top of nature and should rightly use and despoil the rest of the
natural world as we desire&#x2014;because any loss of the ecosystems
is merely an "externality" in economic thought and because any
problems can be addressed later by a technological fix. We are now
living through the painful consequences of that arrogant, ignorant
perspective. Many of our children suffer from accumulations of
mercury and other toxins in their neurological systems,
environmentally related cancer is on the rise, and our air and water
are increasingly polluted. Meanwhile, our ecosystems are being
compromised by the spreading presence of genetically engineered
organisms. 
</p>
      <p>Our houses and buildings, manufacturing
processes, and industrial agriculture were all designed with the
assumption of an endless supply of cheap and readily available fossil
fuels.   Pollution and despoiling the land were not part of the
thinking. The Green Party, however, is optimistic about the
alternatives that now exist and that could be encouraged through tax
policy and the market incentives of fuel efficiency. We also
challenge the grip of the oil, automotive, and automobile insurance
industries that have managed to block or roll back progress in public
mass transit. The gutting of subsidies for the railroads has meant
not only fewer passenger routes but also the addition of thousands of
large freight trucks on our highways, decreasing public safety and
increasing pollution. We are committed to extending the greening of
waste management by encouraging the spread of such practices as
reduce, return, reuse, and recycle. We strongly oppose the recent
attempts to roll back the federal environmental protection laws that
safeguard our air, water, and soil. 
</p>
      <p>The health of the life-support
systems&#x2014;the ecosystems on our continent&#x2014;is of
paramount importance. Inherent in the efficient dynamics of those
ecosystems is a vital profusion of biodiversity.  Therefore, the
Greens call for a halt to the destruction of habitats, which are
being sacrificed to unqualified economic expansion. We humans have a
moral responsibility to all of our relations, many of which are
facing extinction because we carelessly and permanently halt their
long evolutionary journey. 
</p>
      <p>The Green Party also supports the
spread of organic agriculture and the careful tending of our nation's
precious remaining topsoil. We support planetary efforts to slow the
ever-increasing numbers of humans pressuring the ecosystems, and we
especially support the reduction of consumption of the world's raw
materials by the industrialized Northern Hemisphere. We are appalled
by our country's withdrawal from serious efforts to limit
greenhouse gases that are contributing mightily to global climate
disruption. The Green Party strongly urges the United States to adopt
an actively responsible position in this crisis and to take
significant action to address the problem.</p>
      <h3>A. Climate Change</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Greens want to stop runaway climate
change, by reducing greenhouse gas emissions at least 40% by 2020 and
95% by 2050, over 1990 levels.</p>
      <p>     Climate change is the gravest
environmental, social and economic peril that humanity has ever met.
Across the world, it is causing vanishing polar ice, melting
glaciers, growing deserts, stronger storms, rising oceans, less
biodiversity, deepening droughts, as well as more disease, hunger,
strife and human misery. It is a tragedy unfolding in slow motion.</p>
      <p>     Greenhouse gases warm the Earth by
trapping heat in the atmosphere. Much of that heat is initially
absorbed by the ocean, creating roughly a 30-year delay in the impact
of that heat at the surface of the planet. Practically speaking, that
means that the melting glaciers and expanding deserts of 2009 were
the result of greenhouse gases dumped into the atmosphere in the late
1970s, when the level of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere was below
350 parts per million (ppm). To return to a safe level of greenhouse
gases in Earth's atmosphere, we must reduce atmospheric greenhouse
gases as quickly as possible to levels that existed before 1980, to
350ppm carbon dioxide.</p>
      <p>     Greens support science-based
policies to curb climate change. We have an ambitious plan to make
drastic changes quickly to avert global catastrophe. We will expend
maximum effort to preserve a planet friendly to life as we know it by
curtailing greenhouse gas emissions and actively removing greenhouse
gases from the atmosphere.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. Strong International Climate Treaty</p>
      <p>Support a strong international climate
treaty under the auspices of the United Nations Framework Convention
on Climate Change. The United States must do far better than its
offer in Copenhagen to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 4% below
1990 levels. We should support at least a 40% reduction by 2020 and
95% reduction by 2050, over 1990 levels.</p>
      <p>2. Economic Policy For A Safer Climate</p>
      <p>a. Enact a Fee &amp; Dividend system on
fossil fuels to enable the free market to include the environmental
costs of their extraction and use. These fees shall be applied as far
upstream as possible, either when fuel passes from extraction to
refining, distribution or consumption; or when it first enters the
United States' jurisdiction. The carbon fee will initially be small,
a dime per kilogram of carbon, to avoid creating a shock to the
economy. The fee will be increased by 10% each year that global
atmospheric carbon dioxide content is greater than 350 ppm, decreased
10% each year it's less than 300 ppm, and repealed entirely when it
falls below 250 ppm.</p>
      <p>b. Although imported fossil fuel has no
more impact on global climate change than domestic, importing
petroleum and natural gas has a catastrophic impact on American
foreign policy and the American economy. We will enact this same fee
on imported fossil fuels a second time to give the free market an
incentive to wean America off foreign oil and gas.</p>
      <p>c. The Green Party calls for
elimination of subsidies for fossil fuels, nuclear power, biomass and
waste incineration and biofuels. We must also acknowledge that the
bulk of our military budget is, in fact, an indirect subsidy for oil
&amp; gas corporations.</p>
      <p>d. To prevent perverse incentives
arising from higher carbon prices, the Green Party mandates clean
fuels in addition to pricing carbon. Otherwise dirty energy sources
like nuclear power, biomass and biofuels that are not subject to
carbon pricing will become economically competitive.</p>
      <p>3. Repay Our Climate Debt</p>
      <p>a. Pay for adaptation to climate change
in countries with less responsibility for climate change.</p>
      <p>b. Provide a carbon neutral development
path for those countries that can no longer be permitted to develop
in the same way we did&#x2014;by burning cheap fossil fuels.</p>
      <p>4. More Efficiency And Conservation</p>
      <p>a. Adopt energy efficiency standards
that reduce energy demand economy-wide by 50% over the next 20-30
years. The U.S. can make massive reductions in its energy use through
a combination of conservation and efficiency measures. We don't
actually need any additional power. Instead, we can and should reduce
our consumption of power.</p>
      <p>b. Build an efficient, low cost public
transportation system. The best incentive we can provide to live
closer to work and reduce the use of private vehicles is to make the
alternative inexpensive and convenient to use.</p>
      <p>c. Adopt a national zero waste policy.
The less we consume and throw away, the less we will need to produce
and replace.</p>
      <p>5. Clean, Green Energy and Jobs</p>
      <p>a. Create an inclusive program to train
workers for the new, clean energy economy. Focusing on both the
environment and social justice, prioritize the creation of green jobs
in communities of color and low-income communities.</p>
      <p>b. Adopt a clean energy portfolio
standard that rapidly replaces our combustion-based power sources
with wind, solar, ocean, small-scale hydro, and geothermal power.</p>
      <p>c. End the use of nuclear power.
Nuclear energy is massively polluting, dangerous, financially risky,
expensive and slow to implement. Our money is better spent on wind,
solar, geothermal, conservation and small-scale hydroelectric.</p>
      <p>d. Stop "dirty clean energy." Many
of the "solutions" offered in climate legislation aren't real
solutions. Biomass incineration (trees, crops, construction debris
and certain types of waste), landfill gas and many types of biofuels
will dump massive quantities of toxic pollutants into the air and
water, and some of these energy sources produce more greenhouse gas
emissions than coal. Natural gas is primarily methane, which is 25
times more potent than carbon dioxide as a greenhouse gas.
Consequently, when pipeline leakage is considered, the clean-burning
characteristics of natural gas can be lost, resulting in a fuel with
climate impacts as bad as coal. Biomass and biofuels will also
increase deforestation, contributing to more carbon dioxide in the
atmosphere.</p>
      <p>6. Clean, Green Agriculture</p>
      <p>a. Convert U.S farm and ranchland to
organic practices. Chemical and industrial agriculture produces
35-50% of climate destabilizing greenhouse gases.</p>
      <p>b. Switch to local food production and
distribution. Localized, organic food production and distribution
reduce fossil fuel usage and enriches soil that sequesters more
carbon dioxide.</p>
      <p>c. Reduce methane, nitrous oxide and
other greenhouse gases by rapidly phasing out confined animal feeding
operations, and encouraging a reduction in meat consumption.</p>
      <h3>B. Energy</h3>
      <p>The United States has a
high-energy-consumption economy based mainly on fossil energy. The
extraction, refining, and combustion of fossil fuels have proved
extremely harmful to the environment, and supplies are rapidly being
depleted. Over the past century, the infrastructure of our
civilization has become utterly dependent on plentiful oil, coal, and
natural gas: vast land, air, and sea transportation networks;
increasing dependence on imported goods; industrialized food
production dependent on fertilizer and biocides; and sprawling,
car-dependent neighborhoods and workplaces. Our electric grid depends
on fossil fuels for two-thirds of its energy.</p>
      <p>     Dirty and dangerous energy sources
have generated an unparalleled assault on the environment and human
rights. In the U.S., low income communities and communities of color
bear the greatest burden of health impacts due to exposure to
emissions from coal and gas-fired power plants. Native American
communities have been devastated by uranium mining, and the people of
Appalachia watch helplessly as their ancient mountains are destroyed
for coal-fired electricity. Regional and global peaks in supply are
driving up costs and threatening wars and social chaos. (See separate
section on catastrophic Climate Change from excess release of carbon
dioxide.)</p>
      <p>     Since 1859 when the first
commercial oil well was drilled in Pennsylvania, the global community
has consumed about half what nature generated over hundreds of
millions of years. Although coal is more abundant than oil, it is
inherently dirtier than oil, is limited in terms of its use as a
vehicle fuel, and demand is skyrocketing globally for use in
electricity generation. Natural Gas is also in high demand for power
production and is ultimately finite. We must plan and prepare for the
end of fossil fuels now, while we still have energy available to
build the cleaner, more sustainable energy infrastructure that we
will soon need.</p>
      <p>     To simply substitute better energy
sources in place of fossil fuels is not the answer for two main
reasons. First, there are no energy sources (renewable or otherwise)
capable of supplying energy as cheaply and in such abundance as
fossil fuels currently yield in the time that we need them to come
online. Second, we have designed and built our infrastructure to suit
the unique characteristics of oil, natural gas, and coal.</p>
      <p>     The energy transition cannot be
accomplished with a minor retrofit of existing energy infrastructure.
Just as our fossil fuel economy differs from the agrarian economy of
1800, the post-fossil fuel economy of 2050 will be profoundly
different from all that we are familiar with now. Changes would occur
if we wait for the price of fossil fuels to reflect scarcity, forcing
society to adapt; however, lack of government planning will result in
a transition that is chaotic, painful, destructive, and possibly not
survivable.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party advocates a rapid
reduction in energy consumption through energy efficiency and a
decisive transition away from fossil and nuclear power toward
cleaner, renewable, local energy sources. Toward these goals, we
advocate:</p>
      <p>1. Encourage Conservation</p>
      <p>Encourage conservation and a
significant decrease in our energy consumption, institute national
energy efficiency standards.</p>
      <p>     With five percent of the world's
population, U.S residents consume twenty-six percent of the world's
energy. U.S. consumption of electricity is almost nine times greater
than the average for the rest of the world. These are not sustainable
levels.</p>
      <p>a. The U.S. must retrofit its building
stock for energy efficiency. Most U.S. residents live in homes that
require heat during the winter, and most are inadequately insulated.
Buildings in the South require air conditioning during the summer.
Fuel shortages, power outages, and energy price hikes could bring not
just discomfort, but a massive increase in mortality from cold and
heat. Millions of buildings can and must be super-insulated and, as
much as possible, provided with alternative heat sources (passive
solar, geothermal, or district heating).</p>
      <p>b. Energy efficiency standards similar
to those in California must be adopted nationally. The energy
efficiency standards adopted there in the late 1970s have resulted in
overall electricity-use remaining flat over the past three decades
while the population has steadily increased. During the same time
period electricity use in the rest of the U.S. has climbed along with
population growth.</p>
      <p>c. There are many different ways to
increase energy efficiency and the best path for one region of the
country might differ from that of another. We will need concerted
effort to increase efficiency in every sector of our economy.
Technologies exist that, if widely implemented, can result in huge
energy savings.</p>
      <p>d. Cogeneration and use of waste heat
to generate electricity should be encouraged.</p>
      <p>e. A carbon tax, which the Green Party
supports, would serve as an important market incentive to increase
efficiency.</p>
      <p>2. Move to Renewable Sources</p>
      <p>Move decisively to an energy system
based on solar, wind, geo-thermal, marine, and other cleaner
renewable energy sources.</p>
      <p>     The development of Earth-gentle,
sustainable energy sources must be a cornerstone of any plan to
reduce reliance on conventional fossil fuels. The Green Party
advocates clean renewable energy sources such as solar, wind,
geothermal, marine-based, and other cleaner renewable sources as the
long-term solution.</p>
      <p>a. Many other solutions being pushed,
including nuclear power, coal, industrial-scale biofuels, and
low-grade fossil fuels such as oil shale and tar sands, create more
problems than they solve.</p>
      <p>b. Further research with increased
government support is needed into new energy storage technologies, as
well as new cheaper and non-toxic photovoltaic materials and
processes, and new geothermal and ocean power technologies.</p>
      <p>c. Policy tools to directly support the
development of renewable energy sources, such as Renewable Portfolio
Standards (RPS) and Feed-in Tariffs, should also be reviewed for
effectiveness. In general, a feed-in tariff is legislation enacted by
the government that requires the large electric utilities to
guarantee a price for the renewably generated electricity fed into
the grid. When done right, such as in Germany, this policy appears to
succeed in harnessing entrepreneurial zeal.</p>
      <p>d. State-level financing policies like
California's AB 811 can help homeowners install expensive renewable
energy where the county pays the up-front cost and the system is paid
for via the homeowner's property taxes.</p>
      <p>e. Greens support voluntary purchase of
tradable renewable energy certificates; however, voluntary approaches
are not sufficient.</p>
      <p>f. Greens support research into
advanced fuels when the purpose of the research is to develop a fuel
that in its full cycle does not create more problems than it solves.
We support the use of hydrogen as an energy storage medium; however
we oppose the use of nuclear technologies or carbon-based feedstocks
for hydrogen production.</p>
      <p>g. We call for a ban on the
construction of large-scale and inappropriately-located,
hydroelectric dams.</p>
      <p>3. Eliminate dirty and dangerous energy
sources.</p>
      <p>The Green Party advocates the phase-out
of nuclear and coal power plants. All processes associated with
nuclear power are dangerous, from the mining of uranium to the
transportation and disposal of the radioactive waste. Coal is the
largest contributor to climate change with estimates as high as 80%.</p>
      <p>a. The generation of nuclear waste must
be halted. It is hazardous for thousands of years and there is no way
to isolate it from the biosphere for the duration of its toxic life.
We oppose public subsidies for nuclear power. Cost is another huge
factor making it unfeasible, with each new nuclear power plant
costing billions of dollars.</p>
      <p>b. The Green Party calls for a formal
moratorium on the construction of new nuclear power plants, the early
retirement of existing nuclear power reactors, and the phase-out of
technologies that use or produce nuclear waste, such as nuclear waste
incinerators, food irradiators, and all uses of depleted uranium.</p>
      <p>c. We call for a ban on mountaintop
removal coal mining. With limited supplies and in the absence of
commercially viable "clean coal" carbon sequestration,
which may never be feasible, coal is neither an economically nor an
environmentally sustainable solution.</p>
      <p>d. We call for the cessation of
development of fuels produced with polluting, energy-intensive
processes or from unsustainable or toxic feed stocks, such as
genetically-engineered crops, coal and waste streams contaminated
with persistent toxics.</p>
      <p>e. We oppose further oil and gas
drilling or exploration on our nation's outer continental shelf, on
our public lands, in the Rocky Mountains, and under the Great Lakes.</p>
      <p>f. Due to serious negative impacts on
food, soil, and water, we oppose industrial-scale biofuels production
and biomass burning for electric power generation. We approve small
scale distributed production under local control, such as production
of biodiesel from waste oils, production of charcoal and byproducts
from wood wastes or sustainably harvested wood, small scale
production of ethanol from crop wastes or maize stalk sugar, or
production of fuel gas for localized electricity generation from
anaerobic methane digesters or charcoal gasifiers. We do not object
to the utilization of fuel gases seeping from landfills, as that is
one way to reduce air pollution. We support as a minimum standard the
Principles for Sustainable Biomass statement signed by Clean Water
Action, Environmental Defense Fund, Environmental Working Group,
Friends of the Earth, Geos Institute, Greenpeace USA, National
Wildlife Federation, Natural Resources Defense Council, Southern
Alliance for Clean Energy, Southern Environmental Law Center, Union
of Concerned Scientists, The Wilderness Society, and World Wildlife
Fund.</p>
      <p>g. Enact a moratorium on hydraulic
fracturing ("fracking") until its damaging effects on water and
air quality are fully studied and understood. Permanently ban
high-volume hydraulic fracturing in sensitive watersheds. Regulate
hydraulic fracturing under the Safe Drinking Water Act, Clean Water
Act and National Environmental Policy Act, and require public
disclosure of the chemicals used in fracturing fluids.</p>
      <p>4. Decentralize the Grid</p>
      <p>Plan for decentralized, bioregional
electricity generation and distribution.</p>
      <p>     Decentralized power systems are
likely to be more resilient in the face of power disruptions and will
cut transmission losses, assure citizens greater control of their
power grids, and prevent the massive ecological and social
destruction that accompanies production of electricity in mega-scale
projects.</p>
      <p>a. We support "smart grid"
upgrades. The federal government must step in to set goals and
standards and to provide capital. This effort must not favor
commercial utilities over municipal power districts.</p>
      <p>b. The Green Party supports net
metering to make decentralized energy production economically viable.</p>
      <p>c. Greens support tax-exempt bonds to
finance public ownership of utilities and to allow publicly owned
utilities to finance conservation and renewable energy projects.</p>
      <p>d. We oppose deregulation of the energy
industry.</p>
      <p>5. Re-localize the Food System</p>
      <p>De-carbonize and re-localize the food
system.</p>
      <p>     Our national industrial food
system is overwhelmingly dependent upon oil and natural gas for
farm-equipment fuel, fertilizer, pesticides, herbicides, and the
transport. It is responsible for over 12% of all greenhouse gases
from human activities in the U.S. New farming methods, new farmers,
and a re-localization of production and distribution are needed.
These will require land reform, an investment in revitalizing rural
areas and the creation of local food processing plants and storage
centers. Laws and incentives affecting the food system (including
food safety laws and farm subsidies) will need to be rewritten to
provide preferential support for small-scale, local, low-input
producers.</p>
      <p>6. Electrify the Transportation System</p>
      <p>Our enormous investment in highways,
airports, cars, buses, trucks, and aircraft is almost completely
dependent on oil, and it will be significantly handicapped by higher
fuel prices, and devastated by actual fuel shortages. The
electrification of road-based vehicles is a must and will require at
least two decades to fully deploy and we must move to Earth-gentle
electricity generation to charge the vehicles. Meanwhile, existing
private automobiles must be put to use more efficiently through
carpooling, car-sharing, and ride-sharing networks. (See
Transportation section for more, including need for dramatic increase
in CAFE or gasoline efficiency standards.)</p>
      <p>7. Requirements for Energy Transition</p>
      <p>a. Investment: Enormous amounts of
investment capital will be needed to accomplish the energy
transition, much more than the promise of $150 billion for renewable
energy over ten years, and must now come from government.</p>
      <p>b. Coordination: The energy transition
will be complex and comprehensive, and its various strategies will be
mutually impacting. For example, efforts to redirect transport away
from highways and toward rail service will need to be coordinated
with manufacturers, farmers, retailers, and employers. An independent
federal Energy Transition Office should track and manage the
transition.</p>
      <p>c. Education: Community colleges should
prepare workers for new job opportunities, e.g., sustainable food
production, renewable energy installation, grid rebuilding, rail
expansion, public transport construction, and home energy
retrofitting. Grade school curriculum should include gardening
programs in all schools and increased emphasis on energy
conservation.</p>
      <p>d. Public Messaging &amp; Goal Setting:
Our leaders must instill in the nation a sense of collective struggle
and of a long journey toward a clear goal. The success of a project
of this scope will require public buy-in at every stage and level,
including the use of language and images to continually underscore
what is at stake, to foster a spirit of cooperation and willing
sacrifice.</p>
      <p>     Business leaders, advertising
agencies and even Hollywood must be enlisted, a quid pro quo for
government bail out of banks and corporations. Grassroots
initiatives, such as the Transition Towns movement, could lead the
way toward voluntary community efforts. A sophisticated, interactive,
web-based program would inspire action and provide resources.
Ratepayers should get full disclosure of the specific electric
generating facilities used to produce their electricity.</p>
      <p>     A series of challenging yet
feasible targets should be set, with the ultimate goal&#x2014;complete
freedom from fossil fuel dependency&#x2014;to be achieved by 2050.
The federal government should take the lead by setting targets for
federal facilities. Achievement of annual targets should be cause for
public celebration.</p>
      <h3>C. Nuclear Issues</h3>
      <p>1. The Green Party recognizes that
there is no such thing as nuclear waste "disposal." All six of
the "low-level" nuclear waste dumps in the United States have
leaked. There are no technological quick fixes that can effectively
isolate nuclear waste from the biosphere for the duration of its
hazardous life. Therefore, it is essential that generation of
additional nuclear wastes be stopped.   
</p>
      <p>2. The Green Party calls for the early
retirement of nuclear power reactors as soon as possible (in no more
than five years), and for a phase-out of other technologies that use
or produce nuclear waste. These technologies include non-commercial
nuclear reactors, reprocessing facilities, nuclear waste
incinerators, food irradiators, and all commercial and military uses
of depleted uranium. 
</p>
      <p>3. Current methods of underground
storage are a danger to present and future generations. Any nuclear
waste management strategy must be based on waste containers being
stored aboveground and continuously monitored, and the containers
must be retrievable and capable of being repackaged. All such
strategies must also minimize the transportation of wastes. 
</p>
      <p>4. The Green Party strongly opposes any
shipment of high-level nuclear waste across the U.S. to the proposed
Nevada waste repository at Yucca Mountain, or any other centralized
facility. The Green Party believes that this proposal is part of a
move to re-fire a fast-track, commercial nuclear industry by
providing a means for "safe disposal." We deny there is such a
thing as safe disposal of nuclear waste. 
</p>
      <p>     We propose making spent reactor
fuel and other high level wastes safer by vitrification at the site
where it is produced or now stored. 
</p>
      <p>5. We call for cancellation of the
Waste Isolation Pilot Plant (WIPP), the nation's first weapons
complex nuclear dump in southern New Mexico. 
</p>
      <p>6. We call for independent,
public-access radiation monitoring at all nuclear facilities. 
</p>
      <p>7. We support applicable environmental
impact statements (EIS) and National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA)
analysis with citizen participation at all nuclear sites. 
</p>
      <p>8. We support an immediate and
intensive campaign to educate the public about nuclear problems,
including disposal, cleanup, and long-term dangers. 
</p>
      <p>9. We oppose the export of nuclear
technologies or their wastes to other nations. 
</p>
      <p>10. We oppose public subsidies for
nuclear power, including Price-Anderson insurance caps and stranded
cost recovery bailouts. We oppose federal loan guarantees to enable
the construction of a new generation of nuclear reactors. 
</p>
      <p>11. We oppose the development and use
of new nuclear reactors, plutonium (MOX) fuel, nuclear fuel
reprocessing, nuclear fusion, uranium enrichment, and the
manufacturing of new plutonium pits for a new generation of nuclear
weapons. 
</p>
      <p>12. We oppose the deregulation of
radioactive materials and wastes, which is allowing such wastes to be
recycled into consumer products and to enter municipal waste
landfills and incinerators. We call for the strict regulation,
tracking, monitoring, and recapturing of radioactive materials and
wastes. 
</p>
      <p>13. We call on the military to clean up
depleted uranium contamination from testing ranges and battlefields
and to fully compensate exposed veterans and civilians who have been
affected by depleted uranium exposure in the U.S. and elsewhere. 
</p>
      <h3>D. Transportation</h3>
      <p>The Green Party supports a
transportation policy that emphasizes the use of mass transit and
alternatives to the automobile and truck for transport. We call for
major public investment in mass transportation, so that such systems
are cheap or free to the public and are safe, accessible, and easily
understandable to first-time users.</p>
      <p>     We need ecologically sound forms
of transportation that minimize pollution and maximize efficiency.
Surfaces impermeable to rainwater, polluted storm run-off; paved over
or polluted wetlands, the heat island effect, air pollution, and acid
rain are all directly related to a transportation system run amuck. 
</p>
      <p>     Massive subsidies to the auto and
fossil fuel industries, as well as an unworkable approach by urban
planners, maintain the auto's dominance of our cityscapes. The
present-day approach of upgrading streets to accommodate increased
traffic generates new traffic because access is now easier, and
people will now take jobs further from their homes or purchase homes
further from their jobs. Some people shift from public transit to
private cars due to the trip time in cars being shorter. As patronage
for public transit decreases, public transit loses funding, becomes
less viable, and service deteriorates thus encouraging even more
people to use their cars. 
</p>
      <p>     To counteract these trends and
reduce auto use, the Green Party advocates the following strategies:</p>
      <p>1. Pedestrians and Bicyclists</p>
      <p>a. Make streets, neighborhoods and
commercial districts more pedestrian friendly. 
</p>
      <p>b. Increase the greenery of streets. 
</p>
      <p>c. Utilize traffic-calming methods,
where the design of streets promotes safe speeds and safe interaction
with pedestrians. Create auto-free zones. 
</p>
      <p>d. Develop extensive networks of
bikeways, bicycle lanes and paths. Include bike racks on all public
transit. 
</p>
      <p>e. Maintain free community bicycle
fleets, and provide necessary support for cyclists. 
</p>
      <p>2. Mass Transit</p>
      <p>a. Redirect resources that currently go
to enhancing auto capacity into expanding human-scale transit
options. 
</p>
      <p>b. Develop affordable mass transit
systems that are more economical to use than private vehicles. 
</p>
      <p>c. Encourage employer subsidies of
transit commuter tickets for employees, funded by government
Congestion Management grants. 
</p>
      <p>d. Use existing auto infrastructure for
transit expansion where possible. Light rail could be established in
expressway medians through metropolitan high-density corridors. 
</p>
      <p>e. Include land use decisions in
transportation issues, with consideration of the need for mass
transit to have a market and be viable, and with attention paid to
cross-commuting&#x2014;the practice of people commuting to a place where
they could and should live. 
</p>
      <p>f. Expand our country's network of
rail lines, including high-speed regional passenger service. 
</p>
      <p>g. Transfer ownership and operation of
all intercity railroad trackage currently under control of freight
railroads to responsible and adequately funded public agencies, as is
done with highways, to provide for efficiency and safety of all rail
traffic.</p>
      <p>3. Motor Vehicles</p>
      <p>a. Place a moratorium on highway
widening, appropriating funds instead for mass transit and facilities
for pedestrians and bicyclists.</p>
      <p>b. Mandate HOV (High Occupancy Vehicle)
lanes on freeways, and lower tolls for carpools.</p>
      <p>c. Discourage unnecessary auto use by
eliminating free parking in non-residential areas well served by mass
transit, and establish preferential parking rates for HOV.</p>
      <p>d. Regularly increase Corporate Average
Fuel Economy (CAFE) standards to levels which truly challenge
automakers to improve the state of the art, using the fuel economy
performance of vehicles worldwide for reference. Eliminate the
distinction between cars and light trucks, the footprint loophole,
the E85 loophole and the 8500-pound exemption. Eliminate the perverse
incentives for alternative fuels that increase the nation's petroleum
consumption. Enact a Fee
&amp; Dividend system on the carbon content of gasoline, Diesel
fuel and E85.</p>
      <p>e. Enact a fuel-economy-based Federal
sales tax that creates a significant incentive for people to select
more-efficient vehicles, and for automakers to make
them available in the United States.</p>
      <p>f. Lead by example, using government
procurement to put more high-efficiency and alternative-fuel vehicles
into service.</p>
      <p>g. Electrify truck stops, freight
terminals and loading docks. Enact &amp; enforce anti-idling
regulations. Idling engines consume nearly a billion gallons of
gasoline &amp; Diesel fuel and emit ten million tons of carbon
dioxide annually. (2007 data)</p>
      <p>h. Encourage carpooling programs,
telecommuting, and other creative solutions to reduce commuter
traffic congestion.</p>
      <p>i. Remove the most-polluting vehicles
from the road by requiring every vehicle to comply with the emission
standards in effect when it was manufactured before issuing or
renewing its license.</p>
      <p>4. Air Travel</p>
      <p>a. Make airports accessible by local
transit systems. 
</p>
      <p>b. Legislate further incremental
reductions in airplane noise and air pollution. 
</p>
      <p>c. Emphasize the use of light and heavy
rail for freight transportation. 
</p>
      <p>5. Freight</p>
      <p>We call for incentives to get
long-distance truck hauling off of our highways and on to railways.
We favor the removal of any administrative impediments to efficient
long-haul freight transport by rail. Time is lost when switching
goods from one railroad to another, even when the trains are the same
size and gauge, and this waste can be eliminated.</p>
      <h3>E. Zero Waste: Reduce, Reuse, Recycle.</h3>
      <p>Our position</p>
      <p>Greens will shift our nation toward
clean production and principles of zero waste.</p>
      <p>     A waste-free society is essential
to public health and the integrity and sustainability of the
biosphere. Natural ecosystems are self-sustaining and generate no
waste. We humans are a part of these ecosystems, and while we obtain
resources from them, we have a responsibility to return only those
things that can be re-absorbed without detriment. Waste is not an
inevitable part of production and consumption, as it is viewed in the
current economic model.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. Phase out all avoidable production
and sale of toxic metals, persistent organic pollutants, persistent
bio-accumulative toxins, synthetic petrochemicals, and halogenated
chemicals. Replace them with non-toxic alternatives.</p>
      <p>2. Make manufacturers responsible for
the full life cycle of their products by requiring them to take back
used products and packaging for remanufacturing, reuse, or recycling.</p>
      <p>3. Support and implement the
precautionary principle: "When an activity raises threats of harm
to human health or the environment, precautionary measures should be
taken even if some cause and effect relationships are not fully
established scientifically. In this context the proponent of an
activity, rather than the public, should bear the burden of proof.
The process of applying the precautionary principle must be open,
informed and democratic and must include potentially affected
parties. It must also involve an examination of the full range of
alternatives, including no action."</p>
      <p>3. Strengthen right-to-know laws so
that everyone can discover what toxic or potentially toxic chemicals
are used and released in their communities, and in products that they
might purchase or use.</p>
      <p>4. Hold corporations strictly liable
for the consequences of the pollution they produce. We support the
Citizens' Platform on Superfund, as adopted at the 1995 Communities
At Risk Superfund Summit in Washington, DC. End the use of
incineration as a cleanup technology, and ensure that "cleanups"
don't simply relocate toxins to chemical waste dumps in poor
communities of color.</p>
      <p>5. Shut down existing waste
incinerators, impose a moratorium on new waste incinerators, and
phase out landfills. For all possible waste streams, we support the
following strategies (in order of priority) as alternatives to
incineration and landfills:</p>
      <p> (a) Toxics use reduction;</p>
      <p> (b) Source reduction, reuse, clean
recycling or composting /digestion; or,</p>
      <p> (c) Neutralization, sterilization or
detoxification methods where applicable.</p>
      <p>6. Do not deregulate wastes containing
toxic or radioactive contaminants significantly above background
levels. They should not be allowed to be used in "beneficial use"
schemes as fertilizer, "co-products," or fuels; or by "recycling"
them into consumer products (including construction materials) or
disposing of them as municipal waste.</p>
      <p>7. Do not export, under any
circumstances, chemicals that are prohibited in the United States. We
oppose shipping of toxic, hazardous, or radioactive wastes across
national borders, and the shipment of such wastes without strict
regulation across any political borders. Waste should not be
considered a tradable commodity under the Interstate Commerce Clause.</p>
      <p>8. Safe, secure, above ground storage
for existing nuclear waste. We oppose exporting nuclear waste to
other nations.</p>
      <p>9. Strict regulation of radioactive
materials and wastes and prohibiting such wastes to be recycled into
consumer products and to enter municipal waste landfills and
incinerators.</p>
      <p>10. Close, clean up and remediate at
national labs devoted to nuclear energy and weapons development and
operations at the Department of Energy's nuclear production sites.</p>
      <p>11. Clean up depleted uranium
contamination from testing ranges and battlefields, and provide
generously compensate veterans and civilians who have been sickened
by depleted uranium exposure.</p>
      <p>12. Require independent, transparent
radiation monitoring at all nuclear facilities.</p>
      <p>13. Substitute chemical safety testing
on animals with alternatives that do not use animals, wherever such
alternative tests or testing strategies are available.</p>
      <h3>F. Clean Air and Ozone Depletion</h3>
      <p>The strict, comprehensive protections
of the Clean Air Act must be maintained and enhanced if we are to
keep in place effective federal programs that deal with urban smog,
toxic air pollution, acid rain, and ozone depletion. State and local
clean air initiatives should advance and improve national efforts;
for example, moving forward with stricter clean air and fuel
efficiency standards, and with vehicle and fleet conversions.</p>
      <p>     Earth's atmosphere is in great
danger due to man-made chemicals and hydrocarbon emissions.
Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs), hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs), and
other related ozone-depleting substances should be banned as soon as
is possible.  
</p>
      <h3>G. Land Use</h3>
      <p>Our position</p>
      <p>Land use policies must promote
sustainable development and respect ecology.</p>
      <p>     Unlimited growth on a finite
planet cannot be sustained.</p>
      <p>     There is a fundamental difference
between growth and development and between quantity and quality.
Rather than exploiting the Earth for short-term gain, Greens believe
in living in sustainable balance with it.</p>
      <p>     Land use practices must be founded
on stewardship of the Earth, to honor the interconnected and
interdependent nature of all life, to respect ecosystems and other
species, while at the same time providing for human needs in a
responsible and sustainable way.</p>
      <p>     Only an economics that is based
upon environmental health is sustainable.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>Land ownership and property rights</p>
      <p>1. Insist that every property right has
an implied responsibility to provide for the common good of people,
places and the planet.</p>
      <p>2. Encourage the formation and
operation of cooperatives, non-profits, land trusts, co-housing, and
other forms of communal and public interest management of land and
resources.</p>
      <p>Urban land use</p>
      <p>3. Promote livable urban environments
to minimize urban sprawl. Promote urban infill with affordable
housing, mass transit, schools, jobs, health care, public spaces,
bicycle and walking paths, community gardens, open spaces, parks,
playgrounds, and urban growth boundaries.</p>
      <p>4. Green our cities with green belts,
energy-efficient infill, distributed solar and wind generation, gray
water systems, under grounding of wires and pipelines, redevelopment
of brown fields, closed loop, energy-producing sewage systems,
watershed protection and urban agriculture.</p>
      <p>5. Restore damaged urban ecosystems.</p>
      <p>6. Consider the carrying capacities of
the bioregions in which our cities are located and attempt to match
urban populations to these natural limitations.</p>
      <p>5. Support environmental justice
policies that give communities a voice in planning future development
with the goal of preventing concentration of polluting industries and
practices in poor and/or minority communities.</p>
      <p>Rural land use</p>
      <p>6. Preserve and expand rural land use
patterns that promote open space, healthy ecosystems, wildlife
corridors and the ecologically sustainable agriculture. Protect and
expand large continuous tracts of public and private land for
wildlife habitat and biological diversity, to permit healthy,
self-managing wildlife populations to exist in a natural state, and
to promote complete ecosystems.</p>
      <p>7. Promote livable rural communities to
minimize urban migration.</p>
      <p>8. Transition rural communities into
sustainable relationships with ranching, agriculture, forestry and
mining.</p>
      <p>9. Reward farmers and ranchers for the
ecosystem services they provide on private and public lands. Favor
policies that promote mall-scale farmers and ranchers over
large-scale corporate agriculture and ranching.</p>
      <p>Public Lands</p>
      <p>10. Repeal the General Mining Law of
1872.</p>
      <p>11. Enact mining reforms to better
balance mining with other important public land uses; provide a fair
financial return to taxpayers for resources extracted, and create a
fund for clean up of abandoned mines. Enact tough new environmental
safeguards to protect against mining pollution, including strict
curbs on mercury emissions from metal mines.</p>
      <p>12. Eliminate public subsidies for
livestock grazing on public lands. Raise grazing fees on public land
to approximate fair market value.</p>
      <p>13. Oppose the sale of any portion our
national parks, forests or coastlines. Fund and maintain public lands
in a healthy and productive state. Oppose commercial privatization of
the management of these lands.</p>
      <p>14. Ensure public ownership of natural
resources located on public lands. Halt federal mineral, oil and gas,
and resource giveaways, "royalty holidays," and flagrant
concessions to the mining, energy and timber industries on public
lands.</p>
      <p>15. Restore and remediate damaged
ecosystems on public lands.</p>
      <p>16. Protect old growth forests, ban
clear cutting and ban industrial timber harvest on public lands.
Minimize road building on public lands.</p>
      <p>17. Ban indiscriminate wildlife "damage
control practices" and abolish Wildlife Services.</p>
      <h3>H. Water</h3>
      <p>Water is essential to all forms of
life. The Green Party calls for an international declaration that
water belongs to the Earth and all of its species. Water is a basic
human right! The U.S. Government must lead the way in declaring water
a fundamental human right and prevent efforts to privatize, export,
and sell for profit a substance that is essential to all life. 
</p>
      <p>     We face a worldwide water crisis.
According to the United Nations, more than one billion people lack
access to safe drinking water. If current trends persist, by 2025 as
much as two-thirds of the world's population will be living with a
serious scarcity of water. Multinational corporations recognize these
trends and are moving fast to monopolize water supplies around the
world. They argue that privatizing water is the best way to allocate
this valuable resource, and they are scheming to have water declared
a human need so that it can be commodified and sold on the open
market ensuring that the allocation of water will be based on
principles of scarcity and profit maximization. 
</p>
      <p>     We do not agree. With water sold
to the highest bidder, the rich will have plenty while the poor will
be left with little but polluted water.  Short-term profits will
preclude any concern for long term sustainability. We must stop this
privatization before the infrastructures become so established that
it will be impossible to avoid a disaster of epic proportions. 
</p>
      <p>     Governments are signing away their
control over their domestic water supplies by participating in trade
treaties such as the North American Free Trade Agreement and in
institutions such as the World Trade Organization. The World Bank
recently adopted a policy of water privatization and full-cost water
pricing. 
</p>
      <p>1. We need strong national and
international laws to promote conservation, reclaim polluted water
systems, develop water-supply restrictions, ban toxic and pesticide
dumping, control or ban corporate farming, and bring the rule of law
to transnational corporations that pollute water systems. Mining and
depleting the present underground aquifers must be severely
restricted. 
</p>
      <p>2. Greens oppose the privatization of
water and demand that the U.S. government pass strong laws with
effective enforcement mechanisms to assure a safe and adequate supply
of water for its citizens and all life within its borders. 
</p>
      <p>3. New forms of international,
bioregional, and community organizations, watershed/ecosystem-based,
must be created to monitor and equitably distribute the fresh water
necessary for all life on our planet. Decisions about water must be
based on an ecosystems approach. 
</p>
      <p>     Cycles of intense drought and
flooding have demonstrated the need to reorient our priorities in
order to achieve a truly sustainable water policy. Over-development
and poor planning have resulted in increasing rain-impermeable areas,
which compounds the severity and frequency of flooding and pollution
in regions downstream. We must begin to understand and apply a
holistic watershed approach to managing our water resources. The
principle of bioregionalism (living within the means of a region's
natural resources) should give direction to future water policies. 
</p>
      <p>4. Conservation must be an essential
part of any water policy. Water conservation also reduces energy
consumption and pollution. To conserve water, the Green Party
proposes to: 
</p>
      <p>a. Mandate water efficient appliances
and fixtures be used in all new construction, and promote
retrofitting of older buildings. 
</p>
      <p>b. Promote native landscaping and other
drought resistant/ climate-appropriate plants, in order to reduce the
need for irrigation. 
</p>
      <p>c. Promote drip irrigation systems
where irrigation is necessary. 
</p>
      <p>d. Eliminate storm water pollution of
our water resources through education of our citizens, enforcement of
our laws, and holistic watershed management. Promote storm water
technologies that detain, treat, filtrate, and use storm waters near
where it is collected. 
</p>
      <p>e. Promote the appropriate reuse of the
"gray" and "black" waters we produce. Use separation
techniques, such as dual piping systems where pure water is used for
drinking and washing, and reclaimed water is used for lawn watering
and similar purposes. 
</p>
      <p>f. Mandate pre-treatment of industrial
wastes to eliminate the presence of metals, solvents, and other
toxins in sewer water. This would reduce the cost of municipal
treatment and encourage wastewater reuse. 
</p>
      <p>g. Promote passive and natural systems,
such as wetlands, for water and wastewater treatment where
appropriate. 
</p>
      <p>h. Eliminate water subsidies for
corporate agribusiness. Higher water prices give agribusiness
incentives to conserve. 
</p>
      <p>i. Assist community organizations to
monitor the use of local resources, and to oversee the enforcement of
water quality regulations. 
</p>
      <p>j. Preserve and restore the nation's
natural water features (streams, rivers, lakes, bays, wetlands and
groundwater aquifers) that are vital to achieving sustainable use of
water resources. 
</p>
      <p>5. Chemicals used in the fluoridation
of America's public drinking water supplies are toxic waste
byproducts. The majority of these toxic wastes come from the
phosphate fertilizer industry. Fluoride accumulates in the human body
through ingestion and inhalation. A growing body of research suggests
that fluoride may be associated with arthritis, hip fractures, bone
cancer, kidney damage, infertility, and brain disorders. For these
reasons, the Green Party opposes the fluoridation of drinking water.</p>
      <h3>I. Agriculture</h3>
      <p>Food is a necessity and a fundamental
human right. All people have a right to adequate, safe, nutritional
and high quality food; and those who grow it have a right to a fair
return for their labor. 
</p>
      <p>     Our current food system is
dominated by centralized agribusiness and unsustainable practices
that threaten our food security, degrade the environment, destroy
communities, and squeeze out family farmers. Our so-called cheap food
comes at the expense of the exploitation of our farmers along with
the oppression of third world peoples, inhumane treatment of animals,
pollution of air and water, and degradation of our land. 
</p>
      <p>     The agricultural system for the
21st Century must provide a high quality of life for farmers,
nutritious and safe food for consumers, and reward farming methods
that enhance the quality of water, soil, and air, and the beauty of
the landscape.</p>
      <p>     According to the 2006 United
Nations' "Livestock's Long Shadow" report and the World Watch
Institute's 2009 article "Livestock and Climate Change," the
livestock sector is one of the most significant contributors to our
most serious environmental problems, including global warming, land
degradation, air and water pollution, and loss of biodiversity. 
</p>
      <p>1. We encourage legislation that
assists new farmers and ranchers, that promotes widespread ownership
to small and medium-sized farms and ranches, and that revitalizes and
repopulates rural communities and promotes sustainable development
and stewardship. 
</p>
      <p>2. We support new farming and growing
opportunities and urge the inclusion of non-traditional crops and
foods in farm programs. 
</p>
      <p>3. We advocate regionalizing our food
system and decentralizing agriculture lands, production, and
distribution. We encourage public support for producer and consumer
cooperatives, community kitchens, Community Supported Agriculture,
urban agriculture, and community farms and gardens. 
</p>
      <p>4. We advocate the creation of a Food
Policy Council composed of farmers, including small farmers and
consumers, to oversee the USDA and all food policies at the local,
state, and national level. This council should adjudicate conflicts
of interest that arise when industries police themselves. 
</p>
      <p>5. We support the highest organic
standards (California Organic Certification Standards, for example).
We advocate shifting price supports and government subsidies to
organic food products so that they will be competitive with
chemically produced food. We believe that everyone, not just the
wealthy, must be able to afford safe and healthy food. 
</p>
      <p>6. We urge the banning of sewage sludge
or hazardous wastes as fertilizer, and of irradiation and the use of
genetic engineering in all food production.</p>
      <p>7. We would phase-out man-made
pesticides and artificial fertilizers. We support Integrated Pest
Management techniques as an alternative to chemical-based
agriculture. 
</p>
      <p>8. Food prices ought to reflect the
true cost of food, including the health effects of eating processed
foods, antibiotic resistance, pesticide effects on growers and
consumers, soil erosion, water pollution, pesticide drift, and air
pollution. Indirect costs (loss of rural communities, a heavily
subsidized transportation system, cost of the military necessary to
defend cheap oil, and reduced security), though more difficult to
calculate, should be factored into the cost of our highly centralized
food system. 
</p>
      <p>9. World hunger can best be addressed
by food security&#x2014;being self-sufficient for basic needs.
Overpopulation is largely a consequence&#x2014;not simply a
cause&#x2014;of poverty and environmental destruction, and all
remedial actions must address living standards and food security
through sustainable production. 
</p>
      <p>10. Because of the tremendous amount of
energy used in agriculture, we support farm subsidies to encourage
the transition from dirty fuels to clean renewable energy as one of
the most effective ways to move our country to a sustainable future. 
</p>
      <p>11. We support legislation that
provides energy and fuel conservation through rotational grazing,
cover-crop rotations, nitrogen-fixing systems, and fuel-free, clean
renewable energy development on the farm. 
</p>
      <p>12. We encourage states to promote
net-metering to make decentralized energy production economically
viable. 
</p>
      <p>13. Animal farming must be practiced in
ethically and environmentally sustainable ways. We support a rapid
phase out of confined animal feeding operations (CAFOs) not only
because of their adverse impact on the environment, but also on food
safety (e.g. disease epidemics), public health, and animal
protection.</p>
      <p>14. Applying the Precautionary
Principle to genetically modified organisms (GMOs), we support a
moratorium until safety can be demonstrated by independent
(non-corporate funded), long-term tests for food safety, genetic
drift, resistance, soil health, effects on non-target organisms, and
cumulative interactions.</p>
      <p>     Most importantly, we support the
growing international demand to eliminate patent rights for genetic
material, life forms, gene-splicing techniques, and biochemicals
derived from them. This position is defined by the Treaty to Share
the Genetic Commons, which is available through the Institute for
Agriculture and Trade Policy. The implications of corporate takeover
and the resulting monopolization of genetic intellectual property by
the bioengineering industry are immense. 
</p>
      <p>15. We support mandatory,
full-disclosure food and fiber labeling. A consumer has the right to
know the contents in their food and fiber, how they were produced,
and where they come from. Labels should address the presence of GMOs,
use of irradiation, pesticide application (in production, transport,
storage, and retail), and the country of origin.</p>
      <p>16. We support the restoration of
farmlands to Black families who have been discriminated against and
who have lost -- or are about to lose -- their farms as a result.
Greens will work for a meaningful remedy to restore black farmers'
unencumbered ownership of their land. 
</p>
      <h3>J. Biological Diversity</h3>
      <p>Humanity must share the planet with all
other species. Our continuing destruction of animal habitats
threatens an ever-growing number of species with extinction. This not
only deprives these species of their existence, but will deprive
future human generations of the enrichment of having these species on
the Earth.</p>
      <p>     Ecological systems are diverse and
interlocking, and nature's survival strategy can best be found in
the adaptability that comes as a result of biological diversity. All
policies concerning human settlement, food, energy, natural
resources, water, coastal development, and industrialization should
be formulated to prevent further disruption of the non-human
ecosystems' ability to maintain themselves. 
</p>
      <p>1. The Green Party supports a
strengthened and enforceable Endangered Species Act. 
</p>
      <p>2. The Convention on Biological
Diversity, first adopted at the Earth Summit in 1992, is a primary
statement of purpose regarding how we can act to preserve and sustain
our common genetic resources. We protest the demands of the U.S. to
amend this unprecedented international agreement on behalf of the
biotechnology and pharmaceutical industries, with their insistence on
protection of their intellectual property and technology transfer
rights. 
</p>
      <p>3. We encourage, and support public
access to, seed banks and seed collections that emphasize traditional
and heirloom seeds. 
</p>
      <p>4. We call for widespread education on
the critical importance of efforts being made to replant indigenous
plant life where it has dwindled or been lost. 
</p>
      <p>5. We oppose monopolistic production of
high-tech hybrid seeds. This is the basis of monoculture where
agribusiness relies on non-sustainable methods such as single crop
varieties bred with industrial traits and grown with high input of
energy, chemicals, and pesticides. This has led to a massive loss of
biodiversity, displacing traditional varieties and seed stocks. 
</p>
      <p>6. We encourage the use of diverse
natural seed varieties passed down over many generations. Crops can
be grown with the best plants' seeds being saved season to season. 
</p>
      <p>7. We oppose international trade
agreements (NAFTA, GATT and the WTO in particular) that have
precedent-setting provisions protecting transnational, corporate
control of the intellectual property of genetic material, hybrid
seeds, and proprietary products.</p>
      <p>8. We support reintroducing native
species to areas from which they have been eradicated, eliminating
predator control on public lands, and reintroducing native predators
where they would contribute to a viable ecosystem. 
</p>
      <p>9. We should educate ourselves about
animal behaviors to overcome our culture's irrational fear of
wildlife, and learn techniques of co-existence with other species. 
</p>
      <p>10. Since the efforts to clone
animals&#x2014;and eventually humans&#x2014;has been undertaken by
profit-making corporations, the purpose behind such projects is to
manufacture commodities. To classify a human (or any part thereof,
including human DNA and body organs) as a commodity is to turn human
beings into property. 
</p>
      <h3>K. Ethical Treatment Of Animals</h3>
      <p>Cruelty to animals is repugnant and
criminal. The mark of a humane and civilized society lies in how we
treat the least protected among us. To extend rights to other
sentient, living beings is our responsibility and a mark of our place
among all of creation. We call for an intelligent, compassionate
approach to the treatment of animals.</p>
      <p>     We reject the belief that our
species is the center of creation, and that other life forms exist
only for our use and enjoyment. Our species does not have the right
to exploit and inflict violence on other creatures simply because we
have the desire and power to do so. Our ethic upholds not only the
value of biological diversity and the integrity and continuity of
species, but also the value of individual lives and the interest of
individual animals. 
</p>
      <p>     The Green Party advocates humane
treatment of animals with the following policies: 
</p>
      <p>1. Redirect the funds that are
disbursed annually by the National Institutes of Health away from
animal experiments and more towards direct health care, preventive
medicine, and biomedical research using non-animal procedures such as
clinical, epidemiological, and cell culture research. 
</p>
      <p>2. Phase out the use of animals for
consumer product testing, tobacco and alcohol testing, psychological
testing, classroom demonstrations and dissections, weapons
development and other military programs. 
</p>
      <p>3. Mandate clear labeling of products
to tell whether or not they have been tested on animals and if they
contain any animal products or by-products. 
</p>
      <p>4. Establish procedures to develop
greater public scrutiny of all animal research. These should include
the welfare of laboratory animals, and a halt to wasteful public
funding of unnecessary research such as duplicative experiments. 
</p>
      <p>5. End the abuse of animals, including
farm animals, and strengthen our enforcement of existing laws. 
</p>
      <p>6. Ban the use of goods produced from
exotic or endangered animals. 
</p>
      <p>7. Prohibit large scale commercial
breeding facilities, such as "puppy mills," because of the
massive suffering, overpopulation, and ill health such facilities
produce. 
</p>
      <p>8. Subsidize spay and neuter clinics to
combat the ever-worsening pet overpopulation problem that results in
the killing of millions of animals every year. Where unwanted
companion animals are being killed in shelters, we advocate mandatory
spay and neuter laws. 
</p>
      <p>9. Ban the exploitation of animals in
violent entertainment and sports. 
</p>
      <h3>L. Forestry Practices</h3>
      <p>Forests are indispensable to human and
animal life and must be protected. 
</p>
      <p>     Vast forests once covered most
land, moderating the Earth's climate and providing habitats for
myriad species of wildlife. The Earth's remaining forests are a
critical resource in that useful products, especially medicines,
originate in the forest. Today's global market economy, in the
hands of multi-national corporations, irresponsibly uses and often
destroys this valuable and irreplaceable resource. 
</p>
      <p>     The governments of many countries
are selling off their rain forest land to cattle growers for the
production of cheap beef, most of which is exported to first-world
countries such as the U.S. Unsuitable rain forest land is also given
to subsistence farmers who ruin the soil in a few seasons. In the
meantime, landowners hoard prime agricultural land for speculation.
On both state and federal lands, trees are harvested and the raw logs
are exported, causing jobs to be exported. 
</p>
      <p>     The Green Party calls for actions
to protect our forests:</p>
      <p>1. Overhaul state and U.S. Forest
Service rules to protect our forests and use them wisely. 
</p>
      <p>2. Review, reform and restructure all
federal and state land-use policies so that our practices become
environmentally sustainable, and so that forests provide a continuing
supply of high quality wood products. 
</p>
      <p>3. Stop building logging roads in
national forests at taxpayers' expense. These roads not only cost
more than the revenue from timber sales that they expedite, but they
also contribute to soil erosion and silting of streams, which ruin
fish habitats. 
</p>
      <p>4. Ban the harvest of Ancient Forests. 
</p>
      <p>5. Ban the export of raw logs and other
minimally processed forest products (pulp, chips, carts, slabs,
etc.), which causes American job loss. 
</p>
      <p>6. Offer subsidies to local
watershed-based mills. This will maximize employment opportunities
through value-added processing, and promote sustainability and worker
control. 
</p>
      <p>7. Use work projects, goats, and other
sustainable methods to control undergrowth rather than spraying
herbicides, especially near communities.</p>
      <p>8. Grow and use hemp as a plentiful and
renewable resource for the manufacture of paper and other forest
products. 
</p>
      <p>9. Protect significant archaeological,
historical and cultural sites. 
</p>
      <p>10. Support the rights of people
indigenous to the rain forest, and their ecologically sound use of
the forest&#x2014;such as rubber extraction, nut gathering, and
collecting medicinal herbs. End the importation of rain forest beef. 
</p>
      <p>11. Forgive the debts of Third World
countries that need help in halting the destruction of their rain
forest lands. 
</p>
      <p>12. Develop labels that identify
ecologically sound forest products. This would help consumers to
support ecologically sound forestry. 
</p>
      <p>13. Protect wildlife habitats,
fisheries, biodiversity, scenery, and recreation. We must accept
responsibility for the affect local actions have on the global
economy and ecology. 
</p>
      <h3>M. Ocean Protection</h3>
      <p>Our position</p>
      <p>Our oceans, with their enormous
diversity of life and function, are essential to life on Earth and
must be preserved.</p>
      <p>     Our oceans are threatened by
climate change, pollution, whaling, over fishing, factory fishing,
bottom trawling, by catch, pirate fishing and fish farming. Simple,
strong policy changes can rejuvenate the health of our oceans and
planet.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. Protect 40% of the world's oceans
as marine preserves, especially near shore coastal habitats.
Determine protected zones through a democratic process involving all
stakeholders.</p>
      <p>2. Ban offshore oil drilling.</p>
      <p>3. Ban the siting of liquefied natural
gas facilities off the U.S. coast.</p>
      <p>4. Phase out use of the once-through
cooling process, currently used by power plants, in and near coastal
waters.</p>
      <p>5. Require secondary treatment of waste
effluent before release.</p>
      <p>6. Ban ocean transportation of nuclear
and toxic waste.</p>
      <p>7. Ban sonar testing in the oceans.</p>
      <p>8. Support the ban on international
commercial whaling as well as other international efforts to protect
endangered marine species.</p>
      <p>9. Ban drift-net fishing and long-line
fishing and phase out factory trawling.</p>
      <p>10. Map undersea toxic dump sites, and
investigate methods of rendering them harmless.</p>
      <p>11. Ban the importation of fish and
fish products caught by drift-nets and other illegal means.</p>
      <p>12. Ban the importation of coral
products and the destruction of breakwaters.</p>
      <p>13. Support the Law of the Sea Treaty
that establishes the global sharing of ocean resources.</p>
      <p>14. Support complete cleanup of
existing and past oil spills. Cost of cleanups and compensation for
affected communities should be paid by the corporations responsible
for the spills.</p>
      <p>IV. Economic Justice and Sustainability</p>
      <p>Green economics is rooted in ecological
economics. Our economy should serve us and our planet. Our economy
should reflect and respect the diverse, delicate ecosystems of our
planet.</p>
      <p>Our current economic system is gravely
flawed. It is unjust and unsustainable because it is premised on
endless economic growth and destruction of nature. Our market
economy, by externalizing the environmental and social costs of
greenhouse gas emissions, is creating the greatest market failure in
history: climate change, and its devastating effects. Our
government's top economic goal&#x2014;increasing Gross Domestic
Product&#x2014;impels us to perpetually intensify our resource use
and environmental destruction.</p>
      <p>Green economic policy places value not
just on material wealth, but on the things which truly make life
worth living&#x2014;our health, our relationships, our communities,
our environment, and building peace and justice throughout our nation
and the world. We aim to maximize our quality of life with a minimum
of consumption. We aspire to less "stuff" but more happiness. We
propose a shift away from materialism to help people live more
meaningful lives as we save the planet from climate change and
ever-larger mountains of waste. We need to acquire the ability to
distinguish between need and greed.</p>
      <p>We must also end the colossal waste of
taxpayer funds for armaments and war, to reduce our nation's
federal debt, and fund our environmental and social needs.</p>
      <p>Greens intend to provide a green job to
anyone who wants one. We support using the tax system to bring more
equality to our nation. Rising income inequality makes us all poorer
in myriad ways. More equal societies are happier, healthier, safer
and greener.</p>
      <p>Greens support strong local economies
and regional trade. The best model of economic security is for a
community and region to be largely self-sufficient in the production
of its necessities. We support not the corporate control of "free
trade"&#x2014;which, through the machinations of the World Trade
Organization places the enrichment of multinational corporations
above the level of national laws&#x2014;but "fair trade," which
protects communities, labor, consumers and the environment. Local
economic vibrancy and regional trade keep more money in the community
and the region, rather than going to distant corporate headquarters.
This is the most sensible model for economic security.</p>
      <p>Greens will change the legal design of
the corporation so that it does not maximize profits at the expense
of the environment, human rights, public health, workers, or the
communities in which it operates. We believe the giant multinational
corporation is the world's most potent force for environmental and
social destruction.</p>
      <p>Unlike other political parties in the
modern era, the Green Party views economics not as an end in itself
but as a service to community development through the building and
strengthening of community bonds that constitute the social fabric.</p>
      <p>Greens are defenders of the
commons&#x2014;the vast trove of wealth owned by the people, the
social and tangible assets we inherit from generations past. Most
people living in this country yearn for a more vibrant and lively
commons, such as a richer community life, more parks and protected
wilderness, clean air and water, more silence, better access to
information and knowledge, and a more nourishing culture. We must
stop big business from undermining and stealing our common wealth,
such as our public forests and minerals, the fruits of federal
research, the public airwaves and the Internet.</p>
      <h3>A. Ecological Economics</h3>
      <p>To create an enduring society we must
devise a system of production and commerce where every act is
sustainable and restorable. We believe that all business has a social
contract with society and the environment&#x2014;in effect a fiduciary
responsibility&#x2014;and that the concepts of socially responsible
business and shareholder democracy can be models for prospering,
successful business.</p>
      <p>1. We call for an economic system that
is based on a combination of private businesses, decentralized
democratic cooperatives, publicly owned enterprises, and alternative
economic structures. Collectively, this system puts human and
ecological needs alongside profits to measure success, and maintains
accountability to communities.</p>
      <p>2. Community-based economics
constitutes an alternative to both corporate capitalism and state
socialism. It values diversity and decentralization.</p>
      <p>     Recognition of limits is central
to this system. The drive to accumulate power and wealth is a
pernicious characteristic of a civilization headed in a pathological
direction. Greens advocate that economic relations become more
direct, more cooperative, and more egalitarian.</p>
      <p>     Humanizing economic relations is
just one aspect of our broader objective: to shift toward a different
way of life characterized by sustainability, regionalization, more
harmonious balance between the natural ecosphere and the human-made
technosphere, and revival of community life. Our perspective is
antithetical to both Big Business and Big Government.</p>
      <p>3. Greens support a major redesign of
commerce. We endorse true-cost pricing. [See section E.1. True Cost
Pricing] We support production methods that eliminate waste. In
natural systems, everything is a meal for something else. Everything
recycles, there is no waste. We need to mimic natural systems in the
way we manufacture and produce things. Consumables need to be
designed to be thrown into a compost heap and/or eaten. Durable goods
would be designed in closed-loop systems, ultimately to be
disassembled and reassembled. Toxics would be safeguarded, minimally
produced, secured, and would ideally have markers identifying them in
perpetuity with their makers.</p>
      <p>4. Sustaining our quality of life,
economic prosperity, environmental health, and long-term survival
demands that we adopt new ways of doing business. We need to remake
commerce to encourage diversity and variety, responding to the
enormous complexity of global and local conditions. Big business is
not about appropriateness and adaptability, but about power and
market control. Greens support small business, responsible
stakeholder capitalism, and broad and diverse forms of economic
cooperation. We argue that economic diversity is more responsive than
big business to the needs of diverse human populations.</p>
      <p>5. Greens view the economy as a part of
the ecosystem, not as an isolated subset in which nothing but
resources come in and products and waste go out. There is a
fundamental conflict between economic growth and environmental
protection. There is an absolute limit to economic growth based on
laws of thermodynamics and principles of ecology. Long before that
limit is reached, an optimum size of the economy is reached which
maximizes human welfare in an holistic sense.</p>
      <p>6. We support a Superfund for Workers
program as envisioned by the Oil, Chemical and Atomic Workers Union
in 1991. Such a program would guarantee full income and benefits for
all workers displaced by ecological conversion until they find new
jobs with comparable income and benefits.</p>
      <p>7. The Green Party supports methods,
such as the Index of Social Health Indicators, the Index of
Sustainable Economic Welfare, and the Genuine Progress Indicator,
that take into account statistics on housing, income, and nutrition. 
</p>
      <h3>B. Measuring Economic Health</h3>
      <p>Economic growth has been a primary goal
of U.S. policy. Corporations, politicians beholden to corporations,
and economists funded by corporations advocate a theory of unlimited
economic growth stemming from technological progress. Based upon
established principles of the physical and biological sciences,
however, there is a limit to economic growth.</p>
      <p>     This policy of securing economic
growth is having negative effects on the long-term ecological and
economic welfare of the United States and the world. There is a
fundamental conflict between economic growth and ecological health
(for example, biodiversity conservation, clean air and water,
atmospheric stability). 
</p>
      <p>     We cannot rely on technological
progress to solve ecological and long-term economic problems. Rather,
we should endeavor to make lifestyle choices that reinforce a general
equilibrium of humans with nature.  This requires consciously
choosing to foster environmentally sound technologies, whether they
are newer or older technologies, rather than technologies conducive
to conspicuous consumption and waste. 
</p>
      <p>1. Economic growth, as gauged by
increasing Gross Domestic Product (GDP), is a dangerous and
anachronistic goal. The most viable and sustainable alternative is a
steady-state economy. A steady-state economy has a stable or mildly
fluctuating product of population and per capita consumption, and is
generally indicated by stable or mildly fluctuating GDP. The
steady-state economy has become a more appropriate goal than economic
growth in the United States and other large, wealthy economies. A
steady-state economy precludes ever-expanding production and
consumption of goods and services. However, a steady-state economy
does not preclude economic development&#x2014;a qualitative process
not gauged by GDP growth and other measures that overlook ecological
effects. 
</p>
      <p>2. One way to measure the economy is to
assess the value of non-monetary goods and services and measure the
rate of infant mortality, life expectancy of people, educational
opportunities offered by the state, family stability, environmental
data, and health care for all people.  Another measure is to quantify
human benefit (in terms of education, health care, elder care, etc.)
provided by each unit of output. Measuring the gap between the most
fortunate and the least fortunate in our society, for example, tells
us how well or poorly we are doing in creating an economy that does
not benefit some at the expense of others. 
</p>
      <p>3. For many nations with widespread
poverty, increasing per capita consumption (through economic growth
or through more equitable distributions of wealth) remains an
appropriate goal. Ultimately, however, the global ecosystem will not
be able to support further economic growth. Therefore, an equitable
distribution of wealth among nations is required to maintain a global
steady-state economy. A global economy with inequitable wealth
distribution will be subject to continual international strife and
conflict. Such strife and conflict, in turn, ensures the economic
unsustainability of some nations and threatens the economic
sustainability of all. 
</p>
      <h3>C. Curbing Corporate Power</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Greens want to reduce the economic and
political power of large corporations, end corporate personhood and
re-design corporations to serve our society, democracy and the
environment.</p>
      <p>     Unelected and unaccountable
corporate executives are not merely exercising power in our society&#x2014;they are ruling us. Greens will reduce corporate powers and
privileges, including by stripping them of artificial "personhood"
and constitutional protections. The Green Party supports strong and
effectively enforced antitrust laws and regulation to counteract the
concentration of economic and political power that imposes a severe
toll on people, places and the planet.</p>
      <p>     Greens believe the legal structure
of the corporation is obsolete. At present, corporations are designed
solely to generate profit. This legal imperative&#x2014;profit above
all else&#x2014;is damaging our country and our planet in countless
ways. We must change the legal design of corporations so that they
generate profits, but not at the expense of the environment, human
rights, public health, workers, or the communities in which the
corporation operates.</p>
      <p>     One point remains unequivocal: our
planet cannot afford business as usual any longer. Because
corporations have become the dominant economic institution of the
planet, we must compel them to serve human and environmental needs,
so that our peoples, nations and environment may live long and
prosper.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. End corporate personhood. A
key first step will be federal and state constitutional amendments
abolishing the legal fiction of corporate personhood.</p>
      <p>2. Federal chartering of corporations
that includes comprehensive, strict and enforceable social
responsibility requirements.</p>
      <p>3. Strengthen the civil justice system
to ensure that it holds corporations strictly liable for corporate
crime, fraud, violence and malfeasance. This would include revoking
the charters of corporations that routinely violate safety, health,
environmental protection or other laws.</p>
      <p>4. Empower shareholders to stop abuses
by the managers they hire through a structure of democratic
governance and elections.</p>
      <p>5. Enforce existing antitrust laws and
support even tougher new ones to curtail the overwhelming economic
and political power of large corporations.</p>
      <p>6. Increase funding for and strengthen
oversight of federal antitrust enforcement.</p>
      <h3>D. Livable Income</h3>
      <p>We affirm the importance of access to a
livable income. 
</p>
      <p>1. We call for a universal basic income
(sometimes called a guaranteed income, negative income tax, citizen's
income, or citizen dividend). This would go to every adult regardless
of health, employment, or marital status, in order to minimize
government bureaucracy and intrusiveness into people's lives. The
amount should be sufficient so that anyone who is unemployed can
afford basic food and shelter. State or local governments should
supplement that amount from local revenues where the cost of living
is high. 
</p>
      <p>2. Job banks and other innovative
training and employment programs which bring together the private and
public sectors must become federal, state and local priorities.
People who are unable to find decent work in the private sector
should have options through publicly funded opportunities. Workforce
development programs must aim at moving people out of poverty.</p>
      <p>3. The growing inequities in income and
wealth between rich and poor; unprecedented discrepancies in salary
and benefits between corporate top executives and line workers; loss
of the "American dream" by the young and middle-class&#x2014;each is a
symptom of decisions made by policy-makers far removed from the
concerns of ordinary workers trying to keep up. 
</p>
      <p>4. A clear living wage standard should
serve as a foundation for trade between nations, and a "floor" of
guaranteed wage protections and workers' rights should be
negotiated in future trade agreements. The United States should take
the lead on this front&#x2014;and not allow destructive, predatory
corporate practices under the guise of "free" international
trade. 
</p>
      <h3>E.  Fair Taxation</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Federal and state taxes must be
strongly progressive.</p>
      <p>     Our current tax system is
outrageously unjust. It is riddled with loopholes, subsidies and
dodges for corporations and the super-rich. Most working people pay
too much in taxes compared to corporations, multi-millionaires and
billionaires. Many of our biggest and most profitable corporations
pay little or no tax. Much investment income is taxed at less than
the rate workers pay.</p>
      <p>     We can afford to cut taxes for
most people if we make corporations and the super-rich pay their fair
share. Then we can cut them even more when we halt our nation's
wasteful spending on wars, weaponry and militarism.</p>
      <p>     We call for progressive taxation,
shifting tax from individuals to corporations, taxing "bads" not
"goods," taxing unearned income at the same rate as earned
income, taxing speculation on Wall Street, and cutting corporate tax
giveaways.</p>
      <p>     We will institute comprehensive
tax reform to simplify the tax system. We will eliminate loopholes
and other exemptions that favor corporate and wealthy interests over
tax justice.</p>
      <p>     Small business, in particular,
should not be penalized by a tax system which benefits those who can
"work" the legislative tax committees for breaks and subsidies.
We support substantive and wide-ranging reform of the tax system that
helps create jobs, economic efficiencies and innovation within the
small business community. We will end "corporate welfare."
Smaller businesses are the U. S. A's great strength. Greens believe
government should have a tax policy which encourages small and
socially responsible business.</p>
      <p>     Political democracy remains a
distant promise without economic democracy. A principal instrument
for achieving economic democracy is our tax system. Taxes are the
means whereby we fund our public services. They can also help create
equity, justice, health and sustainability.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>Cut taxes for wage workers</p>
      <p>1. Exempt people earning less than
$25,000 per year and families earning less than $50,000 per year
(adjusted for inflation) from the federal and state income taxes.</p>
      <p>2. Exempt food, clothing, prescription
medications, other necessities and second-hand goods from sales
taxes.</p>
      <p>Fair taxes for corporations and the
wealthy</p>
      <p>3. End corporate welfare, such as the
bailouts for Wall Street, the big banks and the automobile industry;
subsidies for agribusiness, Export-Import Bank loan guarantees; tax
abatements for big box stores; the tax loophole for "carried
interest" from private equity and hedge fund managers; tax
deductibility for advertising and business entertainment; offshore
tax avoidance schemes; giveaways for new sports stadiums and casinos.</p>
      <p>4. Impose a financial transaction tax
on trades of stocks, bonds, currency, derivatives, and other
financial instruments.</p>
      <p>5. Block financial transactions with
tax havens, to stop tax evasion.</p>
      <p>6. Decrease the $1 million home value
cap on the mortgage interest tax deduction for federal income taxes,
to reduce the tax subsidy provided to those living in the most
expensive homes.</p>
      <p>7. Restore the estate tax.</p>
      <p>8. Apply the Federal Insurance
Contributions Act (Social Security and Medicare) taxes to investment
income and to all levels of income, not merely the first $106,800
earned.</p>
      <p>9. Oppose the privatization of Social
Security.</p>
      <p>10. Enact a wealth tax of 0.5% per year
on an individual's assets over $5 million.</p>
      <p>Eco-taxes to help save the planet</p>
      <p>11. Establish a system of carbon taxes
on all fossil fuels, to begin to reflect the real environmental cost
of their extraction and use. Carbon taxes should be applied as far
upstream as possible, preferably when possession of the
carbon-bearing fuel passes from extraction (for example, coal mine;
oil wellhead or tanker; gas wellhead) to the next entity in the
supply chain (for example, coal shipper or utility; oil refiner or
importer; natural gas pipeline). Offset potential regressivity for
lower income individuals via the Green Tax shift that lowers income
taxes and/or other approaches.</p>
      <p>12. Eliminate tax subsidies for the
oil, gas, coal, nuclear and timber and mining industries.</p>
      <p>13. Enact a Green Tax Shift that shifts
from taxing people and work (via income and payroll taxes) to taxing
natural resource extraction, use, waste and pollution.</p>
      <p>14. Enact a system of Community Ground
Rent/Land Value Taxation that distinguishes between the socially and
privately created wealth of land, by increasing the taxes on the
former to retain for society the value that it collectively creates
and lowers them on the latter to reward individuals for their
initiative and work.</p>
      <p>15. To ensure that prices reflect their
true environmental cost, enact a system of True Cost Pricing (TCP)
for goods and services. TCP is an accounting and pricing system that
includes all costs in the price of a product. TCP charges extractive
and productive industries for the immediate or prolonged damage
(pollution of air and water) and diminishment of natural resources
caused by their acts.</p>
      <p>16. Impose a carbon fee on goods
imported from nations with lower carbon taxes than in the U.S., based
upon the carbon spent in manufacturing and transporting them to the
U.S.</p>
      <p>Other tax reforms</p>
      <p>17. Simplify the tax code. Make it
transparent, understandable and resistant to the machinations of
powerful corporate and wealthy interests.</p>
      <p>18. Eliminate tax incentives to send
jobs overseas.</p>
      <p>19. Raise taxes on tobacco, alcohol,
soda pop and other junk food. 
</p>
      <h3>F. Local Economic Development</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Greens support reforms that give
communities more control over their own local economies.</p>
      <p>     Greens support decentralization,
and call for a community-based economics whose aim is local
prosperity and self-sufficiency.</p>
      <p>     We support local production, local
manufacturing, local sales, local recycling wherever and whenever
possible. We encourage face-to-face relationships with local business
owners and shopkeepers.</p>
      <p>     Successful local Green communities
nurture everyone of all ages, generate good jobs and housing, and
provide public services; creating cities and towns that educate
everyone, encourage recreation, and preserve natural and cultural
resources; building local governments that protect people from
environmental hazards and crime; and motivating citizens to
participate in making decisions.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. Protect local businesses from the
predatory pricing practices of chain and "big box" stores.</p>
      <p>2. Support incentives for co-operative
enterprises, such as consumer co-ops, workers' co-operatives,
credit unions and other institutions that help communities develop
economic projects.</p>
      <p>3. Allow municipalities to approve or
disapprove large economic projects case-by-case based on
environmental impacts, local ownership, community reinvestment, wage
levels, and working conditions.</p>
      <p>4. Allow communities to set
environmental, consumer, human rights, labor, health and safety
standards higher than federal or state minimums.</p>
      <p>5. Invest in the commons: rebuild
infrastructure; improve mass transit; protect and restore the
environment.</p>
      <p>6. Support local living wage laws.</p>
      <p>7. Establish local currencies such as
Time Dollars, Ithaca Hours and BerkShares, to strengthen local
economies.</p>
      <p>8. Enact place of origin labeling.</p>
      <p>9. Enact corporate "good character"
laws, requiring corporations, when applying for a permit, to disclose
all violations of law they have committed. Empower officials to deny
permits based on such information. 
</p>
      <h3>G. Small Business and the Self-Employed</h3>
      <p>Greens support a program that
counteracts concentration and abuse of economic power. We support
many different initiatives for forming successful, small enterprises
that together can become an engine of (and sustainable model for) job
creation, prosperity and progress. Small businesses are where the
jobs are being created. Over the past decade and a half, all new net
job growth has come from the small business sector. 
</p>
      <p>     The Green economic model is about
true prosperity&#x2014;Green means prosperity. Our goal is to go
beyond the dedicated good work being done by many companies (referred
to as "socially responsible business") and to present new ways of
seeing how business can help create a sustainable world, while
surviving in a competitive business climate. 
</p>
      <p>     We believe that conservation
should be profitable, and employment should be creative, meaningful
and fairly compensated. 
</p>
      <p>     Access to capital is often an
essential need in growing a business. [See section I. Banking and
Insurance Reform in this chapter] 
</p>
      <p>     The present tax system acts to
discourage small business as it encourages waste, discourages
conservation, and rewards consumption. Big business has used insider
access to dominate the federal tax code. The tax system needs a major
overhaul to favor the legitimate and critical needs of the small
business community. Retention of capital through retained earnings,
efficiencies, and savings is central to small business
competitiveness. Current tax policies often act to unfairly penalize
small business. 
</p>
      <p>1. Government should reduce unnecessary
restrictions, fees, and bureaucracy. In particular, the Paper
Simplification Act should be seen as a way to benefit small business,
and it should be improved in response to the needs of small
businesses and the self-employed. 
</p>
      <p>2. Health insurance premiums paid by
the self- employed should be fully deductible. 
</p>
      <p>3. State and local government should
encourage businesses that benefit the community especially. Economic
development initiatives should include citizen and community input.
The type and size of businesses that are given incentives (tax,
loans, bonds, etc.) should be the result of local community
participation. 
</p>
      <p>4. Pension funds (the result of
workers' investments) should be examined as additional sources of
capital for small business. [See section J. Pension Reform in this
chapter] 
</p>
      <p>5. Insurance costs should be brought
down by means of active engagement with the insurance industry.
Insurance pools need to be expanded. 
</p>
      <p>6. One-stop offices should be
established by government to assist individuals who want to change
careers or go into business for the first time. 
</p>
      <p>7. Home-based and neighborhood-based
businesses should be assisted by forward-looking planning, not hurt
by out-of-date zoning ordinances. Telecommuting and home offices
should be aided, not hindered, by government. 
</p>
      <h3>H.  Work and Job Creation</h3>
      <p>There is plenty of work to do that does
not jeopardize our future, does not widen the gap between the richest
and the poorest in our society, and that can enrich our communities.
We must encourage the creation of these opportunities. People whose
livelihoods depend on supporting remote, multi-national corporations
cannot be expected to support changing the system.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party proposes a third
alternative to a job or no job dichotomy: that is to provide everyone
a sustainable livelihood. The need of our times is for security, not
necessarily jobs. We need security in the knowledge that, while
markets may fluctuate and jobs may come and go, we are still able to
lead a life rooted in dignity and well-being. 
</p>
      <p>     The concept of a "job" is only
a few hundred years old; and the artificial dichotomy between
"employment" and "unemployment" has become a tool of social
leverage for corporate exploiters. This produces a dysfunctional
society in various ways: (1) It is used to justify bringing harmful
industries to rural communities, such as extensive prison
construction and clear cutting of pristine forests. (2) It has been
used to pit workers (people needing jobs) against the interests of
their own communities. (3) It has created a self-esteem crisis in a
large segment of the adult population who have been forced into doing
work that is irrelevant, socially harmful, or environmentally
unsound. 
</p>
      <p>     We will also promote policies that
have job-increasing effects. Many people will still need jobs for
their security. We need to counterbalance the decline in jobs caused
either by new technology, corporate flight to cheaper labor markets
outside our borders, or the disappearance of socially wasteful jobs
that will inevitably occur as more and more people embrace a green
culture. 
</p>
      <p>     To begin a transition to a system
providing sustainable livelihood, we support:</p>
      <p>1. Creating alternative,
low-consumption communities and living arrangements, including a
reinvigorated sustainable homesteading movement in rural areas and
voluntary shared housing in urban areas. 
</p>
      <p>2. Universal health care requiring
coverage for all. [See section F. Health Care in chapter II] 
</p>
      <p>3. The creating and spreading local
currencies and barter systems. 
</p>
      <p>4. Subsidizing technological
development of consumer items that would contribute toward economic
autonomy, such as renewable energy devices. 
</p>
      <p>5. Establishing local non-profit
development corporations. 
</p>
      <p>6. Providing people with information
about alternatives to jobs. 
</p>
      <p>Creating jobs</p>
      <p>For creating jobs we propose:</p>
      <p>7. Reducing taxes on labor. This will
make labor more competitive with energy and capital investment. (See
Taxation above) 
</p>
      <p>8. Solidarity with unions and workers
fighting the practice of contracting out tasks to part-time workers
in order to avoid paying benefits and to break up unions. 
</p>
      <p>9. Adopting a reduced-hour (30-35
hours) work week as a standard. This could translate into as many as
26 million new jobs. 
</p>
      <p>10. Subsidizing renewable energy
sources, which directly employ 2 to 5 times as many people for every
unit of electricity generated as fossil or nuclear sources yet are
cost competitive. Also, retrofit existing buildings for energy
conservation and build non-polluting, low impact transportation
systems. 
</p>
      <p>11. Supporting small business by
reducing tax, fee and bureaucratic burdens. The majority of new jobs
today are created by small businesses. This would cut their failure
rate and help them create more jobs. 
</p>
      <p>12. Opposing the trend toward
"bundling" of contracts that minimizes opportunity for small,
minority-owned, and women-owned businesses. 
</p>
      <p>13. Reducing consumption to minimize
outsourcing&#x2014;the exportation of jobs to other countries&#x2014;thus
reducing the relative price of using U.S. workers. 
</p>
      <h3>I.  Banking and Insurance Reform</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Greens will overhaul the financial
industries to end their culture of impunity and to prevent them from
committing fraud or malfeasance so severe as to drive our nation into
a massive recession or depression.</p>
      <p>     Since finance, banking, and
insurance institutions occupy a privileged position of power at the
center of commerce, this special advantage brings with it special
social responsibilities. We must ensure that the institutions
chartered for these roles take that responsibility seriously and
serve the public interest.</p>
      <p>     Greens aim to reform the financial
industries to eliminate usury (exorbitantly high interest rates on
loans) and ensure that they meet their obligations to taxpayers and
local communities.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>Banking reform</p>
      <p>1. Break up our nation's largest
banks and financial institutions so that none is "too big to fail."
End taxpayer-funded bailouts for banks, insurers and other financial
companies.</p>
      <p>2. Regulate all financial derivatives,
ban any predatory or gambling use of derivatives, and require full
transparency for all derivative trades, to control risk of
systemic financial collapse. Require regulatory pre-approval of
exotic financial instruments.</p>
      <p>3. Re-enact the Glass-Steagall Act,
which prohibited bank holding companies from owning other financial
companies and engaging in risky economic transactions.</p>
      <p>4. Oppose the federal government being
the final guarantor of speculative investments. During a financial
crisis, if the federal government and/or a central bank must provide
relief, it should be given in an equal manner and at the most local
level possible, so that benefits are equitably dispersed and burdens
are equitably borne. So rather than pouring trillions of dollars into
the banking system, they should have provided direct mortgage relief
to homeowners suffering the most from the housing bubble and
negotiated with lenders to provide partial loan forgiveness.</p>
      <p>5. Ensure that low- and middle-income
people have access to banking services, affordable loans, and
small-business supporting capital, especially through credit unions.</p>
      <p>6. Oppose disinvestment practices, in
which lending and financial institutions move money deposited in
local communities out of those same communities, damaging the best
interests of their customers and community.</p>
      <p>7. Support the extension of the
Community Reinvestment Act to provide public and timely information
on the extent of housing loans, small business loans to
minority-owned enterprises, investments in community development
projects, and affordable housing.</p>
      <p>8. Strengthen disclosure laws,
anti-redlining laws, and openness on the part of lenders regarding
what criteria they use in making lending decisions.</p>
      <p>9. Oppose arbitrary or discriminatory
practices that deny individuals or small business access to credit.</p>
      <p>10. Support development of charter
community development banks, which would be capitalized with public
funds and work to meet the credit needs of local communities.</p>
      <p>11. Support the expansion of
co-operative credit unions.</p>
      <p>12. Prosecute criminal banking
speculation</p>
      <p>The Green Party of the United States
stands for the reversing the U.S. government bailouts of speculators
who engaged in mortgage fraud and related financial crimes. The Green
Party calls for aggressive investigation and prosecution of the
individuals and corporate entities that targeted families of modest
means for predatory home loans, and the large-scale securitization of
these loans. Penalties should include prison terms, revocation of
corporate charters and confiscation of corporate and individual
assets.</p>
      <p>13. Impose a moratorium on foreclosures</p>
      <p>An ongoing mortgage-related crime wave
is occurring around fraudulent foreclosures, rushed through without
proper legal clearances or documentation, often on properties which
foreclosing entities cannot even prove they own. We demand a
four-year moratorium on foreclosures intended to recoup losses from
predatory lending. The proposed moratorium would apply to all homes
used as a primary residence and valued under $350,000.</p>
      <p>14. Access to primary, secondary,
post-secondary and vocational education should be a right of all, not
a privilege of the wealthy, and certainly not an opportunity for
predatory lenders. It's time to forgive all student and parent
loans taken out to finance post-secondary and vocational education.
The estimated $40 billion is a fraction of the bailout distributed
among the predatory lenders who created the student debt crisis and
would make a material difference for households across the country.</p>
      <p>Monetary Reform (Greening the Dollar)</p>
      <p>The crisis in our financial system
makes it imperative that we restructure our monetary system. The
present system of privatized control has resulted in the misdirection
of our resources to speculation, toxic loans, and phony financial
instruments that create huge profits for the few but no real wealth
or jobs. It is both possible and necessary for our government to take
back its special money creation privilege and spend this money into
circulation through a carefully controlled policy of directing funds,
through community banks and interest-free loans, to local and state
government entities to be used for infrastructure, health, education,
and the arts This would add millions of good jobs, enrich our
communities, and go a long way toward ending the current deep
recession.</p>
      <p>     To reverse the privatization of
control over the money issuing process of our nation's monetary
system; to reverse its resulting obscene and undeserved concentration
of wealth and income; to place it within a more equitable public
system of governmental checks and balances; and to end the regular
recurrence of severe and disruptive banking crises such as the
ongoing financial crisis which threatens the livelihood of millions;
the Green Partysupports the following interconnected solutions:</p>
      <p>15. Nationalize the 12 Federal Reserve
Banks, reconstituting them and the Federal Reserve Systems Washington
Board of Governors under a new Monetary Authority Board within the
U.S. Treasury. The private creation of money or credit which
substitutes for money, will cease and with it the reckless and
fraudulent practices that have led to the present financial and
economic crisis.</p>
      <p>16. The Monetary Authority, with
assistance from the FDIC, the SEC, the U.S. Treasury, the
Congressional Budget Office, and others will redefine bank lending
rules and procedures to end the privilege banks now have to create
money when they extend their credit, by ending what's known as the
fractional reserve system in an elegant, non disruptive manner. Banks
will be encouraged to continue as profit making companies, extending
loans of real money at interest; acting as intermediaries between
those clients seeking a return on their savings and those clients
ready and able to pay for borrowing the money; but banks will no
longer be creators of what we are using for money.</p>
      <p>17. The new money that must be
regularly added to an improving system as population and commerce
grow will be created and spent into circulation by the U. S.
Government for infrastructure, including the "human infrastructure"
of education and health care. This begins with the $2.2 trillion the
American Society of Civil Engineers warns us is needed to bring
existing infrastructure to safe levels over the next 5 years. Per
capita guidelines will assure a fair distribution of such
expenditures across the United States, creating good jobs,
re-invigorating the local economies and re-funding government at all
levels. As this money is paid out to various contractors, they in
turn pay their suppliers and laborers who in turn pay for their
living expenses and ultimately this money gets deposited into banks,
which are then in a position to make loans of this money, according
to the new regulations.</p>
      <p>Insurance reform</p>
      <p>18. Clean up the insurance industry.
Eliminate special-interest protections, collusion, over-pricing and
industry-wide practices that too often injure the interests of the
insured when they are most vulnerable. Prohibit bad-faith insurance
practices, such as avoidance of obligations and price fixing.</p>
      <p>19. Enact single-payer universal health
insurance. Until single-payer is established, we support laws that
act to make insurance policies transportable from job to job.</p>
      <p>20. Support and encourage the insurance
industry's efforts for "loss prevention," that is, to reduce
the incidence of death, injuries, disease and other calamities.</p>
      <p>21. Support initiatives in secondary
insurance markets that expand credit for economic development in
inner cities, affordable housing and home ownership among the poor,
sustainable agriculture and rural development maintaining family
farms.</p>
      <p>22. Prohibit companies from being the
beneficiary of insurance on their own employees.</p>
      <p>Broader financial industry reforms</p>
      <p>23. Support a 10% cap on interest
rates, above inflation, for credit cards, mortgages, payday loans and
all other consumer lending.</p>
      <p>24. Aggressively crack down on crime,
fraud, malfeasance and tax evasion in the financial and insurance
industries.</p>
      <p>25. Reduce excessive executive pay.</p>
      <p>26. Support the formation of Citizens'
Utility Boards to defend the interests of consumers and
policyholders.</p>
      <p>27. Favor a tax on stock, bond, foreign
currency and derivatives transactions to discourage excessive
speculation. 
</p>
      <h3>J. Pension Reform</h3>
      <p>Working people&#x2014;who own over $3
trillion in pension monies (deferred wages in effect)&#x2014;should have
financial options in where their money is invested apart from the
current near-monopoly exerted by a handful of managers, banks,
insurance companies, and mutual funds. Pension funds should not be
used for corporate mergers, acquisitions and leveraged buyouts,
corporate decisions that undercut workers rights, employment, and
retirement while generously rewarding non-productive speculation. The
current system has allowed vast amounts of workers' hard-earned
money to be squandered on job-ending, plant-moving, corporate
downsizing. 
</p>
      <p>     Pension funds are gigantic capital
pools that can, with government support, be used to meet community
needs and benefit workers and their families directly. 
</p>
      <p>1. Corporate-sponsored pension funds
(the biggest category of funds) should be jointly controlled by
management and workers, not exclusively by management. 
</p>
      <p>2. Federal law must be changed so that
pension funds need simply to seek a reasonable rate of return, not
the prevailing market rate which greatly restricts where investments
can be made. 
</p>
      <p>3. A secondary pension market
established by the government to insure pension investments made in
socially beneficial programs must be considered as one method that
could greatly expand the impact of this capital market, as
demonstrated in the case of federally insured / subsidized
mortgage lending.</p>
      <p>4. Prudent pension fund investing
should both make money and do good work. Creating jobs and supporting
employment programs in public/ private partnerships can become a
priority as we seek to expand towards opportunities where new jobs
are created small business, not transnational business. We could
target the under- and un-employed. We believe there are myriad
opportunities for a profound shift in how the savings of our workers
are best put to use. 
</p>
      <h3>K. Anti-Trust Enforcement</h3>
      <p>The Green Party supports strong and
effectively enforced anti-trust regulation to counteract the
concentration of economic power that imposes a severe toll on the
economy. The anti-trust division of the Justice Department has had
its scope and powers reduced. An explosion of unregulated mergers and
acquisitions, spin-offs, and leveraged buy-outs has overwhelmed the
federal government's capacity to provide effective oversight.
Financial and trading markets have become particularly vulnerable to
insider trading. Securities and Exchange Commission regulation of
these markets has seriously fallen short. Overall, what we see in
unchecked market power is self-serving abuse of the democratic
political process, price gouging, loss of productivity and jobs,
reduced competitiveness, and of predatory and monopolistic practices.
</p>
      <p>1. The Federal Trade Commission must
vigorously oversee mergers where the combined sales of the companies
exceeds $1 billion. 
</p>
      <p>2. The Justice Department must redefine
"relevant market share" in assessing mergers. 
</p>
      <p>3. The Congress must enact its calls
for competitiveness by stopping illegal monopolistic practices. 
</p>
      <p>4. We oppose the largesse of government
in the form of massive corporate entitlements. 
</p>
      <h3>L. Advanced Technology and Defense
  Conversion</h3>
      <p>The Green Party supports defense
technology transfer towards a peacetime technology-based economy,
particularly new industrial applications and developments in the
areas of advanced communications, alternative energy, non-toxic
battery technology and waste management.</p>
      <p>1. Consolidation of the nuclear weapons
complex should move toward alternative civilian technologies and
non-proliferation work, not toward a new generation of nuclear weapon
design and production. 
</p>
      <p>2. We recognize the need for
de-escalating the continuing arms race, and we strongly oppose
putting nuclear weapons, lasers and other weapons in space in a new
militarization policy that is in clear violation of international
law. [See section F. Demilitarization and Exploration of Space in
chapter I] 
</p>
      <p>3. Let us go forward with government
and civilian space programs; research initiatives in sustainability
science, environmental protection, ecological economics and
transportation, appropriate technologies and technology transfer;
environmental sampling and monitoring; systems testing; laser
communications; and high speed computers. 
</p>
      <p>4. Let us devote a larger percentage of
our nation's research and development budget, both private and
public, toward civilian use and away from military use. Let us
address our chronic trade imbalance in this fashion&#x2014;not by
increasing exports of military weapons and technologies. 
</p>
      <p>5. The Green Party opposes patenting or
copyrighting life forms, algorithms, DNA, colors or commonly used
words and phrases. We support broad interpretation and ultimate
expansion of the Fair Use of copyrighted works. We support open
source and copyleft models in order to promote the public interest
and the spirit of copyright. 
</p>
      <p>6. We call for a federal Technology
Assessment Office to examine how technology fits with life on Earth,
with our neighborhoods, and with the quality of our daily lives. 
</p>
      <p>Telecommunications</p>
      <p>Advanced telecommunications
technologies (many of which came originally from defense
applications), such as fiber optics, broadband infrastructure, the
Internet, and the World Wide Web hold great promise for education,
decentralized economies, and local control of decision-making. We
believe we must move toward decentralization in these efforts,
carefully protecting our individual rights as we go forward.</p>
      <p>7. Advanced and high definition TV,
digital communications, and wireless communications hold promise and
challenge. For example, the public airwaves that will accommodate the
new generation of telecommunications technology should not be free
giveaways to media giants. An auction and built-in requirements that
attach licenses to act in the public interest is needed. Technology
provides tools: we must use these tools appropriately and ethically.
[See section J. Free Speech and Media Reform in chapter II] 
</p>
      <p>8. Broadband Internet access should be
open to bidding, not simply the current choice between cable or
telephone company monopolies, where grassroots Internet service
providers must merge or go out of business. Broadband access should
be a taxpayer-funded utility, like water and sewer, ending the
"digital divide" that keeps low-income folks from access to the
Internet. 
</p>
      <p>     The Internet is a commons,
developed with public funds, and must insure freedom and equality of
access. The Green Party opposes Internet access tiered service
controlled by an Internet service provider (ISP), with independent
(not housed with the ISP) most costly and inaccessible. ISPs and
advertisers should not be gatekeepers.</p>
      <p>     The Green Party calls for
increased protection for user privacy and for accountability on the
part of ISPs.</p>
      <p>Open-Source Software</p>
      <p>Open-source software is necessary to
achieve personal, cultural, and organizational security in the face
of technological threats brought by corporations and individual
criminals. 
</p>
      <p>9. Government has a vital role in
breaking up software monopolies, not so much by filing antitrust
suits, but by buying nothing but open systems. The U.S. Government
and the larger states are buyers large enough to influence the
computer and software systems through their purchasing. It should be
illegal for a government agency to create and store information vital
to its operations in a format it doesn't control. Governments
should always consider storing information with open-source software
and in-house staff instead of only commercial systems, vendors and
software. One way to achieve this would be to add a virtual bid for
in-house open source deployment whenever a software purchase goes out
for bid. 
</p>
      <p>10. The Green Party supports protection
of software (free or proprietary) by means of the copyright. We
strongly oppose granting of software patents. Mathematical algorithms
are discovered, not invented, by humans; therefore, they are not
patentable. The overwhelming majority of software patents cover
algorithms, and should never have been awarded, or they cover message
formats of some kind, which are essentially arbitrary. Format patents
only exist to restrain competition, and the harm falls
disproportionately on programmers who work independently or for the
smallest employers. 
</p>
      <p>Nanotechnology</p>
      <p>Nanotechnology&#x2014;the science of
manipulating matter at the molecular level&#x2014;is poised to
provide a new industrial revolution with vast social and
environmental consequences. Like nuclear science and biotechnology,
nanotechnology is being pursued largely outside of public debate,
risking great harm and abuse in its use and application. 
</p>
      <p>     The Green Party calls for a halt
to nanotechnology development until the following conditions are met:</p>
      <p>11. Development of full and open public
debate about the implications of nanotechnology and the fusion of
nanotech with biological, materials and information sciences. 
</p>
      <p>12. Development of democratic public
control mechanisms to regulate the direction of nanotechnology
research and development. 
</p>
      <p>13. Expanded research into the
environmental and health consequences of exposure to nano-scale
materials.</p>
      <p>14. Development of technology to
contain and monitor nano-scale materials, and.</p>
      <p>15. Development of precautionary safety
measures for the containment and control over nano-scale materials. 
</p>
      <h3>M: National Debt</h3>
      <p>Our Position</p>
      <p>Greens will reduce our national debt.</p>
      <p>     Presidents George W. Bush and
Barack Obama have irresponsibly expanded our national debt by
trillions of dollars to finance tax cuts for savings of our workers
are wealthiest citizens, war, corporate welfare and bailouts of Wall
Street and the automotive industry. This debt and the interest that
must be paid on it is not sustainable.</p>
      <p>     Working people and the small
business community are bearing a disproportionate amount of the
federal debt burden. Yet the federal debt is, to a large degree, the
end product of tax cuts for the wealthy and big business, and the
military-defense industry buildup.</p>
      <p>     For many years the federal
government borrowed trillions of dollars. Money that should have been
going into a better "safety net" for the poor, homes for the
homeless, environmental and public lands conservation, sustainable
jobs, research and development, roads and bridges, schools and the
technologies of tomorrow, has been lost to servicing the national
debt. We cannot ignore the consequences of our nation's past
deficits and the related costs of debt service.</p>
      <p>Green Solutions</p>
      <p>1. Reduce our national debt by
increasing taxes on large corporations, the super-rich and pollution;
and decreasing expenditures in some areas, especially for war,
armaments and corporate welfare.</p>
      <p>2. Oppose privatization of Social
Security.</p>
      <p>3. Increase funding for green jobs,
Social Security, public housing, higher education, public
transportation, environmental protection, renewable energy and energy
conservation.</p>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</platform>
