<?xml version="1.0"?>
<platform>
  <party>Justice</party>
  <year>2012</year>
  <source>http://justicepartyusa.org/</source>
  <body>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Preamble</h2>
      <p>At no time in the last century have so few held so much of our nation&#x2019;s wealth, nor have our children faced less prosperity than their forebears.</p>
      <p>The two-party system has failed us.</p>
      <p>The moment has come for American citizens to come together for our mutual benefit to solve the problems that lie before us.</p>
      <p>The Justice Party issues a clarion call to join our community of concerned Americans demanding social, economic, and environmental justice for all, not just for the wealthiest Americans and their corporations.</p>
      <p>We seek to return political power to the people through fair and transparent elections, campaign finance reform, proportional representation, and Constitutional amendment.</p>
      <p>The Justice Party is a grassroots, broad-based, real political alternative to the corporate-controlled Democratic and Republican parties. We invite you to help build America’s just future.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Economic Justice</h2>
      <p>Implement major domestic green jobs and infrastructure programs</p>
      <p>Re-establish and make viable workers’ right to organize</p>
      <p>Create a fair, democratic, and transparent financial sector that serves the needs of start-ups, small business and consumers</p>
      <p>End incentives for U.S. companies to send jobs overseas</p>
      <p>Enact a financial transaction tax that will curb reckless speculation and provide revenue for job creation, job training and education</p>
      <p>End the Bush tax cuts for the wealthy</p>
      <p>Compassionate and rational immigration reform</p>
      <p>End to subsidies for oil and gas companies</p>
      <p>Free education through four years of college or equivalent as a right</p>
      <p>Protect public investments by opposing and reversing the privatization of public assets</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Environmental Justice</h2>
      <p>Enforce employee and environmental safeguards in trade agreements</p>
      <p>Ban the Canada-to-Mexico tar sands pipeline and mountain top removal</p>
      <p>Enhance air and water quality protections by strengthening the EPA</p>
      <p>Take aggressive action and leadership on the climate crisis and the environment</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <h2>Social and Civic Justice</h2>
      <p>Affordable universal health care through Improved Medicare for All</p>
      <p>An end to the wars; reduce the military budget and redirect money to domestic economy</p>
      <p>Marriage equality</p>
      <p>End race and gender discrimination</p>
      <p>Treat substance abuse within a public health framework rather than as a criminal matter</p>
      <p>Repeal the PATRIOT Act</p>
      <p>Abolish corporate personhood and implement campaign finance reform to end the corrupting influence of money in politics</p>
      <p>Prosecute the illegal conduct that led to the economic melt-down</p>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</platform>
