<?xml version="1.0"?>
<platform>
  <party>Democratic</party>
  <year>1940</year>
  <source>http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=29597</source>
  <body>
  <chapter>
              <h2>
               Preamble
              </h2>
             <p>
              The world is undergoing violent change. Humanity, uneasy in this machine age, is demanding a sense of security and dignity based on human values.
             </p>
             <p>
              No democratic government which fails to recognize this trend&#8212;and take appropriate action&#8212;can survive.
             </p>
             <p>
              That is why the Government of this nation has moved to keep ahead of this trend; has moved with speed incomprehensible to those who do not see this trend.
             </p>
             <p>
              Outside the Americas, established institutions are being overthrown and democratic philosophies are being repudiated by those whose creed recognizes no power higher than military force, no values other than a false efficiency.
             </p>
             <p>
              What the founding fathers realized upon this continent was a daring dream, that men could have not only physical security, not only efficiency, but something else in addition that men had never had before&#8212;the security of the heart that comes with freedom, the peace of mind that comes from a sense of justice.
             </p>
             <p>
              To this generation of Americans it is given to defend this democratic faith as it is challenged by social maladjustment within and totalitarian greed without. The world revolution against which we prepare our defense is so threatening that not until it has burned itself out in the last corner of the earth will our democracy be able to relax its guard.
             </p>
             <p>
              In this world crisis, the purpose of the Democratic Party is to defend against external attack and justify by internal progress the system of government and way of life from which the Democratic Party takes its name.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Fulfilling American Ideal
             </h3>
             <p>
              Toward the modern fulfillment of the American ideal, the Democratic Party, during the last seven years, has labored successfully:
             </p>
             <p>
              1. To strengthen democracy by defensive preparedness against aggression, whether by open attack or secret infiltration;
             </p>
             <p>
              2. To strengthen democracy by increasing our economic efficiency; and
             </p>
             <p>
              3. To strengthen democracy by improving the welfare of the people.
             </p>
             <p>
              These three objectives are one and inseparable. No nation can be strong by armaments alone. It must possess and use all the necessary resources for producing goods plentifully and distributing them effectively. It must add to these factors of material strength the unconquerable spirit and energy of a contented people, convinced that there are no boundaries to human progress and happiness in a land of liberty.
             </p>
             <p>
              Our faith that these objectives can be attained is made unshakable by what has already been done by the present Administration&#8212;in stopping the waste and exploitation of our human and natural resources, in restoring to the average man and woman a stake in the preservation of our democracy, in enlarging our national armaments, and in achieving national unity.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall hold fast to these gains. We are proud of our record. Therefore the Party in convention assembled endorses wholeheartedly the brilliant and courageous leadership of President Franklin D. Roosevelt and his statesmanship and that of the Congress for the past seven trying years. And to our President and great leader we send our cordial greetings.
             </p>
             <h3>
               We Must Strengthen Democracy Against Aggression
             </h3>
             <p>
              The American people are determined that war, raging in Europe, Asia and Africa, shall not come to America.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will not participate in foreign wars, and we will not send our army, naval or air forces to fight in foreign lands outside of the Americas, except in case of attack. We favor and shall rigorously enforce and defend the Monroe Doctrine.
             </p>
             <p>
              The direction and aim of our foreign policy has been, and will continue to be, the security and defense of our own land and the maintenance of its peace.
             </p>
             <p>
              For years our President has warned the nation that organized assaults against religion, democracy and international good faith threatened our own peace and security. Men blinded by partisanship brushed aside these warnings as war-mongering and officious intermeddling. The fall of twelve nations was necessary to bring their belated approval of legislative and executive action that the President had urged and undertaken with the full support of the people. It is a tribute to the President's foresight and action that our defense forces are today at the peak of their peacetime effectiveness.
             </p>
             <p>
              Weakness and unpreparedness invite aggression. We must be so strong that no possible combination of powers would dare to attack us. We propose to provide America with an invincible air force, a navy strong enough to protect all our seacoasts and our national interests, and a fully-equipped and mechanized army. We shall continue to coordinate these implements of defense with the necessary expansion of industrial productive capacity and with the training of appropriate personnel. Outstanding leaders of industry and labor have already been enlisted by the Government to harness our mighty economic forces for national defense.
             </p>
             <p>
              Experience of other nations gives warning that total defense is necessary to repel attack, and that partial defense is no defense.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have seen the downfall of nations accomplished through internal dissension provoked from without. We denounce and will do all in our power to destroy the treasonable activities of disguised anti-democratic and un-American agencies which would sap our strength, paralyze our will to defend ourselves, and destroy our unity by inciting race against race, class against class, religion against religion and the people against their free institutions.
             </p>
             <p>
              To make America strong, and to keep America free, every American must give of his talents and treasure in accordance with his ability and his country's needs. We must have democracy of sacrifice as well as democracy of opportunity.
             </p>
             <p>
              To insure that our armaments shall be implements of peace rather than war, we shall continue our traditional policies of the good neighbor; observe and advocate international respect for the fights of others and for treaty obligations; cultivate foreign trade through desirable trade agreements; and foster economic collaboration with the Republics of the Western Hemisphere.
             </p>
             <p>
              In self-defense and in good conscience, the world's greatest democracy cannot afford heartlessly or in a spirit of appeasement to ignore the peace-loving and liberty-loving peoples wantonly attacked by ruthless aggressors. We pledge to extend to these peoples all the material aid at our command, consistent with law and not inconsistent with the interests of our own national self-defense&#8212;all to the end that peace and international good faith may yet emerge triumphant.
             </p>
             <p>
              We do not regard the need for preparedness a warrant for infringement upon our civil liberties, but on the contrary we shall continue to protect them, in the keen realization that the vivid contrast between the freedom we enjoy and the dark repression which prevails in the lands where liberty is dead, affords warning and example to our people to confirm their faith in democracy.
             </p>
             <h3>
               We Must Strengthen Democracy By Increasing Our Economic Efficiency
             </h3>
             <p>
              The well being of the land and those who work upon it is basic to the real defense and security of America.
             </p>
             <p>
              The Republican Party gives its promises to the farmer and its allegiance to those who exploit him.
             </p>
             <p>
              Since 1932 farm income has been doubled; six million farmers, representing more than 80 per cent of all farm families, have participated in an effective soil conservation program; the farm debt and the interest rate on farm debt have been reduced, and farm foreclosures have been drastically curtailed; rural highways and farm-to-market roads have been vastly improved and extended; the surpluses on the farms have been used to feed the needy; low cost electricity has been brought to five million farm people as a result of the rural electrification program; thousands of impoverished farm families have been rehabilitated; and steps have been taken to stop the alarming growth of farm tenancy, to increase land ownership, and to mitigate the hardships of migratory farm labor.
             </p>
             <h3>
               The Land and the Farmer
             </h3>
             <p>
              <br />
              We pledge ourselves:
             </p>
             <p>
              To make parity as well as soil conservation payments until such time as the goal of parity income for agriculture is realized.
             </p>
             <p>
              To extend and enlarge the tenant-purchase program until every deserving tenant farmer has a real opportunity to have a firm of his own.
             </p>
             <p>
              To refinance existing farm debts at lower interest rates and on longer and more flexible terms.
             </p>
             <p>
              To continue to provide for adjustment of production through democratic processes to the extent that excess surpluses are capable of control.
             </p>
             <p>
              To continue the program of rehabilitation of farmers who need and merit aid.
             </p>
             <p>
              To preserve and strengthen the ever-normal granary on behalf of the national defense, the consumer at home and abroad, and the American farmer.
             </p>
             <p>
              To continue to make commodity loans to maintain the ever-normal granary and to prevent destructively low prices.
             </p>
             <p>
              To expand the domestic consumption of our surpluses by the food and cotton stamp plan, the free school lunch, low-cost milk and other plans for bringing surplus farm commodities to needy consumers.
             </p>
             <p>
              To continue our substantially increased appropriations for research and extension work through the land-grant colleges, and for research laboratories established to develop new outlets for farm products.
             </p>
             <p>
              To conserve the soil and water resources for the benefit of farmers and the nation. In such conservation programs we shall, so far as practicable, bring about that development in forests and other permanent crops as will not unduly expand livestock and dairy production.
             </p>
             <p>
              To safeguard the farmer's foreign markets and expand his domestic market for all domestic crops. To enlarge the rural electrification [sic].
             </p>
             <p>
              To encourage farmer-owned and controlled co-operatives.
             </p>
             <p>
              To continue the broad program launched by this Administration for the coordinated development of our river basins through reclamation and irrigation, flood control, reforestation and soil conservation, stream purification, recreation, fish and game protection, low-cost power, and rural industry.
             </p>
             <p>
              To encourage marketing agreements in aid of producers of dairy products, vegetables, fruits and specialty crops for the purpose of orderly marketing and the avoidance of unfair and wasteful practices.
             </p>
             <p>
              To extend crop insurance from wheat to other crops as rapidly as experience justifies such extension.
             </p>
             <p>
              To safeguard the family-sized farm in all our programs.
             </p>
             <p>
              To finance these programs adequately in order that they may be effective.
             </p>
             <p>
              In settling new lands reclaimed from desert by projects like Grand Coulee, we shall give priority to homeless families who have lost their farms. As these new lands are brought into use, we shall continue by Federal purchase to retire from the plow submarginal lands so that an increased percentage of our farmers may he able to live and work on good land.
             </p>
             <p>
              These programs will continue to be in the hands of locally-elected farmer committees to the largest extent possible. In this truly democratic way, we will continue to bring economic security to the farmer and his family, while recognizing the dignity and freedom of American farm life.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Industry and the Worker
             </h3>
             <p>
              Under Democratic auspices, more has been done in the last seven years to foster the essential freedom, dignity and opportunity of the American worker than in any other administration in the nation's history. In consequence, labor is today taking its rightful place as a partner of management in the common cause of higher earnings, industrial efficiency, national unity and national defense.
             </p>
             <p>
              A far-flung system of employment exchanges has brought together millions of idle workers and available jobs. The workers' right to organize and bargain collectively through representatives of their own choosing is being enforced. We have enlarged the Federal machinery for the mediation of labor disputes. We have enacted an effective wage and hour law. Child labor in factories has been outlawed. Prevailing wages to workers employed on Government contracts have been assured.
             </p>
             <p>
              We pledge to continue to enforce fair labor standards; to maintain the principles of the National Labor Relations Act; to expand employment training and opportunity for our youth, older workers, and workers displaced by technological changes; to strengthen the orderly processes of collective bargaining and peaceful settlement of labor disputes; and to work always for a just distribution of our national income among those who labor.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will continue our efforts to achieve equality of opportunity for men and women without impairing the social legislation which promotes true equality by safeguarding the health, safety and economic welfare of women workers. The right to work for compensation in both public and private employment is an inalienable privilege of women as well as men, without distinction as to marital status.
             </p>
             <p>
              The production of coal is one of our most important basic industries. Stability of production, employment, distribution and price are indispensable to the public welfare. We pledge continuation of the Federal Bituminous Coal Stabilization Act, and sympathetic consideration of the application of similar legislation to the anthracite coal industry, in order to provide additional protection for the owners, miners and consumers of hard coal.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall continue to emphasize the human element in industry and strive toward increasingly wholehearted cooperation between labor and industrial management.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Capital and the Business Man
             </h3>
             <p>
              To make democracy strong, our system of business enterprise and individual initiative must be free to gear its tremendous productive capacity to serve the greatest good of the greatest number.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have defended and will continue to defend all legitimate business.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have attacked and will continue to attack unbridled concentration of economic power and the exploitation of the consumer and the investor.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have attacked the kind of banking which treated America as a colonial empire to exploit; the kind of securities business which regarded the Stock Exchange as a private gambling club for wagering other people's money; the kind of public utility holding companies which used consumers' and investors' money to suborn a free press, bludgeon legislatures and political conventions, and control elections against the interest of their customers and their security holders.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have attacked the kind of business which levied tribute on all the rest of American business by the extortionate methods of monopoly.
             </p>
             <p>
              We did not stop with attack&#8212;we followed through with the remedy. The American people found in themselves, through the democratic process, ability to meet the economic problems of the average American business where concentrated power had failed.
             </p>
             <p>
              We found a broken and prostrate banking and financial system. We restored it to health by strengthening banks, insurance companies and other financial institutions. We have insured 62 million bank accounts, and protected millions of small investors in the security and commodity markets. We have thus revived confidence, safeguarded thrift, and opened the road to all honorable business.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have made credit at low interest rates available to small-business men, thus unfastening the oppressive yoke of a money monopoly, and giving the ordinary citizen a chance to go into business and stay in business.
             </p>
             <p>
              We recognize the importance of small business concerns and new enterprises in our national economy, and favor the enactment of constructive legislation to safeguard the welfare of small business. Independent small-scale enterprise, no less than big business, should be adequately represented on appropriate governmental boards and commissions, and its interests should be examined and fostered by a continuous research program.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have provided an important outlet for private capital by stimulating home building and low-rent housing projects. More new homes were built throughout the nation last year than in any year since 1929.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have fostered a well-balanced American merchant marine and the world's finest system of civil aeronautics, to promote our commerce and our national defense.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have steered a steady course between a bankruptcy-producing deflation and a thrift-destroying inflation, so that today the dollar is the most stable and sought-after currency in the world&#8212;a factor of immeasurable benefit in our foreign and domestic commerce.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall continue to oppose barriers which impede trade among the several states. We pledge our best efforts in strengthening our home markets, and to this end we favor the adjustment of freight rates so that no section or state will have undue advantage over any other.
             </p>
             <p>
              To encourage investment in productive enterprise, the tax-exempt privileges of future Federal, state and local bonds should be removed.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have enforced the anti-trust laws more vigorously than at any time in our history, thus affording the maximum protection to the competitive system.
             </p>
             <p>
              We favor strict supervision of all forms of the insurance business by the several states for the protection of policyholders and the public.
             </p>
             <p>
              The full force of our policies, by raising the national income by thirty billion dollars from the low of 1932, by encouraging vast reemployment, and by elevating the level of consumer demand, has quickened the flow of buying and selling through every artery of industry and trade.
             </p>
             <p>
              With mass purchasing power restored and many abuses eliminated, American business stands at the threshold of a great new era, richer in promise than any we have witnessed&#8212;an era of pioneering and progress beyond the present frontiers of economic activity&#8212;in transportation, in housing, in industrial expansion, and in the new utilization of the products of the farm and the factory.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall aid business in redeeming America's promise.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Electric Power
             </h3>
             <p>
              During the past seven years the Democratic Party has won the first major victories for the people of the nation in their generation-old contest with the power monopoly.
             </p>
             <p>
              These victories have resulted in the recognition of certain self evident principles and the realization of vast benefits by the people. These principles, long opposed by the Republican Party, are:
             </p>
             <p>
              That the power of falling water is a gift from God, and consequently belongs not to a privileged few, but to all the people, who are entitled to enjoy its benefits;
             </p>
             <p>
              That the people have the right through their government to develop their own power sites and bring low-cost electricity to their homes, farms and factories;
             </p>
             <p>
              That public utility holding companies must not be permitted to serve as the means by which a few men can pyramid stocks upon stocks for the sole purpose of controlling vast power empires.
             </p>
             <p>
              We condemn the Republican policies which permitted the victimizing of investors in the securities of private power corporations, and the exploitation of the people by unnecessarily high utility costs.
             </p>
             <p>
              We condemn the opposition of utility power interests which delayed for years the development of national defense projects in the Tennessee Valley, and which obstructed river basin improvements and other public projects bringing low-cost electric power to the people. The successful power developments in the Tennessee and Columbia River basins show the wisdom of the Democratic Party in establishing government-owned and operated hydro-electric plants in the interests of power and light consumers.
             </p>
             <p>
              Through these Democratic victories, whole regions have been revived and restored to prosperous habitation. Production costs have been reduced. Industries have been established which employ men and capital. Cheaper electricity has brought vast economic benefits to thousands of homes and communities.
             </p>
             <p>
              These victories of the people must be safeguarded. They will be turned to defeat if the Republican Party should be returned to power. We pledge our Party militantly to oppose every effort to encroach upon the inherent right of our people to be provided with this primary essential of life at the lowest possible cost.
             </p>
             <p>
              The nomination of a utility executive by the Republican Party as its presidential candidate raises squarely the issue, whether the nation's water power shall be used for all the people or for the selfish interests of a few. We accept that issue.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Developments of Western Resources
             </h3>
             <p>
              We take satisfaction in pointing out the incomparable development of the public land states under the wise and constructive legislation of this Administration. Mining has been revived, agriculture fostered, reclamation extended and natural resources developed as never before in a similar period. We pledge the continuance of such policies, based primarily on the expansion of opportunity for the people, as will encourage the full development, free from financial exploitation, of the great resources&#8212;mineral, agricultural, livestock, fishing and lumber&#8212;which the West affords.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Radio
             </h3>
             <p>
              Radio has become an integral part of the democratically accepted doctrine of freedom of speech, press, assembly and religion. We urge such legislative steps as may be required to afford the same protection from censorship that is now afforded the press under the Constitution of the United States.
             </p>
             <h3>
               We Must Strengthen Democracy By Improving the Welfare of the People
             </h3>
             <p>
              We place human resources first among the assets of a democratic society.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Unemployment
             </h3>
             <p>
              The Democratic Party wages war on unemployment, one of the gravest problems of our times, inherited at its worst from the last Republican administration. Since we assumed office, nine million additional persons have gained regular employment in normal private enterprise. All our policies&#8212;financial, industrial and agricultural&#8212;will continue to accelerate the rate of this progress.
             </p>
             <p>
              By public action, where necessary to supplement private reemployment, we have rescued millions from idleness that breeds weakness, and given them a real stake in their country's well being. We shall continue to recognize the obligation of Government to provide work for deserving workers who cannot be absorbed by private industry.
             </p>
             <p>
              We are opposed to vesting in the states and local authorities the control of Federally-financed work relief. We believe that this Republican proposal is a thinly disguised plan to put the unemployed back on the dole.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will continue energetically to direct our efforts toward the employment in private industry of all those willing to work, as well as the fullest employment of money and machines. This we pledge as our primary objective. To further implement this objective, we favor calling, under the direction of the President, a national unemployment conference of leaders of government, industry, labor and farm groups.
             </p>
             <p>
              There is work in our factories, mines, fields, forests and river basins, on our coasts, highways, railroads and inland waterways. There are houses to be built to shelter our people. Building a better America means work and a higher standard of living for every family, and a richer and more secure heritage for every American.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Social Security
             </h3>
             <p>
              The Democratic Party, which established social security for the nation, is dedicated to its extension. We pledge to make the Social Security Act increasingly effective, by covering millions of persons not now protected under its terms; by strengthening our unemployment insurance system and establishing more adequate and uniform benefits, through the Federal equalization fund principle; by progressively extending and increasing the benefits of the old-age and survivors insurance system, including protection of the permanently disabled; and by the early realization of a minimum pension for all who have reached the age of retirement and are not gainfully employed.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Health
             </h3>
             <p>
              Good health for all the people is a prime requisite of national preparedness in its broadest sense. We have advanced public health, industrial hygiene, and maternal and child care. We are coordinating the health functions of the Federal Government. We pledge to expand these efforts, and to provide more hospitals and health centers and better health protection wherever the need exists, in rural and urban areas, all through the co-operative efforts of the Federal, state and local governments, the medical, dental, nursing and other scientific professions, and the voluntary agencies.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Youth and Education
             </h3>
             <p>
              Today, when the youth of other lands is being sacrificed in war, this nation recognizes the full value of the sound youth program established by the Administration. The National Youth Administration and Civilian Conservation Corps have enabled our youth to complete their education, have maintained their health, trained them for useful citizenship, and aided them to secure employment.
             </p>
             <p>
              Our public works have modernized and greatly expanded the nation's schools. We have increased Federal aid for vocational education and rehabilitation, and undertaken a comprehensive program of defense-industry training. We shall continue to bring to millions of children, youths and adults, the educational and economic opportunities otherwise beyond their reach.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Slum-Clearance and Low-Rent Housing
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have launched a soundly conceived plan of loans and contributions to rid America of overcrowded slum dwellings that breed disease and crime, and to replace them by low-cost housing projects within the means of low-income families. We will extend and accelerate this plan not only in the congested city districts, but also in the small towns and farm areas, and we will make it a powerful arm of national defense by supplying housing for the families of enlisted personnel and for workers in areas where industry is expanding to meet defense needs.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Consumers
             </h3>
             <p>
              We are taking effective steps to insure that, in this period of stress, the cost of living shall not be increased by speculation and unjustified price rises.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Negroes
             </h3>
             <p>
              Our Negro citizens have participated actively in the economic and social advances launched by this Administration, including fair labor standards, social security benefits, health protection, work relief projects, decent housing, aid to education, and the rehabilitation of low-income farm families. We have aided more than half a million Negro youths in vocational training, education and employment. We shall continue to strive for complete legislative safeguards against discrimination in government service and benefits, and in the national defense forces. We pledge to uphold due process and the equal protection of the laws for every citizen, regardless of race, creed or color.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Veterans
             </h3>
             <p>
              We pledge to continue our policy of fair treatment of America's war veterans and their dependents, in just tribute to their sacrifices and their devotion to the cause of liberty.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Indians
             </h3>
             <p>
              We favor and pledge the enactment of legislation creating an Indian Claims Commission for the special purpose of entertaining and investigating claims presented by Indian groups, bands and tribes, in order that our Indian citizens may have their claims against the Government considered, adjusted, and finally settled at the earliest possible date.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Civil Service
             </h3>
             <p>
              We pledge the immediate extension of a genuine system of merit to all positions in the executive branch of the Federal Government except actual bona fide policy-making positions. The competitive method of selecting employes shall be improved until experience and qualification shall be the sole test in determining fitness for employment in the Federal service. Promotion and tenure in Federal service shall likewise depend upon fitness, experience and qualification. Arbitrary and unreasonable rules as to academic training shall be abolished, all to the end that a genuine system of efficiency and merit shall prevail throughout the entire Federal service.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Territories and District of Columbia
             </h3>
             <p>
              We favor a larger measure of self-government leading to statehood, for Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico. We favor the appointment of residents to office, and equal treatment of the citizens of each of these three territories. We favor the prompt determination and payment of any just claims by Indian and Eskimo citizens of Alaska against the United States.
             </p>
             <p>
              We also favor the extension of the right of suffrage to the people of the District of Columbia.
             </p>
             <h3>
               True First Line of Defense
             </h3>
             <p>
              We pledge to continue to stand guard on our true first line of defense&#8212;the security and welfare of the men, women and children of America.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Our Democratic Faith
             </h3>
             <p>
              Democracy is more than a political system for the government of a people. It is the expression of a people's faith in themselves as human beings. If this faith is permitted to die, human progress will die with it. We believe that a mechanized existence, lacking the spiritual quality of democracy, is intolerable to the free people of this country.
             </p>
             <p>
              We therefore pledge ourselves to fight, as our fathers fought, for the right of every American to enjoy freedom of religion, speech, press, assembly, petition, and security in his home.
             </p>
             <p>
              It is America's destiny, in these days of rampant despotism, to be the guardian of the world heritage of liberty and to hold aloft and aflame the torch of Western civilization.
             </p>
             <p>
              The Democratic Party rededicates itself to this faith in democracy, to the defense of the American system of government, the only system under which men are masters of their own souls, the only system under which the American people, composed of many races and creeds, can live and work, play and worship in peace, security and freedom.
             </p>
             <p>
              Firmly relying upon a continuation of the blessings of Divine Providence upon all our righteous endeavors to preserve forever the priceless heritage of American liberty and peace, we appeal to all the liberal-minded men and women of the nation to approve this platform and to go forward with us by wholeheartedly supporting the candidates who subscribe to the principles which it proclaims.
              </p>
  </chapter>
  </body>
</platform>
