<?xml version="1.0"?>
<platform>
  <party>Democratic</party>
  <year></year>
  <source></source>
  <body>
  <chapter>
             <p>
				 We hold this truth to be self-evident&#8212;that the test of a representative government is its ability to promote the safety and happiness of the people.
             </p>
             <p>
              We hold this truth to be self-evident&#8212;that 12 years of Republican leadership left our Nation sorely stricken in body, mind, and spirit; and that three years of Democratic leadership have put it back on the road to restored health and prosperity.
             </p>
             <p>
              We hold this truth to be self-evident&#8212;that 12 years of Republican surrender to the dictatorship of a privileged few have been supplanted by a Democratic leadership which has returned the people themselves to the places of authority, and has revived in them new faith and restored the hope which they had almost lost.
             </p>
             <p>
              We hold this truth to be self-evident&#8212;that this three-year recovery in all the basic values of life and the reestablishment of the American way of living has been brought about by humanizing the policies of the Federal Government as they affect the personal, financial, industrial, and agricultural well-being of the American people.
             </p>
             <p>
              We hold this truth to be self-evident&#8212;that government in a modern civilization has certain inescapable obligations to its citizens, among which are:
             </p>
             <p>
              (1) Protection of the family and the home.
             </p>
             <p>
              (2) Establishment of a democracy of opportunity for all the people.
             </p>
             <p>
              (3) Aid to those overtaken by disaster. These obligations, neglected through 12 years of the old leadership, have once more been recognized by American Government. Under the new leadership they will never be neglected.
             </p>
             <h3>
               For the Protection of the Family and the Home
             </h3>
             <p>
              (1) We have begun and shall continue the successful drive to rid our land of kidnappers and bandits. We shall continue to use the powers of government to end the activities of the malefactors of great wealth who defraud and exploit the people.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Savings and Investment
             </h3>
             <p>
              (2) We have safeguarded the thrift of our citizens by restraining those who would gamble with other peoples savings, by requiring truth in the sale of securities; by putting the brakes upon the use of credit for speculation; by outlawing the manipulation of prices in stock and commodity markets; by curbing the overweening power and unholy practices of utility holding companies; by insuring fifty million bank accounts.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Old Age and Social Security
             </h3>
             <p>
              (3) We have built foundations for the security of those who are faced with the hazards of unemployment and old age; for the orphaned, the crippled, and the blind. On the foundation of the Social Security Act we are determined to erect a structure of economic security for all our people, making sure that this benefit shall keep step with the ever-increasing capacity of America to provide a high standard of living for all its citizens.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Consumer
             </h3>
             <p>
              (4) We will act to secure to the consumer fair value, honest sales and a decreased spread between the price he pays and the price the producer receives.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Rural Electrification
             </h3>
             <p>
              (5) This administration has fostered power rate yardsticks in the Tennessee Valley and in several other parts of the Nation. As a result, electricity has been made available to the people at a lower rate. We will continue to promote plans for rural electrification and for cheap power by means of the yardstick method.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Housing
             </h3>
             <p>
              (6) We maintain that our people are entitled to decent, adequate housing at a price which they can afford. In the last three years, the Federal Government, having saved more than two million homes from foreclosure, has taken the first steps in our history to provide decent housing for people of meagre incomes. We believe every encouragement should be given to the building of new homes by private enterprise; and that the Government should steadily extend its housing program toward the goal of adequate housing for those forced through economic necessities to live in unhealthy and slum conditions.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Veterans
             </h3>
             <p>
              (7) We shall continue just treatment of our war veterans and their dependents.
             </p>
             <h3>
               For the Establishment of a Democracy of Opportunity
             </h3>
             <h3>
               Agriculture
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have taken the farmers off the road to ruin. We have kept our pledge to agriculture to use all available means to raise farm income toward its pre-war purchasing power. The farmer is no longer suffering from 15-cent corn, 3-cent hogs, 2 1/2-cent beef at the farm, 5-cent wool, 30-cent wheat, 5-cent cotton, and 8-cent sugar.
             </p>
             <p>
              By Federal legislation, we have reduced the farmer's indebtedness and doubled his net income. In cooperation with the States and through the varmers' own committees, we are restoring the fertility of his land and checking the erosion of his soil. We are bringing electricity and good roads to his home.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will continue to improve the soil conservation and domestic allotment program with payments to farmers.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will continue a fair-minded administration of agricultural laws, quick to recognize and meet new problems and conditions. We recognize the gravity of the evils of farm tenancy, and we pledge the full cooperation of the Government in the refinancing of farm indebtedness at the lowest possible rates of interest and over a long term of years.
             </p>
             <p>
              We favor the production of all the market will absorb, both at home and abroad, plus a reserve supply sufficient to insure fair prices to consumers; we favor judicious commodity loans on seasonal surpluses; and we favor assistance within Federal authority to enable farmers to adjust and balance production with demand, at a fair profit to the farmers.
             </p>
             <p>
              We favor encouragement of sound, practical farm co-operatives.
             </p>
             <p>
              By the purchase and retirement of ten million acres of sub-marginal land, and assistance to those attempting to eke out an existence upon it, we have made a good beginning toward proper land use and rural rehabilitation.
             </p>
             <p>
              The farmer has been returned to the road to freedom and prosperity. We will keep him on that road.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Labor
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have given the army of America's industrial workers something more substantial than the Republicans' dinner pail full of promises. We have increased the worker's pay and shortened his hours; we have undertaken to put an end to the sweated labor of his wife and children; we have written into the law of the land his right to collective bargaining and self-organization free from the interference of employers; we have provided Federal machinery for the peaceful settlement of labor disputes.
             </p>
             <p>
              We will continue to protect the worker and we will guard his rights, both as wage-earner and consumer, in the production and consumption of all commodities, including coal and water power and other natural resource products.
             </p>
             <p>
              The worker has been returned to the road to freedom and prosperity. We will keep him on that road.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Business
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have taken the American business man out of the red. We have saved his bank and given it a sounder foundation; we have extended credit; we have lowered interest rates; we have undertaken to free him from the ravages of cutthroat competition.
             </p>
             <p>
              The American business man has been returned to the road to freedom and prosperity. We will keep him on that road.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Youth
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have aided youth to stay in school; given them constructive occupation; opened the door to opportunity which 12 years of Republican neglect had closed.
             </p>
             <p>
              Our youth have been returned to the road to freedom and prosperity. We will keep them on that road.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Monopoly and Concentration of Economic Power
             </h3>
             <p>
              Monopolies and the concentration of economic power, the creation of Republican rule and privilege, continue to be the master of the producer, the exploiter of the consumer, and the enemy of the independent operator. This is a problem challenging the unceasing effort of untrammeled public officials in every branch of the Government. We pledge vigorously and fearlessly to enforce the criminal and civil provisions of the existing anti-trust laws, and to the extent that their effectiveness has been weakened by new corporate devices or judicial construction, we propose by law to restore their efficacy in stamping out monopolistic practices and the concentration of economic power.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Aid to Those Overtaken By Disaster
             </h3>
             <p>
              We have aided and will continue to aid those who have been visited by widespread drought and floods, and have adopted a Nation-wide flood-control policy.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Unemployment
             </h3>
             <p>
              We believe that unemployment is a national problem, and that it is an inescapable obligation of our Government to meet it in a national way.
             </p>
             <p>
              Due to our stimulation of private business, more than five million people have been reemployed; and we shall continue to maintain that the first objective of a program of economic security is maximum employment in private industry at adequate wages. Where business fails to supply such employment, we believe that work at prevailing wages should be provided in cooperation with State and local governments on useful public projects, to the end that the national wealth may be increased, the skill and energy of the worker may be utilized, his morale maintained, and the unemployed assured the opportunity to earn the necessities of life.
             </p>
             <h3>
               The Constitution
             </h3>
             <p>
              The Republican platform proposes to meet many pressing national problems solely by action of the separate States. We know that drought, dust storms, floods, minimum wages, maximum hours, child labor, and working conditions in industry, monopolistic and unfair business practices cannot be adequately handled exclusively by 48 separate State legislatures, 48 separate State administrations, and 48 separate State courts. Transactions and activities which inevitably overflow State boundaries call for both State and Federal treatment.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have sought and will continue to seek to meet these problems through legislation within the Constitution.
             </p>
             <p>
              If these problems cannot be effectively solved by legislation within the Constitution, we shall seek such clarifying amendment as will assure to the legislatures of the several States and to the Congress of the United States, each within its proper jurisdiction, the power to enact those laws which the State and Federal legislatures, within their respective spheres, shall find necessary, in order adequately to regulate commerce, protect public health and safety and safeguard economic security. Thus we propose to maintain the letter and spirit of the Constitution.
             </p>
             <h3>
               The Merit System in Government
             </h3>
             <p>
              For the protection of government itself and promotion of its efficiency, we pledge the immediate extension of the merit system through the classified civil service&#8212;which was first established and fostered under Democratic auspices&#8212;to all non-policy-making positions in the Federal service.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall subject to the civil service law all continuing positions which, because of the emergency, have been exempt from its operation.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Civil Liberties
             </h3>
             <p>
              We shall continue to guard the freedom of speech, press, radio, religion and assembly which our Constitution guarantees; with equal rights to all and special privileges to none.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Government Finance
             </h3>
             <p>
              The Administration has stopped deflation, restored values and enabled business to go ahead with confidence.
             </p>
             <p>
              When national income shrinks, government income is imperilled. In reviving national income, we have fortified government finance. We have raised the public credit to a position of unsurpassed security. The interest rate on Government bonds has been reduced to the lowest point in twenty eight years. The same Government bonds which in 1932 sold under 83 are now selling over 104.
             </p>
             <p>
              We approve the objective of a permanently sound currency so stabilized as to prevent the former wide fluctuations in value which injured in turn producers, debtors, and property owners on the one hand, and wage-earners and creditors on the other, a currency which will permit full utilization of the country's resources. We assert that today we have the soundest currency in the world.
             </p>
             <p>
              We are determined to reduce the expenses of government. We are being aided therein by the recession in unemployment. As the requirements of relief decline and national income advances, an increasing percentage of Federal expenditures can and will be met from current revenues, secured from taxes levied in accordance with ability to pay. Our retrenchment, tax and recovery programs thus reflect our firm determination to achieve a balanced budget and the reduction of the national debt at the earliest possible moment.
             </p>
             <h3>
               Foreign Policy
             </h3>
             <p>
              In our relationship with other nations, this Government will continue to extend the policy of the Good Neighbor. We reaffirm our opposition to war as an instrument of national policy, and declare that disputes between nations should be settled by peaceful means. We shall continue to observe a true neutrality in the disputes of others; to be prepared, resolutely to resist aggression against ourselves; to work for peace and to take the profits out of war; to guard against being drawn, by political commitments, international banking or private trading, into any war which may develop anywhere.
             </p>
             <p>
              We shall continue to foster the increase in our foreign trade which has been achieved by this administration; to seek by mutual agreement the lowering of those tariff barriers, quotas and embargoes which have been raised against our exports of agricultural and industrial products; but continue as in the past to give adequate protection to our farmers and manufacturers against unfair competition or the dumping on our shores of commodities and goods produced abroad by cheap labor or subsidized by foreign governments.
             </p>
             <h3>
               The Issue
             </h3>
             <p>
              The issue in this election is plain. The American people are called upon to choose between a Republican administration that has and would again regiment them in the service of privileged groups and a Democratic administration dedicated to the establishment of equal economic opportunity for all our people.
             </p>
             <p>
              We have faith in the destiny of our nation. We are sufficiently endowed with natural resources and with productive capacity to provide for all a quality of life that meets the standards of real Americanism.
             </p>
             <p>
              Dedicated to a government of liberal American principles, we are determined to oppose equally, the despotism of Communism and the menace of concealed Fascism.
             </p>
             <p>
              We hold this final truth to be self-evident&#8212;that the interests, the security and the happiness of the people of the United States of America can be perpetuated only under democratic government as conceived by the founders of our nation.
              </p>
  </chapter>
  </body>
</platform>
